. >> GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYBODY
WELCOME TO THE FEBRUARY THIRD, 2026 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL? >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISE FOR CHAN CHIN CHAN PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHAN
PRESENT SUPERVISOR DORSI DORSI PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER PRESENT SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN PRESENT MANDEL MAN PRESENT SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR PRESENT SUPERVISOR SADR SADR PRESENT
SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHERRELL PRESENT SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR WONG WONG PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT
ALL MEMBERS ARE PRESENT. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT
WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL HOMELAND OF THE RAMA TO SALONI
WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL INHABITANTS OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO PENINSULA AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS
LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE
RAMAKRISHNA LONI HAVE NEVER CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR
RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS
WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL
TERRITORY AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM
LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOMELANDS.
WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS,
ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE ROMITA SHALINI COMMUNITY AND BY
AFFIRMING THEIR SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
>> COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE? I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG
OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND TO THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH
IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD ,INDIVISIBLE, WITH LIBERTY
AND JUSTICE FOR ALL. >> ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD I
WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT S.F. GOV TV TODAY THAT IS
ESPECIALLY KALEENA MENDOZA. THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR
MEETINGS AND MAKE THE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE
PUBLIC ONLINE. >> MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY
COMMUNICATIONS? YES, MR. PRESIDENT.
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WOULD LIKE TO
WELCOME YOU ALL TO BE HERE IN ATTENDANCE IN THE BOARD'S
LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER WHICH HAS ROOM TO 50 ON THE SECOND FLOOR
OF CITY HALL. WHEN YOU CANNOT BE HERE THE
PROCEEDING IS AIRING LIVE ON AS OF GOVEE TV'S CHANNEL 26.
OR YOU CAN VIEW THE LIVE STREAM AT W W W DOT S.F. GOVEE TV DOT
ORG IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO SUBMIT YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT AND WRITING
YOU CAN DO SO BY SENDING AN EMAIL TO B.
>> S AT S F CAVALIERE OR YOU CAN USE THE U.S. POSTAL SERVICE
ADDRESS YOUR ENVELOPE TO THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON B GOOD PLACE CITY HALL
ROOM 244 SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA 94102 IF YOU WOULD
LIKE TO MAKE A REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION FOR A FUTURE
MEETING UNDER THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT OR TO
REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE, PLEASE CONTACT THE CLERK'S
OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE BY CALLING
(415) 554-5184. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. >> LET'S GO TO APPROVAL OF OUR
CONSENT AGENDA. PLEASE CALL ITEMS ONE THROUGH
EIGHT TOGETHER. >> ITEMS ONE THROUGH EIGHT ARE
ON CONSENT. THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED TO
BE ROUTINE. IF A MEMBER OBJECTS AN ITEM MAY
BE REMOVED AND CONSIDERED SEPARATELY.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE CONSENT AGENDA.
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR OF MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR MENDELSON HI
MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUTER SADR
I AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THESE ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK
LET'S GO TO UNFINISHED BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEMS NINE AND TEN
TOGETHER ITEMS NINE AND TEN COMPRISE TWO ORDINANCES THAT
PERTAIN TO THE CAPITAL EXPENDITURE PLAN AND THE
GENERAL OBLIGATION BOND. ITEM NINE AMENDS THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO CHANGE THE REPORTING REQUIREMENT FOR
THE CAPITAL EXPENDITURE PLANS FROM ODD YEARS TO EVEN YEARS
WITH THE NEXT REPORT DUE MARCH 1ST, 2028 AND ITEM TEN THIS
ORDINANCE PURSUANT TO THE CALIFORNIA GOVERNMENT CODE.
THIS MATTER SHALL REQUIRE A VOTE OF TWO THIRDS OR EIGHT
VOTES OF ALL MEMBERS TO APPROVE FOR FINAL PASSAGE OF THIS
ORDINANCE TODAY THIS ORDINANCE CALLS FOR AND PROVIDES FOR A
SPECIAL ELECTION TO BE HELD ON TUESDAY JUNE 2ND, 2026 TO
SUBMIT TO THE SAN FRANCISCO VOTERS A PROPOSITION TO INCUR
UP TO 535 MILLION IN BOND DEBT TO FINANCE THE ASR FACILITIES
AND ADDITIONALLY TO CONSOLIDATE THE SPECIAL ELECTION WITH THE
GENERAL SECTION TO ESTABLISH THE ELECTION PRECINCTS VOTING
PLACES AND OFFICERS FOR THE ELECTION SUPERVISOR WONG
SPEAKING TO ITEM TEN PREPARING FOR EARTHQUAKES IS ONE OF THE
MOST BASIC RESPONSIBILITIES WE HAVE AS THE CITY ESPECIALLY
WHEN IT COMES TO PROTECTING LIVES AND ENSURING OUR PUBLIC
SAFETY SYSTEM REMAINS OPERATIONAL.
ACCORDING TO THE US GEOLOGICAL SURVEY THERE IS A 72% CHANCE OF
A MAGNITUDE 6.7 OR GREATER EARTHQUAKE IN OUR REGION WITH
THE NEXT 30 YEARS. THIS IS NOT A HYPOTHETICAL
RISK. IT IS SOMETHING SAN FRANCISCO
MUST BE READY FOR THE TERRIBLE POLICE STATION WILL BE ONE OF
THE TWO STATIONS IN THE CITY THAT THE CITY PRIORITIZED FOR
FUNDING FOR THIS BOND. THE STATION SERVES MUCH OF THE
WEST SIDE AND DISTRICT FOUR. IT HAS OVER 110 YEARS OLD
AND WAS BUILT LONG BEFORE MODERN SEISMIC STANDARDS IN A
MAJOR EARTHQUAKE. THE STATION IS EXPECTED TO BE
SEVERELY DAMAGED OR POTENTIALLY UNUSABLE IF THE TERRIBLE
STATION WERE TAKEN OFFLINE, DISTRICT FOUR AND SURROUNDING
NEIGHBORHOODS WOULD FACE SLOWER EMERGENCY RESPONSE TIMES
AND DELAYED SERVICE AT THE EXACT MOMENT RESIDENTS WOULD
NEED HELP THE MOST. >> RETROFITTING THE STATION IS
ABOUT PROTECTING THE OFFICERS AND STAFF WHO WORK THERE
AND ENSURING THE SAN FRANCISCO POLICE DEPARTMENT CAN FULLY
SUPPORT PUBLIC SAFETY NEEDS AND ASSIST RESIDENTS
IMMEDIATELY FOLLOWING A MAJOR EARTHQUAKE.
>> THE EASIER GABON CUBAN ALLOWS US TO MAKE RESPONSIBLE
PREVENTATIVE INVESTMENTS SO CRITICAL PUBLIC SAFETY
INFRASTRUCTURE REMAINS FUNCTIONAL WHEN IT MATTERS MOST
FOR DISTRICT FOUR THIS IS ABOUT READINESS, RESILIENCE
AND EQUITY FOR THE WEST SIDE. EARTHQUAKES DON'T GIVE WARNINGS
. STRENGTHENING TRAVEL STATION
ENSURES OUR OFFICERS CAN REPORT FOR DUTY AND OUR RESIDENTS CAN
GET HELP WHEN THEY NEED IT MOST.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR KONG MADAM
MADAM CLERK LET'S TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 11.
>> ITEM 11 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE BUILDING CODE TO
CREATE A PERMIT AND PERMITTING PROCESS FOR HYDROGEN FUELING
STATION EQUIPMENT INSTALLATION AND TO AFFIRM THE SEQUENCE
DETERMINATION PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 11 SUPERVISOR
WALTON WILTON EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHEN
CHEN NO SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN RIGHT RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER I AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL I THERE ARE NINE EYES AND TWO NOS WITH SUPERVISORS
CHAN AND FIELDER VOTING NO THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED
MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 12 ITEM 12 THIS IS A CHARTER
AMENDMENT FIRST DRAFT TO AMEND THE CHARTER OF THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO TO CHANGE THE CURRENT TWO YEAR
LIMITS TO TERM LIMITS FOR THE OFFICE OF MAYOR AND THE OFFICE
OF MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FROM CONSECUTIVE
TERM LIMITS TO LIFETIME TERM LIMITS AT AN ELECTION TO BE
HELD ON JUNE 2ND, 2026 SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU SO
MUCH PRESIDENT MADAM AND I JUST WANTED TO ASK A QUESTION TO THE
CITY ATTORNEY I KNOW THERE IS A STATE LAW IN PLACE RIGHT NOW
THAT STATES THAT IF YOU WANT TO CHANGE THE TERM LIMITS FOR
BODIES LIKE THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS OR FOR MAYOR, YOU
CAN IT SHOULD ONLY APPLY PROSPECTIVELY AND NOT APPLY FOR
MEMBERS WHO HAVE CURRENTLY OR SERVED IN THE PAST AND THAT
STATUTE IS CALIFORNIA GOVERNMENT CODE SECTION 36502
AND IT HAS BEEN IN EFFECT SINCE 1996 AND IT SAYS ANY PROPOSAL
TO LIMIT THE NUMBER OF TERMS AN ELECTED MAY SERVE SHALL APPLY
PROSPECTIVELY ONLY. AND I JUST WANTED TO CHECK
IN WITH THE CITY ATTORNEY ABOUT THAT STATE LAW AND HOW THAT
APPLIES TO SAN FRANCISCO. >> MR. CITY ATTORNEY GOOD
AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY BRAD RUSTY.
UNDER CURRENT CASE LAW THE STATUTE THAT SUPERVISOR WALTON
MENTIONED DOES NOT APPLY TO SAN FRANCISCO, THE CITY'S HOME RULE
AUTHORITY UNDER THE STATE CONSTITUTION AS A CHARTER CITY
AUTHORIZES THE CITY TO DETERMINE HOW TERM LIMITS ARE
APPLIED AND THIS WOULD INCLUDE APPLYING THE PROPOSED MEASURE
LIFETIME TERM LIMITS BOTH TO CURRENT OFFICEHOLDERS AND PAST
OFFICEHOLDERS. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK,
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 12 SUPERVISOR WALTON NO WALTON.
NO SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MENDELSON NO MANDEL MAN NO SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
THERE ARE SEVEN EYES AND FOUR NOS WITH SUPERVISORS WALTON
CHAN CHIN AND MANDEL MEN VOTING NO THE CHARTER AMENDMENT IS
ORDERED SUBMITTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 13 ITEM 13
THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE BUSINESS AND TAX
REGULATIONS CODE TO REVISE HOW THE AULT OR THE ACCESS LINE TAX
APPLIES TO THE VOIP THE VOICE OVER INTERNET PROTOCOL SERVICES
TO REQUIRE COLLECTION AND REMITTANCE OF THE ALT ON
VOIP SERVICES USING THE LOWER OF THE NUMBER OF TELEPHONE
NUMBERS PROVIDED TO A SUBSCRIBER AND THE NUMBER OF
CALLS THAT THE SUBSCRIBER CAN MAKE AND OR RECEIVE AT THE SAME
TIME USING THOSE TELEPHONE NUMBERS PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON
ITEM 13 SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WONG
EYES SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN MAN WOMAN
I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I THERE ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 14 AND 15 TOGETHER ITEMS 14 AND 15
ARE TWO ITEMS THAT AUTHORIZE THE OFFICE OF THE MAYOR TO
ACCEPT AND EXPEND GRANTS FOR ITEM 14.
THIS IS 7 MILLION A $7 MILLION GRANT FROM BLOOMBERG
PHILANTHROPIES TO FUND THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF INNOVATION
JANUARY 1ST, 2026 THROUGH DECEMBER 31ST 2028 TO APPROVE
THE ASSOCIATED GRANT AGREEMENT UNDER CHARTER SECTION 9.118
AND TO AMEND THE ANNUAL SALARY ORDINANCE FILE NUMBER 250590
FOR FISCAL YEARS 20 2526 AND 20 2627 TO PROVIDE FOR THE
CREATION OF FOUR GRANT FUNDED FULL TIME POSITIONS IN THE
OFFICE OF THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR WITH ONE POSITION
IN EACH OF THE FOLLOWING CLASSES 093110531054 AND 1043
AND FOUR ITEM 15 THIS RESOLUTION RETROACTIVELY
AUTHORIZES THE MAYOR'S OFFICE TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND A $700,000
GRANT FROM TIPPING POINT COMMUNITY FOR THE ESTABLISHMENT
OF A DIRECTOR OF STRATEGIC PARTNERSHIPS TO ADVANCE PUBLIC
PRIVATE PARTNERSHIP INITIATIVES ALIGNED WITH MAYORAL PRIORITY
FOR THE TERM JANUARY 20TH, 2026 THROUGH JULY 1ST, 2028.
>> CHAIR CHAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDARIN COLLEAGUES
MY APOLOGIES. THERE WAS AN OVERSIGHT AT THE
BUDGET COMMITTEE FOR ITEM 14 FOR THE BLOOMBERG GRANT THAT IS
SHOULD BE LISTED OR AMENDED TO BE RETROACTIVE AND THEREFORE I
WOULD LIKE TO MOVE TO AMEND ITEM 14 TO INCLUDE THE
RETROACTIVITY FOR THIS ACCEPT AND EXPAND GRANT.
>> IS THERE A SECOND? SECOND BY DORSEY I THINK WE CAN
TAKE THAT MOTION WITHOUT OBJECTION.
AND THEN I THINK WE CAN TAKE THESE ITEMS.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCES PASSED
ON FIRST READING AND THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 16 THROUGH 18 TOGETHER
ITEM 16 THROUGH 18 OR 3 RESOLUTIONS THAT AUTHORIZE THE
RECREATION AND PARKS DEPARTMENT TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND GRANTS FOR
INDIA BASIN SHORELINE PARK PROJECT.
ITEM 16 IS FOR APPROXIMATELY A $1.1 MILLION GRANT FROM THE SAN
FRANCISCO BAY RESTORATION AUTHORITY.
MEASURE AA GRANT FOR A TO ENTER INTO THE ASSOCIATED GRANT
AGREEMENT THAT REQUIRES THE CONTINUED OPERATION OF THE
PROPERTY FOR PUBLIC RECREATION FOR A 20 YEAR TERM UPON PROJECT
COMPLETION. ITEM 17 IS FOR A $2 MILLION
GRANT FROM THE UNITED STATES ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY
FOR THE BROWNFIELD CLEANUP PROGRAM TO SUPPORT ENVIRONMENT
REMEDIATION AND PARK REDEVELOPMENT THROUGH TO AN
ESTIMATED END DATE OCTOBER 1ST, 2025 TO OCTOBER 31ST, 2029
AND FOR ITEM 18 THIS IS FOR AN APPROXIMATE $3 MILLION GRANT
INCREASE FROM THE CALIFORNIA STATE COASTAL CONSERVANCY FOR A
NEW TOTAL GRANT AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 8.6 MILLION FOR
THE PARKS REDEVELOPMENT PROJECT.
>> LET'S TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 19 ITEM 19 THIS IS A
RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE 10TH AMENDMENT TO THE CONTRACT
BETWEEN THE MUNICIPAL TRANSPORTATION AGENCY
AND TEXACO LLC FOR SERVICES RELATED TO THE TOWING, STORAGE
AND DISPOSAL OF ABANDONED AND ILLEGALLY PARKED VEHICLES.
TO INCREASE THE CONTRACT AMOUNT BY 22.1 MILLION FOR A TOTAL
CONTRACT AMOUNT OF 158.8 MILLION AND TO EXTEND THE
CONTRACT TERM BY NINE MONTHS WITH UP TO SIX ADDITIONAL ONE
MONTH EXTENSIONS FOR A POTENTIAL NEW TERM APRIL 1ST
2016 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2027. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 20.
>> ITEM 20 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO ESTABLISH THE SAN FRANCISCO
DOWNTOWN REVITALIZATION AND ECONOMIC RECOVERY FINANCING
DISTRICT TO APPROVE THE DOWNTOWN REVITALIZATION FUND
FINANCING PLAN TO INCLUDE THE DIVISION OF TAXES SET FORTH
THEREIN AND DOCUMENTS AND ACTIONS RELATED THERETO
AND TO AUTHORIZE THE FILING OF A JUDICIAL VALIDATION ACTION.
>> SUPERVISOR FIELDER. >> THANKS PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN,
COLLEAGUES UNLIKE MOST OTHER TAX INCREMENT FINANCING
DISTRICTS WHICH NORMALLY FUND PROGRAMS LIKE AFFORDABLE
HOUSING, UTILITIES OR PUBLIC INFRASTRUCTURE FOR THE PUBLIC
GOOD, THIS PLAN INSTEAD DIVERTS 610 MILLION IN TAXPAYER REVENUE
INTO PRIVATE HANDS TO USE FOR MARKET RATE DEVELOPMENTS.
>> FURTHERMORE, THIS PLAN ALSO EXEMPTS THE FIRST ONE POINT
5,000,000FT2 OF THE CONVERSIONS FROM THE CITY'S AFFORDABILITY
REQUIREMENTS AND ACCORDING TO THE VLA WOULD CREATE AN
INCENTIVE FOR THESE PROPERTIES TO BE DEVELOPED AS LUXURY
APARTMENTS THAT WILL BE UNAFFORDABLE TO MOST OF THE
CITY'S WORKING CLASS RESIDENTS. GIVEN THE CITY'S BUDGET
AND HOUSING AND AFFORDABILITY CRISES, IT IS HIGH TIME WE
START PRIVATIZING PROFITS AND SOCIALIZING COSTS
SUBSIDIZING PRIVATE DEVELOPERS AT THE EXPENSE OF SAN FRANCISCO
TAXPAYERS OURS. BECAUSE OF THIS I'LL BE VOTING
AGAINST THIS RESOLUTION. SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MANDELMAN, I VOTED IN SUPPORT OF THIS AT THE
BUDGET COMMITTEE WITH THE EXPECTATION THAT I WILL HAVE A
LIST OF THE 48 PROPERTIES THAT CAN BE BENEFITED FROM THIS TAX
INCREMENT. AND AS OF NOW AT 2:20 P.M. AT
THE BOARD MEETING I HAVE YET TO RECEIVE THE SPECIFIC LOTS
AND ADDRESSES OF THE PROPERTIES OF THE 48 PROPERTIES THAT
SHOULD THEY ANTICIPATED THEY WILL BE RECEIVED AS BENEFITS.
IT IS NOT CLEAR TO ME WHICH 48 PROPERTIES WILL THEN RECEIVE
THIS TAX INCREMENT IS NOT TRANSPARENT.
>> LOOK WE ALREADY WAY IN THE SAKE OF REVITALIZING DOWNTOWN
WE FIRST WAIVE THE IMPACT FEE FOR ANY PROPERTY CONVERTING
FROM COMMERCIAL TO RESIDENTIAL AND THEN WE ALSO HAVE WAIVED
INCLUSIONARY REQUIREMENTS. BUT THANKS TO SUPERVISOR RYAN
CHEN THAT WE WERE ABLE TO CAP IT AT I BELIEVE WHAT WAS A
77,000 SQUARE FOOTAGE THAT WAS SUPPOSED TO YIELD 14,000
HOUSING UNITS. NOW WE ARE GOING TO GIVE AWAY
OUR TAX INCREMENT TO THESE SPECIFIC 48 PROPERTIES WHICH AS
INDICATED BY THE BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYST QUITE A
BIT OF CHUNK OF MONEY THAT PROJECTING AT POTENTIALLY A
$610 MILLION OVER 45 YEARS TIME.
CLEARLY WE CAN'T BE SURE HOW THAT IS.
WHAT WOULD REALLY BE DIFFERENT LIKE IN A DEFINITE TERM TO
EMPOWER GENERAL FUND. WE SEE THAT THERE COULD BE A
VARIANCE BETWEEN NEGATIVE TO POSITIVE X SIGNIFICANTLY
POSITIVE TAX REVENUE IMPACT. SO AND WITHOUT THE TRANSPARENCY
OF THAT 48 PROPERTIES IT IS DIFFICULT FOR ME TO TELL WHAT
IS HAPPENING WITH THE OFFICE OF ECONOMIC AND WORKFORCE
DEVELOPMENT HERE. THE RELATIONSHIP AND THE
CONVERSATIONS ARE NOT CLEAR TO ME HOW WE CAME TO THE
CONCLUSIONS OF 48 PROPERTIES WITHOUT KNOWING SPECIFICALLY
WHICH 48 AND TO SIMPLY GIVE AWAY WAY TAX DOLLARS
AND BENEFITS WITHOUT KNOWING WHICH 48 PROPERTIES WILL BE
BENEFITING. MEANING BY CONCLUSION THE
POTENTIALLY 48 OR MORE OR LESS PROPERTY OWNERS THAT COULD BE
BENEFITING FROM THIS TAX INCREMENT.
AND WITH THAT REGRETTABLY I WILL BE VOTING AGAINST THIS
MEASURE TODAY. THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU PRESIDENT MENEM AND YOU KNOW
THIS THIS ITEM I KNOW WAS DISCUSSED AT THE BUDGET
COMMITTEE AND DID MOVE OUT WITH RECOMMENDATION.
AND I WOULD CERTAINLY WELCOME MORE INFORMATION ON THOSE
SPECIFIC PROPERTIES BUT I WAS ALWAYS UNDER THE IMPRESSION
THAT THOSE PROPERTIES WERE AN EXERCISE.
THERE'S NOTHING IN HERE WHERE WE'RE ASSIGNING INCENTIVES TO A
SPECIFIC PROPERTIES BUT THOSE WERE ALWAYS AN EXERCISE
IN LOOKING AT THE SPACES AND BUILDINGS DOWNTOWN THAT
WOULD FIT THE CRITERIA PUT FORTH IN THIS PACKAGE AND THAT
HAS ALWAYS BEEN MY EXPECTATION AND I KNOW HOW IT'S BEEN
PRESENTED. >> BUT I DO WANT TO NOTE THAT
THIS GOES BACK THE GROUNDWORK FOR THIS WAS LAID AT THE STATE
LEVEL BY THE FORMER ASSEMBLYMEMBER PHIL TING
AND YOU KNOW, SO MUCH OF WHAT WE'RE LOOKING AT HERE WAS SET
OUT IN STATE LEGISLATION. I WOULD CERTAINLY WELCOME MORE
AFFORDABLE HOUSING BUT I DO, YOU KNOW, THINK WE HAVE A
CHOICE HERE AND WHEN WE'RE LOOKING AT THIS BILL AND WHEN
WE'RE LOOKING AT DOWNTOWN IN THESE SPACES, IT IS A CHOICE
BETWEEN EMPTY OFFICES AND SPACE FOR NEW HOMES AND WELCOMING
RESIDENTS DOWNTOWN. I THINK THAT'S THE CHOICE
BEFORE US TODAY. IT'S WHY I'M SUPPORTING THIS
AND I JUST WANT TO EMPHASIZE THAT, YOU KNOW, WE HAVE TAKEN
SOME INITIATIVES HERE WHEN WHEN IT COMES TO THE DOWNTOWN
EFFORTS TO CONVERT OFFICES TO HOUSING BUT CLEARLY NOT ENOUGH
. CLEARLY WHAT WE'VE DONE SO FAR
IS NOT WORKING. I MEAN YOU LOOK AT EVERY OTHER
CITY AROUND THE COUNTRY AND WE ARE JUST SO FAR BEHIND.
I MEAN YOU LOOK AT YOU CAN JUST PULL ALL THESE NAMES OUT.
CHARLOTTE, ATLANTA, CHICAGO, PITTSBURGH, OMAHA, DENVER.
I MEAN ALMOST EVERY SINGLE CITY OF ANY SIGNIFICANCE IS IS AHEAD
OF US WHEN YOU LOOK AT THESE CONVERSIONS.
AND I THINK WE HAVE TO DO MORE AND THAT'S WHY I'M SUPPORTING
THIS SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN.
I'M A MEMBER OF THE DOWNTOWN REVITALIZATION FINANCING
DISTRICT BOARD AND BY NOW I'VE SPOKEN SEVERAL TIMES ON THIS.
I'LL TRY TO BE BRIEFER THAN USUAL.
I'M AN ENTHUSIASTIC SUPPORTER OR SUPPORTER OF THIS PLAN.
LIKE MOST PUBLIC POLICY INNOVATIONS I KNOW THAT
REASONABLE MINDS MAY DISAGREE AND MY RESPECT AND AFFECTION
FOR MY COLLEAGUES WHO DISAGREE IS UNDIMINISHED BY OUR DEBATE
HERE IN MY VIEW THE IMPERATIVE REFLECTED IN THE DOWNTOWN
DISTRICT FINANCING PLAN ISN'T SOLELY ECONOMIC REVITALIZATION
AS AN ADAPTIVE REUSE PLAN. THIS IS ALSO A ONCE IN A
LIFETIME OPPORTUNITY FOR US TO CORRECT 20TH CENTURY LAND USE
DECISIONS THAT CONTEMPLATED 9 TO 5 NEIGHBORHOODS AND BRING
THEM INTO THE 21ST CENTURY AS MORE VIBRANT AND DIVERSE 24
SEVEN NEIGHBORHOODS. I'M LUCKY TO REPRESENT SOME OF
THOSE 21ST CENTURY NEIGHBORHOODS AND I THINK THEY
ARE DRIVING A LOT OF OUR ECONOMIC ACTIVITY NOW.
I THINK WE SHOULD DO MORE OF THAT AS AN ADAPTIVE REUSE PLAN.
IT WILL ENABLE US TO PRESERVE AND REPURPOSE BUILDINGS THAT
ARE PART OF OUR CITY'S RICH CULTURAL HERITAGE DONE RIGHT.
I THINK THIS PLAN WILL HELP FULFILL A VERSION OF 21ST
CENTURY URBANISM THAT REIMAGINED OUR DOWNTOWN AS A
REINVIGORATED, THRIVING NEIGHBORHOOD THAT'S MIXED USE
AND MIXED INCOME WITH MORE RESIDENTS, MORE COMMUTERS, MORE
SHOPPERS, MORE VISITORS AND MORE AMENITIES TO SERVE
THEM. I ALSO THINK THIS PLAN BALANCES
THE NEED FOR AN EFFECTIVE FINANCING TOOL WITH CRITICAL
GUARDRAILS. THE PROGRAM ITSELF IS TIME
LIMITED IT WILL SUNSET IN 2032 ALL PROJECTS SEEKING THIS
BENEFIT WILL COME BEFORE THE DISTRICT BOARD FOR APPROVAL
AND THE BOARD IS REQUIRED TO PUBLISH AN ANNUAL REPORT.
SO WE'LL BE ABLE TO CLOSELY FOLLOW THE FISCAL IMPACT OF THE
PROGRAM AND I LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING WITH MY COLLEAGUES ON
THE DISTRICT BOARD TO ENSURE THAT WE'RE SUPPORTING THESE
MUCH NEEDED CONVERSION PROJECTS WHILE EXERCISING OUR FISCAL
OVERSIGHT AUTHORITY. AND WITH THAT I HOPE THAT WE
CAN HAVE MAJORITY SUPPORT OF OUR COLLEAGUES.
>> SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU FOR PRESENT COLLEAGUE AGAIN
EARLY LAST YEAR ONE OF MY VERY FIRST FALL AS A NEW SUPERVISOR
WAS TO AUTHORIZE TO WAIVING OF INCLUSIONARY REQUIREMENTS
AND IMPACT FEES FOR DOWNTOWN OFFICE TO RESIDENTIAL
CONVERSIONS AT A TIME. I WAS ALSO VERY CONCERNED THAT
OUR DESIRE TO STIMULATE NEW DEVELOPMENT IN THE DOWNTOWN
AREA WE WERE SACRIFICING THE ECONOMIC RECOVERY OF OUR LOWER
INCOME RESIDENTS AND OUR WORKERS.
>> WHEN THAT LEGISLATION WAS PASSED I WAS TOLD BY THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE THAT THEY WOULD MEET WITH COMMUNITY LEADERS TO
DISCUSS STRATEGIES TO ADVANCE AFFORDABLE HOUSING
AND COMMUNITY STABILIZATION GOALS IN THE VIBRANT YET
VULNERABLE COMMUNITIES IN THE DOWNTOWN AREA TODAY I'M NOT
AWARE THAT THIS CONVERSATION HAVE HAPPENED.
>> I'M NOT COMFORTABLE AUTHORIZING ADDITIONAL
LEGISLATION THAT FURTHER SACRIFICES OUT AFFORDABLE
HOUSING AND COMMUNITY STABILIZATION GOALS ESPECIALLY
WHEN THEY INVOLVE ADDITIONAL PUBLIC FUNDS.
>> THE 5% REQUIREMENT FOR BELOW MARKET RATE UNITS IS
IN RESPONSIBLE AND IT GOES AGAINST OUR STATED GOALS OF
WORKING TOWARDS A MORE AFFORDABLE CITY IDEALLY FOR US
THAT WE HAVE ADOPTED IN A CITY HAVE HIGHER INCLUSIONARY RATES
AND DOWNTOWN SHOULD NOT BE AN EXCEPTION.
I AM SUPPORTIVE OF OUR DOWNTOWN RECOVERY STRATEGY THAT IT'S
MORE BALANCED IT BY DELIVERING NEW HOUSING WHILE ENSURING THAT
A FAIR RETURN FOR AFFORDABLE HOMES UNITS.
>> OTHERWISE WE HAVE A DOWNTOWN RECOVERY WITHOUT A FAIR
RECOVERY FOR OUR WORKING CLASS FAMILIES.
FOR THESE REASONS I'M UNABLE TO SUPPORT THE LEGISLATION AS IT'S
CURRENTLY FORM TODAY. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU PRESIDENT AND I WILL BE
SUPPORTING THIS LEGISLATION TODAY AND I WANTED TO FOLLOW UP
A LITTLE BIT ON THE COMMENTS OF MY COLLEAGUE SUPERVISOR DORSEY
. I THINK YOU KNOW OUR DOWNTOWN
HAS BEEN AILING FOR QUITE A WHILE DURING THE PANDEMIC.
YOU KNOW THE SORT OF DYSTOPIAN PICTURE OF WHAT WAS HAPPENING
DOWNTOWN WAS FODDER FOR FOX NEWS AND A BUNCH OF, YOU KNOW,
RIGHT WING MEDIA AROUND THE COUNTRY SORT OF SHOWING HOW WE
HAVE FAILED. BUT THE TRUTH IS THAT OUR
DOWNTOWN IS SUFFERING FROM A BUNCH OF LAND USE DECISIONS
THAT PREVIOUS LEADERSHIP OF CITY MADE OVER DECADES AND WE
ZONED ALMOST EXCLUSIVELY FOR RETAIL AND RETAIL DRUG
MAGICALLY CHANGED NOT DURING THE PANDEMIC BUT WHEN SOMEBODY
BRINGS YOU A LITTLE BOX WITH WHATEVER YOUR HEART DESIRES TO
YOUR DOOR THE MOTIVATION TO GO TO THE EIGHTH FLOOR OF
NORDSTROM IS NOT SO PRESSING. SO WE FAILED TO ADAPT A LOT OF
OUR LAND USE. USES TO REFLECT WHAT RETAIL IS
TODAY AND OUR DOWNTOWN WHICH MADE UP ALMOST 60% OF OUR TAX
BASE STARTED FAILING. I WANT TO REMIND EVERYONE THAT
THE MACY'S MEN'S STORE AT DISAPPEARED EIGHT YEARS AGO WAY
BEFORE THE PANDEMIC AND PEOPLE STOPPED GOING TO THE SECOND
FLOOR THE THIRD FLOOR. FIRST IT WAS MACY'S FIRST IT
WAS I MAGNIN, THEN MACY'S AND NORDSTROM.
IT JUST REALLY CHANGED. AND NOW WE HAVE A WESTFIELD
MALL THAT'S COMPLETELY EMPTY. SO I HAVE NO DOUBT THAT WE HAVE
TO DO SOMETHING TO MAKE SURE THAT OUR DOWNTOWN SUCCEEDS
AND THRIVES. A LOT OF IT HAS TO DO TO THINK
WITH THINKING WHAT THE USE SHOULD BE NOT JUST RETAIL BUT
WHAT SHOULD BE HAPPENING BECAUSE OUR ENTIRE
TRANSPORTATION INFRASTRUCTURE RUNS THROUGH DOWNTOWN.
IT'S ADJACENT TO THE FINANCIAL DISTRICT TO A BUNCH OF THE
OTHER USES THAT WE HAVE. SO I LIKE IT THAT THIS ENDS
IN 1932. >> IT GIVES US SOME TIME TO
REASSESS. AND I WILL ALSO POINT OUT THAT
THE MATH OF THIS LEGISLATION ONLY WORKS IF THERE IS AN
INCREASE IN THE ASSESSMENT VALUE OF THESE PROPERTIES IF
THERE ISN'T, THERE'S NOTHING THAT WE CAN DO HERE.
SO I THINK THAT IT IS PREDICATED ON HOPING TO
REINVENT SOMETHING THAT IT WILL BE SUCCESSFUL THAT WE ARE
REVITALIZING THROUGH THESE LIKE REDEVELOP LITTLE REDEVELOPMENT
EFFORTS. AND I AM HOPING THAT WE CAN ALL
WORK TOGETHER TO MAKE SURE THAT IT SUCCEEDS BECAUSE THE REST OF
THE CITY DOES DEPEND ON THE SUCCESS OF THIS SMALL AREA.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MOMENTUM AND DEFINITELY BELIEVING
CONVERSION. I THINK THAT'S GOING TO BE
IMPORTANT FOR US TO ADDRESS HOUSING NEEDS AS WE MOVE
FORWARD. BUT I AM STRUGGLING WITH
AND THIS IS THROUGH THE CHAIR UNLESS THE CHAIR CAN AS IT A
QUESTION WHY CAN'T WE SPECIFICALLY IDENTIFY THE
PROPERTIES THAT WERE USED FOR THE EXERCISE OF DETERMINING HOW
MANY PROPERTIES THIS MAY AFFECT ?
IF WE KNOW A SPECIFIC NUMBER WHY CAN'T WE IDENTIFY WITH WHAT
THOSE WERE? SO THAT A QUESTION FOR STAFF
THE QUESTION FOR WHOEVER FOR ANYBODY WHO WANTS TO ANSWER IT.
>> MR. BENTLEY IF THERE'S LUZINSKI BECAUSE IT WAS STATED
THAT THERE ARE 48 THAT MIGHT QUALIFY.
SO I'M JUST WONDERING WHY WE CAN'T KNOW SPECIFICALLY WHAT
THOSE 48 ARE. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR
AND THROUGH THE CHAIR JACOB BUTLER FOR THE OFFICE OF
ECONOMIC AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT AS WE DISCUSSED
IN THE BUDGET COMMITTEE AND A SUPERVISOR SOUDER ALLUDED TO
THE EXERCISE WE HAD OUR CONSULTANTS DO WAS TO DO A HIGH
LEVEL ANALYSIS OF HOW MANY PROPERTIES WITHIN THE DISTRICT
BOUNDARIES MIGHT BE LIKELY CANDIDATES TO CONVERT.
THEY DID NOT DO A SITE SPECIFIC INVENTORY THAT IDENTIFIED
SPECIFIC PROPERTIES THAT WOULD CONVERT THE PROGRAM APPLIES TO
THE ENTIRE AREA ANY PROPERTY WITHIN THE DISTRICT AREA IS
ELIGIBLE TO COME FORWARD, A SUPERVISOR DORSEY SAID THROUGH
THE DISTRICT BOARD PROCESS. AND THEY HAVE TO EACH ONE
ENROLL INDIVIDUALLY BEFORE 2032 SO WE'LL KNOW WHICH PROJECTS
THEY ARE AS THEY COME FORWARD. BUT THERE IS NO LIST OF
SPECIFIC PROJECTS THAT WOULD QUALIFY OR NOT QUALIFY.
>> SO WHAT DID THE NUMBER 48 COME FROM?
IT CAME FROM THAT EXERCISE THAT OUR CONSULTANTS DID WHERE THEY
ESTIMATED HOW MANY PROPERTIES WOULD BE LIKELY BASED ON
BUILDING AGE VACANCY RATES THAT WERE AVAILABLE AT THE TIME.
THE CLASS OF THE BUILDING THE SIZE OF THE FLOOR PLATES
CHARACTERISTICS LIKE THAT SOME OF THE VARIABLES LIKE THE
RENTS, THE OFFICE RENTS AND THE VACANCY RATE CHANGE AND THAT
WAS DATA THAT WAS AVAILABLE AT THE TIME.
SO IT WAS NEVER INTENDED TO BE AN EXERCISE THAT WOULD GENERATE
A DEFINITIVE LIST OF PROJECTS BUT SOMETHING MORE AKIN TO
POLLING WHERE YOU DO A SAMPLE YOU GET A BASIC SENSE OF WHERE
PEOPLE ARE BUT YOU DON'T KNOW WHAT EACH INDIVIDUAL RESPONDENT
WOULD DO ON THAT QUESTION. BUT YOU KNOW WHAT THOSE 48
PROPERTIES ARE I DON'T KNOW WHERE THEY'RE LOCATED.
I DON'T SOMEBODY DOES. >> WELL, YOU GAVE A SPECIFIC
NUMBER OR THE PEOPLE WHO DID THE STUDY GAVE A SPECIFIC
NUMBER WHICH MEANS THEY KNOW 48 PROPERTIES SOMEWHERE IN THE
UNIVERSE AND THEY ACTUALLY DO HAVE ADDRESSES I'M GOING TO
ASSUME SO WHY IS IT HARD TO JUST SAY THESE ARE THE 48 THAT
WERE LOOKED AT DURING THE EXERCISE?
>> I MEAN THIS IS NOT SOMETHING THAT, YOU KNOW, IS PROBLEMATIC
THAT WE CAN'T SAY 40 EIGHT ADDRESSES MAYBE POSSIBLY
QUALIFY BECAUSE THAT WOULD HELP WITH DECISION MAKING MOVING
FORWARD. YEAH.
SO IT WAS NOT A DELIVERABLE FROM OUR CONSULTANTS TO PROVIDE
A SITE SPECIFIC LIST. THEY LOOKED AT A LIST OF ALL
THE PARCELS IN THE CITY AND THEN WITHIN THIS AREA
AND THEY PROVIDED THE DATA THAT WE HAVE RIGHT BUT THEY GAVE A
NUMBER THEY GAVE YOU A 48 THEY DID AN ESTIMATE.
THEY DIDN'T SAY IT COULD BE 10,000.
THEY DIDN'T SAY THEY SAID 48. THAT MEANS THEY HAVE 48
ADDRESSES SOMEWHERE. >> I'M GOING TO ASSUME.
YES. AND SO THE DELIVERABLE THAT WE
RECEIVED IS THAT THERE IS AN ESTIMATE OF APPROXIMATELY 48
PROPERTIES WITHIN THE DISTRICT THAT WOULD QUALIFY.
WE TOOK THAT PROJECTION THAT WAS ESTIMATED TO BE A CERTAIN
AMOUNT OF REVENUE THE $600 MILLION OVER 30 YEARS THAT WAS
PROJECTED AND THAT'S WHAT THE PROGRAMS ACCOMMODATING FOR.
SO IF THERE WERE MORE PROPERTIES OR A DIFFERENT SET
OF PROPERTIES THAT CAPITAL I'M NOT ASKING FOR MORE OR LESS YOU
MAY PROJECTIONS ON A SPECIFIC NUMBER OF PROPERTIES THAT ARE
POSSIBLY SOMETHING THAT MIGHT BE A PART OF HOW WE MOVE
FORWARD BUT WE DON'T KNOW WHAT THOSE 48 ADDRESSES ARE.
THAT'S THAT'S THAT'S THAT'S WHAT WAS PROBLEMATIC FOR ME.
I UNDERSTAND WHAT THE CHARGE WAS BUT I JUST I AGREE WITH MY
COLLEAGUE THAT YOU SHOULD BE ABLE TO GIVE US A LIST OF WHAT
THESE APPROXIMATE 48 PROPERTIES ARE THAT MIGHT QUALIFY FOR
SOMETHING THAT WOULD BENEFIT THE CITY IN THE FUTURE.
>> I AGREE WITH WHAT YOU'RE TRYING TO DO HERE.
I'M JUST IT'S JUST TROUBLING THAT WE CAN'T LOOK AT THE
PROPERTIES THAT ARE POSSIBLE BECAUSE SOMEBODY HAS TO
PRIORITIZE AT SOME POINT WHICH ONES ARE MORE FEASIBLE, WHICH
ONES ARE NOT. YOU GAVE US A NUMBER ESTIMATED
NUMBER ABOUT WHAT THE BENEFIT WOULD BE FROM THESE 48
PROPERTIES. SO THAT LEADS ME TO BELIEVE
THAT WE KNOW WHAT THESE 48 PROPERTIES ARE.
UNDERSTOOD. ALL RIGHT.
>> THANK YOU. ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 20 SUPERVISOR WALTON NO WALTON.
NO SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN NO.
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR OR DORSEY DORSEY
EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
MANAGEMENT I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I THERE ARE SEVEN EYES AND FOUR
NOS WITH SUPERVISORS WALTON CHAN CHEN AND FIELDER VOTING NO
AND THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR
230 SPECIAL ORDER OUR 230 SPECIAL ORDER IS THE
RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATIONS FOR MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE
CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO AND WE WILL START
WITH DISTRICT TEN SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU SO MUCH
PRESIDENT AND MADAM MIN. COLLEAGUES IN HONOR OF BLACK
HISTORY MONTH THIS YEAR WE WANT TO TAKE THE TIME TO HONOR
COMMUNITY LEADERS THAT MAKE POSITIVE CHANGE EVERY DAY FOR
OUR YOUNG PEOPLE AND COMMUNITIES AS A WHOLE
AND WHO ARE NOT USUALLY RECOGNIZED BECAUSE THEY WOULD
RATHER STAY IN COMMUNITY AND DO THE WORK VERSUS FOCUSING ON
HIGHLIGHTING THE WONDERFUL THINGS THAT THEY DO.
>> SO TODAY WE WILL START WITH PAUL BELSEN JR OH PAUL IS A
LIFELONG RESIDENT OF SAN FRANCISCO'S HUNTERS POINT
HARLEY ROCK COMMUNITY A HISTORICALLY ROOTED AREA
ENCOMPASSING THE HOLLISTER AND DOUBLE ROCK NEIGHBORHOODS
FIRST INCARCERATED AT THE AGE OF 12, PAUL SPENT MUCH OF HIS
YOUTH AND EARLY ADULTHOOD CYCLING THROUGH THE JUSTICE
SYSTEM UNTIL AGE 28. RATHER THAN ALLOWING THOSE
EXPERIENCES TO DEFINE HIM, HE MADE A DELIBERATE DECISION TO
CHANGE COURSE. >> HE CHOSE DISCIPLINE,
ACCOUNTABILITY AND PURPOSE. HIS JOURNEY REFLECTS THE
REALITY FACED BY MANY YOUNG PEOPLE RAISED
IN UNDER-RESOURCED COMMUNITIES AND DEMONSTRATES THE POWER OF
CHANCE PERMIT TRANSFORMATION WHEN OPPORTUNITY MEETS
DETERMINATION TODAY PAUL IS A SKILLED TRADES PROFESSIONAL
COMMUNITY LEADER AND CEO COMMITTED TO REBUILDING BOTH
INFRASTRUCTURE AND COMMUNITY THROUGH FORMAL CONSTRUCTION
TRAINING. HE BECAME A UNION IRONWORKER
AND EXPANDED HIS EXPERTISE INTO UTILITY AND WELDING WORK
CONTRIBUTING TO PROJECTS ESSENTIAL TO PUBLIC SAFETY
AND LONG TERM STABILITY BEYOND HIS PROFESSION OR CAREER, PAUL
REMAINS DEEPLY INVESTED IN STRENGTHENING FAMILIES
AND NEIGHBORHOODS THROUGH MENTORSHIP, HOUSING SUPPORT
AND COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT. HIS WORK REFLECTS A BELIEF THAT
SECOND CHANCES WERE MET WITH RESPONSIBLE AND SERVICE CAN
PRODUCE LEADERS WHO UPLIFT ENTIRE COMMUNITIES.
AS CEO OF BROADWAY PLAYS, PAUL PROVIDES TRANSITIONAL HOUSING
AND RECOVERY SUPPORT. HE ALSO HELPS LEAD IMPACTFUL
COMMUNITY INITIATIVES INCLUDING PARTICIPATION IN BATTER'S UP
GUNS DOWN AN ANTI-VIOLENCE PROGRAM USING SOFTBALL TO
MENTOR YOUTH AND HARLEY ROCK ALL-STARS A SOFTBALL LEAGUE
FOSTERING POSITIVE ENGAGEMENT ADDITIONALLY, HE ORGANIZES
FAMILY CENTERED EVENTS SUCH AS THE ANNUAL FATHER DAUGHTER
DANCE AND COMMUNITY AND MORE RECENTLY THE MOTHER SON DANCE
AND ANNUAL HOLIDAY TOY DRIVES ALL OF THESE EVENTS WERE
FEATURED IN LOCAL NEWS OUTLETS AS IT IS IMPORTANT FOR THESE
MESSAGES OF POSITIVITY FROM A NATIVE SON TO BE HIGHLIGHTED,
PAUL'S JOURNEY IS A TESTAMENT TO RESILIENCE, TRANSFORMATION
AND THE POWER OF GIVING BACK. PAUL TODAY WE CELEBRATE YOU
ALONG WITH COMMUNITY AND WANT TO THANK YOU FOR CONTINUING TO
INSPIRE OTHERS TO REWRITE THEIR STORIES AND UPLIFT THEIR
COMMUNITIES. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, MR. WALTON, FOR THE ACKNOWLEDGMENT FOR YOUR
RECOGNITION. FIRST AND FOREMOST I LIKE TO
GIVE HONOR AND GLORY TO GOD WITHOUT HIS GUIDANCE, HIS
PROTECTION AND HIS GRACE AND NONE OF THIS WILL BE
POSSIBLE. I'D ALSO LIKE TO THANK MY
FAMILY YOUR PATIENCE, YOUR SACRIFICE AND YOUR BELIEF
IN THE WORK. ALLOW ME TO KEEP SHOWING UP
EVEN WHEN THE LOAD IS HEAVY. THANK YOU TO THE D-10 DISTRICT
TEN OFFICE THE DREAM TEAM. WE APPRECIATE ALL THE SUPPORT
YOU GUYS DO BEHIND THE SCENES. THIS MOMENT MEANS A LOT.
THE VERY FIRST OF THIS HONOR AND I RECEIVE IT WITH HUMILITY
BUT I WANT TO BE VERY CLEAR THIS RECOGNITION DOES NOT
BELONG TO ME ALONE. IT BELONGS TO THE HOLLY ROCK
ALL STARS UP TOP SOFTBALL BATTERS UP, GUNS DOWN.
>> KEEP GOING. THIS TEAM ALLOWED US TO
OPERATE. THEY HAVE ALLOWED US TO OPERATE
IN PEACE. THEY MADE SURE RESOURCES WERE
AVAILABLE, COMMUNICATED CLEARLY, WENT ABOVE AND BEYOND
FINANCIALLY, PHYSICALLY AND EMOTIONALLY SO THE WORK
COULD CONTRIBUTE WITHOUT DISRUPTION.
LEADERSHIP IS NEVER SOLO ACT SO IT'S IMPORTANT TO ME THAT THOSE
WHO STOOD IN IT WITH ME. I WANT TO THANK.
STARTED FROM LEFT TO RIGHT. IT'S A LOT OF NAMES SO MRS.
BANKS, MRS. JONES, MR. DARDEN, J.B. GERM, EUGENE LIBERTY,
COREY SWIFT. >> MOSES JOHNSON.
GREGORY TUCKER. LAVELL SHAW.
RONNIE EARL. RONNIE WOODS.
SAMUEL MARKELL. WILL VARGAS.
ARMANI BROOKS. JOE JACOBS.
MATTHEW DONALDSON. JAMAL GRACIE.
RONALD BLACK. JAVON MARSHALL.
DOMINIQUE JACKSON. GEORGE KENT.
TERRELL ROGERS. PHILLIP BUFORD.
MICHAEL BARBER. BO CORBIN.
DAVID REYNOLDS DENNIS TUCKER. ORLANDO HODGES GINO CARPENTER.
>> ROLAND BLACK AND DEANDRE CHOISNE.
>> EACH OF YOU PLAYED A ROLE. CHARLES GARNER AND MY APOLOGY
TO JIMMY WILSON EACH EACH OF YOU PLAYED A ROLE SOME VISIBLE,
SOME BEHIND THE SCENES BUT EVERY CONTRIBUTION MATTER.
I ALSO WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE PROGRAMS AND INDIVIDUALS WHO
SUPPORTED ME THROUGH THIS JOURNEY.
THOSE WHO BELIEVED IN A MISSION TO HELP ME CARE FOR JIMMY
WILSON AND CHARLES PEREZ. THANK YOU FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP
AND COUNSEL. Y C D RAFIKI WELLNESS CAMP
WILSON WELCOME DISPARITIES US FOR US HEALING AND GROWTH
OPPORTUNITY. SENSELESS TRAGEDIES OPPRESSING
OUR PEOPLE AND DAD CLUB WERE HERE BUT AND ANSWER THE
SPEAKERS AS WELL THANK YOU FOR STANDING IN ALIGNMENT
AND SHOWING WHAT COLLABORATION TRULY LOOKS LIKE.
THIS AWARD CARRIES MY NAME BUT IT REPRESENTS MANY HANDS, MANY
SHOULDERS AND MANY HEARTS. WE MOVE AS ONE EVEN WE
RECOGNIZE IT VISUALLY. BUT UNITY ISN'T ABOUT WHO
STARES AT THE PODIUM. IT'S ABOUT WHO STOOD IN AND
WORKED TOGETHER AS FREDERICK DOUGLASS REMINDS US.
IF THERE IS NO STRUGGLE, THERE IS NO PROGRESS.
WE STRUGGLE TOGETHER. WE'LL BUILD TOGETHER.
WE WILL CONTINUE TO RISE TOGETHER.
THANK YOU ALL FOR EVERYTHING YOU HAVE DONE.
AGAIN, THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR ALL YOUR SUPPORT FROM THE
BEGINNING YOU TOLD US TO GET OUT THERE AND DO IT.
YOU KNOW WHAT I'M SAYING? AND YOU WILL SUPPORT US IT HAS
IT BEEN ANYTHING WE CAME ACROSS THAT YOU HAVE SUPPORTED US WITH
FROM THE SMALLEST THINGS? THANK YOU TO THE TANGERINE TEAM
YOU GUYS REALLY DO CARE AND HAVE SHOWN US AND A THANK
YOU TO MY MENTOR AND COUNSELOR YOU KNOW YOU KNOW SLEEP TIGHT
REDUCTIONS MAY POPULAR CERTIFICATE DISTRICT FIVE
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
HONORED TO RECOGNIZE VICTORIA LEE.
>> WHERE YOU WANT TO COME UP TO STAND.
>> VICTORIA IS A QUIET FORCE WHOSE NEARLY FIVE DECADES OF
SERVICE HELPED SHAPE THE HEART AND CULTURE OF GLIDE MEMORIAL
CHURCH. VICTORIA LEE WAS BORN
AND RAISED IN OAKLAND TO IMMIGRANT PARENTS.
THE SECOND OF FOUR CHILDREN IN A LIVELY HOUSEHOLD THAT
TAUGHT HER EARLY LESSONS ABOUT WHAT PROVIDING SERVICE TRULY
MEANS. >> AFTER GRADUATING FROM
COLLEGE, VICTORIA WORKED IN A CHILDHOOD EDUCATION AND CHURCH
ADMINISTRATION. DURING THIS TIME SHE BECAME
DEEPLY INSPIRED BY GLIDE, THE REVEREND CECIL WILLIAMS SUNDAY
CELEBRATION WHICH CENTERED THE VALUES OF INCLUSIVITY
AND COMMUNITY SERVICE. THOSE VALUES RESONATED DEEPLY
AND IN 1978 VICTORIA JOINED GLIDE BEGINNING WHAT WOULD
BECOME A 47 YEAR COMMITMENT TO THE ORGANIZATION AND ITS
MISSION. VICTORIA'S OFFICIAL ROLE WAS
MANAGING GLIDES BUILDING AND BUSINESS OFFICE.
>> BUT HER TRUE CONTRIBUTION EXTENDED FAR BEYOND ANY JOB
TITLE. >> OVER THE DECADES SHE BECAME
AN ORGANIZER, CURATOR, HISTORIAN, EVENT PLANNER,
GRAPHIC DESIGNER AND KEEPER OF GLIDES CULTURE.
>> IT'S A LOT OF JOBS. >> ONLY PART.
>> WORKING CLOSELY ALONGSIDE REVEREND CECIL WILLIAMS
AND GLIDE CO-FOUNDER JANICE MIRIKITANI.
>> VICTORIA HELPED VICTORIA HELP BUILD NOT JUST AN
ORGANIZATION BUT A COMMUNITY ROOTED IN TRUE SERVICE.
>> HER IMPACT IS PERHAPS BEST CAPTURED BY THE WORDS OF A
GLIDE COMMUNITY MEMBER WHO SHARED HER GRACE, RADIANT
SPIRIT AND TIRELESS DEDICATION KEPT US GOING.
AND HER PRESENCE CONTINUES TO SHAPE WHO WE ARE.
>> GLIDE WAS ALSO WHERE VICTORIA FOUND LOVE.
SHE MET HER LATE HUSBAND DAVID RICHMOND, ANOTHER FOUNDATIONAL
FIGURE AND GLIDES HISTORY TOGETHER MARRIED TO ONE ANOTHER
INTO THE MISSION OF GLIDE. THEY DEDICATED THEIR LIVES TO
SERVICE, WITNESSING THE ORGANIZATION'S GROWTH
AND DEEPENING ITS IMPACT ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO.
>> OVER THE DECADES BEYOND GLIDE VICTORIA IS A DEVOTED
ARTIST AND CALLIGRAPHER. SHE'S A LONG TIME MEMBER OF
FRIENDS OF CALLIGRAPHY, AN INTERNATIONAL CALLIGRAPHY
SOCIETY WHERE SHE HAS VOLUNTEERED AT WORKSHOPS
AND EXHIBITIONS AND CONTINUED TO EXPAND HER CRAFT.
HER WORK HAS BEEN EXHIBITED AT THE SAN FRANCISCO MAIN LIBRARY
AND SHE IS KNOWN FOR HER BOOKBINDING HANDMADE PAPERS
AND INTRICATELY COLLAGE AND SEWN CARDS.
HER ARTISTIC PRACTICE REFLECTS THE SAME CARE AND PATIENCE SHE
HAS BROUGHT TO HER WORK IN THE COMMUNITY.
>> TODAY AS VICTORIA LEE RETIRES AFTER NEARLY FIVE
DECADES OF SERVICE, WE HONOR HER NOT ONLY FOR HER
EXTRAORDINARY WORK BUT THE SPIRIT WITH WHICH SHE CARRIED
IT OUT. VICTORIA THANK YOU FOR YOUR
DEVOTION AND YOUR UNWAVERING COMMITMENT TO THE COMMUNITY
YOUR LEGACY LIVES ON AND THE COUNTLESS LIVES YOU HAVE
TOUCHED. >> THANK YOU.
MY PERSONAL POET AND TEACHER MARGARET KAY WHITE.
I DON'T SPEAK FOR VICKI. SHE HAS HER HAND ON MY BACK
AND SPEAKS THROUGH ME. >> MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS HONORED COLLEAGUES AND MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC.
MY NAME IS MARVIN KAYE WHITE AND I AM THE MINISTER OF
CELEBRATION AT GLIDE MEMORIAL CHURCH AND ON BEHALF OF THE
GLIDE MEMORIAL CHURCH CONGREGATION CLIENTS
AND COMMUNITY THE GLIDE MEMORIAL CHURCH BOARD OF
DIRECTORS REVEREND DR. GINA FROMER, OUR CEO AND PRESIDENT
OF THE GLIDE FOUNDATION. WE KNOW THAT THERE ARE MOMENTS
IN THE LIFE OF AN INSTITUTION REALLY IN THE LIFE OF A CITY.
WHEN WE PAUSE NOT BECAUSE THE WORK HAS ENDED BUT BECAUSE
SOMEONE HAS CARRIED IT SO FAITHFULLY THAT WE MUST STOP
LONG ENOUGH TO SAY THANK YOU. >> TODAY WE JOIN IN HONORING
VICTORIA VICKI LEE, WHOSE 47 YEARS OF EXTRAORDINARY SERVICE
SPAN NEARLY THE ENTIRE MODERN LIFE OF GLIDE MEMORIAL CHURCH
AND ITS EVOLVING RELATIONSHIP WITH THE GLIDE FOUNDATION.
AS YOU'VE HEARD TODAY THAT VICKI CAME TO GLIDE AS A YOUNG
WOMAN SEEKING WORK THAT MATTERED.
SHE WAS DRAWN BY THE RADICAL INVITATION OF CECIL WILLIAMS
AND SHAPED UNDER THE VISIONARY LEADERSHIP OF JANICE
MIRIKITANI. SHE ENTERED THE COMMUNITY READY
TO SERVE, READY TO BUILD AND READY TO TAKE HER PLACE
IN A MOVEMENT ROOTED IN UNCONDITIONAL LOVE, JUSTICE
AND LIBERATION. >> FROM THE BEGINNING VICKI
BECAME THE QUIET CONSTANT ACROSS NEARLY FIVE DECADES OF
SOCIAL TRANSFORMATION. HER TENURE SPANS THE DEFINING
ERAS OF OUR CITY AND OUR CONGREGATION FROM THE
POST-CIVIL RIGHTS AND WOMEN'S LIBERATION MOVEMENTS OF THE
1970S THROUGH THE AIDS PANDEMIC AND SANCTUARY MOVEMENT OF THE
1980S FROM THE RACIAL JUSTICE RECKONING AND WELFARE REFORM
BATTLES OF THE 1990S INTO THE 2000 MARKED BY LGBTQ MARRIAGE
STRUGGLES POST-9-11 SOLIDARITY AND THE RAPIDLY CHANGING SAN
FRANCISCO. BUT ACROSS EVERY DECADE
AND THROUGH EVERY POLITICAL SHIFT CULTURAL UPHEAVAL
AND INSTITUTIONAL EVOLUTION, VICKI REMAINED THE STEADY HEART
OF THE CHURCH OFFICE. SHE HELD OUR ARCHIVES IN HER
MEMORY, OUR SCHEDULES IN OUR HANDS AND OUR COMMUNITY IN HER
CARE. >> HER WORK WAS RARELY ON THE
STAGE BUT IT WAS ALWAYS THE REASON THE STAGE COULD BE SET.
>> VICKI BEGAN HER SERVICE WHEN GLIDE WAS ONE ORGANIZATION,
CHURCH AND FOUNDATION HELD TOGETHER BY A SHARED MISSION
AND SHARED BREADTH. WHEN GLIDE EVOLVED, WHEN THE
CHURCH AND THE GLIDE FOUNDATION BECAME DISTINCT EXPRESSIONS OF
THE SAME CALLING, VICKI TRANSITIONED WITH GRACE,
INTEGRITY AND DEEP INSTITUTIONAL WISDOM.
VERY FEW PEOPLE HOLD THAT KIND OF HISTORY.
FEWER STILL HOLD IT WITH GENEROSITY.
IN MORE RECENT YEARS SHE CONTINUED HER FAITHFUL SERVICE
THROUGH GUIDES, TRANSITIONS OF OUR CO-FOUNDERS AND OUR
ORGANIZATION OFFERING STEADINESS, CONTINUITY
AND INSTITUTIONAL MEMORY DURING SEASONS OF GROWTH AND CHANGE.
HER ABILITY TO BRIDGE ERAS LEADERS AND STRUCTURES HAS BEEN
A QUIET BUT ESSENTIAL GIFT TO GUIDES ONGOING LIFE.
HER TITLE NEVER FULLY CAPTURED HER CONTRIBUTION.
VICKI WAS NOT SIMPLY AN OFFICE MANAGER.
SHE WAS A BOARD ORGANIZER OR A CURATOR AND HISTORIAN AND EVENT
PLANNER A DESIGNER ASSISTANT ASSISTANCE PROVIDER AND KEEPER
OF CULTURE. SHE MADE IT POSSIBLE FOR
MINISTRIES TO FUNCTION, FOR CELEBRATIONS TO UNFOLD AND FOR
GLIDE TO REMAIN ROOTED EVEN AS THE CITY AROUND IT CHANGED.
SHE WELCOMED THOUSANDS I WOULD EVEN SAY HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS
CONGREGANTS, NEIGHBORS, VOLUNTEERS AND SEEKERS WITH
PATIENTS CLARITY AND THE SPIRIT THAT EMBODIED GLIDES OF VALUES
LONG BEFORE THOSE VALUES WERE WRITTEN DOWN.
VICKI ALSO FOUND HER LOVE AT GLIDE.
SHE AND HER LATE HUSBAND DAVID RICHMOND HIMSELF A FORMATIVE
LEADER IN GLIDES EARLY YEARS, WERE MARRIED NOT ONLY TO ONE
ANOTHER BUT TO THE MISSION THEY SERVED TOGETHER.
THEIR SHARED DEVOTION REMINDS US THAT INSTITUTIONS ARE
ULTIMATELY SUSTAINED BY RELATIONSHIPS AND NOT STRUCTURE
ALONE. VICKI IS OFTEN WE CALL IT THE
GLUE BUT THAT WORD IS TOO SMALL .
>> GLUE SUGGESTS SOMETHING SILENT AND BURDENED.
VICKI HAS BEEN THE HEARTBEAT STEADY, COMPASSIONATE
AND STRONG. SHE REMINDS US THAT CARE IS
INFRASTRUCTURE. MEMORY IS CIVIC LABOR AND LOVE.
PRACTICE DAILY IS A GOOD PUBLIC GOOD.
AGAIN IT IS WITH PROFOUND GRATITUDE THAT WE KNOW THAT
VICKI RECEIVES THIS COMMENDATION NOT ONLY AS
RECOMMENDATION, NOT ONLY AS RECORD RECOGNITION OF A
REMARKABLE LIFE BUT AS AN AFFIRMATION OF THE QUIET
FAITHFUL LABOR THAT HELPS HOLD A CITY'S CONSCIENCE IN PLACE.
VICKI LEE, WE THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR SERVICE AND WISH YOU
THE BEST IN YOUR RETIREMENT. >> SHE'S NOT GOING TO TALK ALL
THE THINGS SHE SAID. >> OKAY, HERE WE GO.
BUT YOU THINK RIGHT NOW. ALL RIGHT.
>> SUPERVISOR WONG, YOU HAVE YOUR YOU HAVE YOUR FOLKS HERE.
YES, I DO. RIGHT.
LET'S GO WITH DISTRICT FOUR SUPERVISOR WONG.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU, PRESIDENT
AND COLLEAGUES. AS A SUPERVISOR FOR THE SUNSET
DISTRICT FOUR, I'M TRULY PROUD TO RECOGNIZE ST IGNATIUS, A
SCHOOL THAT HAS BEEN PART OF THE SUNSET AND PART OF SAN
FRANCISCO SINCE 1855. ST IGNATIUS IS KNOWN NOT ONLY
FOR ACADEMIC EXCELLENCE BUT FOR HELPING STUDENTS LEARN HOW TO
BALANCE HARD WORK IN THE CLASSROOM WITH COMMITMENT ON
THE FIELD AND HOW TO GROW AS WHOLE PEOPLE.
THIS PAST SEASON THE WILDCATS MADE HISTORY BY WINNING THE
SCHOOL'S FIRST STATE CHAMPIONSHIP.
TO THE STUDENT ATHLETES HERE TODAY WHAT MAKES THIS
ACHIEVEMENT ESPECIALLY MEANINGFUL IS NOT JUST THE
TITLE ITSELF. YOU SHOWED THAT IT IS POSSIBLE
TO COMPETE AT THE HIGHEST LEVEL WHILE STILL SHOWING UP FOR YOUR
STUDIES, YOUR TEAMMATES AND YOUR COMMUNITY, YOUR
DISCIPLINE, TEAMWORK AND PERSEVERE REFLECT VALUES
THAT WILL STAY WITH YOU LONG AFTER FOOTBALL.
>> I ALSO WANT TO RECOGNIZE COACH HEAD COACH LAWSON,
PRINCIPAL BULLARD AND ALL OF THE SUPPORT STAFF WHO ARE HERE
WITH US TODAY. THANK YOU FOR EVERYTHING YOU DO
FOR THESE STUDENTS. THIS KIND OF SUCCESS COMES FROM
LEADERSHIP THAT CARES DEEPLY ABOUT WHO THESE STUDENTS ARE
BECOMING NOT JUST WHAT SHOWS UP ON THE SCOREBOARD.
YOU HAVE BUILT A PROGRAM THAT EMPHASIZES CHARACTER, INTEGRITY
AND BALANCE AND THAT IMPACT WILL LAST BEYOND THIS SEASON
AND TO THE ENTIRE SEASON. IGNATIUS COMMUNITY INCLUDING
STUDENTS, FAMILIES, ALUMNI, FACULTY AND STAFF.
THIS SEASON BROUGHT REAL JOY TO THE SUNSET AND TO DISTRICT FOUR
NEIGHBORS FOLLOWED THE TEAM CELEBRATED TOGETHER AND FELT
PROUD SEEING A LOCAL SCHOOL REPRESENT SAN FRANCISCO SO
WELL. THAT SHARED PRIDE AND SENSE OF
JOY IS SOMETHING THAT OUR COMMUNITY TRULY VALUES.
ON BEHALF OF THE CITY AND COUNTY ATTENDING SCHOOL,
I'M HONORED TO COMMEND THE SAINT IGNATIUS COLLEGE
PREPARATORY WILDCATS ON THIS HISTORIC ACHIEVEMENT.
CONGRATULATIONS ON A REMARKABLE SEASON AND THANK YOU FOR THE
INSPIRATION YOU BROUGHT TO OUR COMMUNITY.
WITH THAT I'D LIKE TO TURN IT OVER TO MR. DE LUCCI, THE
CAPTAIN OF THE TEAM. >> GO WILDCATS.
THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR WONG. MY NAME IS DAVID DELUCA AND I'M
A TEAM CAPTAIN FOR THE 2025 S.I. VARSITY FOOTBALL TEAM.
I'M GRATEFUL TO BE UP HERE SPEAKING ON BEHALF OF MY TEAM
AND COMMUNITY IN ACCEPTING THIS RECOGNITION.
AS A COMMUNITY WE WANT TO THANK THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ALAN
WONG SPECIFICALLY FOR THIS RECOGNITION.
THANK YOU FOR THE SEND OFF AND YOUR SUPPORT AS WE WENT TO
PLAY IN THE STATE CHAMPIONSHIP GAME GROWING UP IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND ATTENDING S.I. HAS SHOWN ME THE SIZE AT THE
HEART OF OUR CITY MORE PERSONALLY FIVE GENERATIONS OF
MY FAMILY HAS ATTENDED S.I.. SO BEING UP HERE TODAY MAKES ME
FEEL EVEN MORE CONNECTED TO THEM BEING A PART OF S.I.
FOOTBALL SINCE FRESHMAN YEAR MEANS EVERYTHING GROWING A
BROTHERHOOD THAT WILL LAST A LIFETIME.
I'VE MADE PLENTY OF FRIENDS THROUGHOUT MY FOUR YEARS THAT I
KNOW I CAN RELY ON IF ANYTHING EVER GETS HARD.
AND JUST BEING A PART OF THAT AND GETTING TO GROW IN THAT IS
WHAT MAKES US SO SPECIAL. WE CONTINUE TO BUILD THAT EVERY
DAY AND IT GOES PAST JUST ONE CLASS OR JUST ONE YEAR WHICH IS
SOMETHING I'M GOING TO BE ETERNALLY GRATEFUL FOR FROM
S.I.. S.I. IS SAN FRANCISCO
AND FOOTBALL IS OUR WAY TO GIVE BACK SOME SPECIAL THANKS WE
WANT TO GIVE IS TO THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR ALLOWING US TO
HAVE LIGHTS AND EMBRACE THE FRIDAY NIGHT LIGHTS SPIRIT THAT
IS HIGH SCHOOL FOOTBALL. WE APPRECIATE THAT.
ADDITIONALLY, I WANT TO THANK ALL THE PEOPLE OUTSIDE THAT
HELPED US GET TO THIS MOMENT INCLUDING TRAINERS, STAFF
COACHES AND TEACHERS. THANK YOU ALL AGAIN
AND SPEAKING ON BEHALF OF ALL OF US, I THANK YOU FOR THIS
RECOGNITION. >> GO CATS
ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, LET'S GET THROUGH A COUPLE MORE ITEMS
PLEASE CALL ITEM 21. >> ITEM 21.
>> THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE FIRST AMENDMENT TO
THE AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE CITY ACTING THROUGH THE DEPARTMENT
OF PUBLIC HEALTH AND HEALTH RAY 360 TO PROVIDE WITHDRAWAL
MANAGEMENT AND RESIDENTIAL TREATMENT SERVICES TO EXTEND
THE TERM BY TWO YEARS FOR A NEW TERM OF JULY 1ST 2024 THROUGH
JUNE 30TH 2028 AND TO INCREASE THE AMOUNT BY APPROXIMATELY
28.6 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL AMOUNT OF 38.6 MILLION.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 21 SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON
EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG ABSENCE SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN
EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR AMANDA. WOMAN ALL RIGHT.
MANDEL MEN EYES SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR EYES SUPERVISOR
SADR SADR EYE AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EITHER ARE TEN
EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
AND WITH THAT LET'S GO TO OUR FIRST 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER THE
FIRST 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER ITEMS 33 THROUGH 36 COMPRISE A
PUBLIC HEARING OF PERSONS INTERESTED IN THE DECISION OF
PUBLIC WORKS DATED NOVEMBER 7TH 2025 TO APPROVE A TENTATIVE
PARCEL MAP FOR A THREE LOT VERTICAL SUBDIVISION FIVE
RESIDENTIAL AND TEN COMMERCIAL MIXED USE CONDOMINIUM PROJECT
AT 3333 MISSION STREET AND 190 CALL RIDGE STREET.
ITEM 34 THAT'S THE MOTION TO APPROVE THE PUBLIC WORKS
DECISION TO APPROVE THE TENTATIVE PARCEL MAP ITEM 35
THAT'S THE MOTION TO CONDITIONALLY DISAPPROVE THE
PUBLIC WORKS DECISION BASED UPON OR SUBJECT TO THE ADOPTION
OF WRITTEN FINDINGS IN SUPPORT OF THE DISAPPROVAL AND ITEM 36
THAT'S THE MOTION TO DIRECT THE PREPARATION OF FINDINGS.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES, THE CLERK HAS
DESCRIBED THE APPEAL BEFORE US. WE'LL HAVE OUR HEARING AFTER
THE HEARING. THE VOTE WILL.
THE BOARD WILL VOTE ON WHETHER TO APPROVE OR CONDITIONALLY
DISAPPROVE THE DECISION OF PUBLIC WORKS UNLESS THERE ARE
OBJECTIONS. I PROPOSE WE PROCEED AS FOLLOWS
WE WILL GIVE UP TO TEN MINUTES FOR A PRESENTATION BY THE
APPELLANTS. THEN WE'LL TAKE PUBLIC COMMENT
WITH UP TO TWO MINUTES PER SPEAKER IN SUPPORT OF THE
APPEAL. THEN WE WILL GIVE THE CITY
DEPARTMENTS OF UP TO TEN MINUTES TO MAKE THEIR
PRESENTATION AND THEN WE WILL GIVE THE PROJECT SPONSOR UP TO
TEN MINUTES AND THEN AGAIN WE WILL TAKE PUBLIC COMMENT TWO
MINUTES PER SPEAKER IN OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL.
AND THEN FINALLY WE WILL GIVE THE APPELLANT THREE MINUTES FOR
A REBUTTAL. I DON'T SEE ANY OBJECTIONS
SEEING NONE. >> THE HEARING WILL THE PUBLIC
HEARING WILL PROCEED AS INDICATED AND IS NOW OPEN AND I
DON'T SEE ANY NAMES ON THE ROSTER.
SO I'M GOING TO INVITE THE APPELLANT TO COME FORWARD
AND PRESENT THEIR CASE. AND I THINK THAT'S DON LUCCHESI
AND MARTHA WHO. YES.
THANK YOU. GOOD AFTERNOON.
ACTUALLY I'M GOING TO BE SPEAKING ON BEHALF OF THE
PRESENTATION AND MARTHA WILL FOLLOW AS BEING ONE OF THE
PUBLIC COMMENTERS AFTER THIS. IT'S A BEAUTIFUL ROOM.
GOOD AFTERNOON AND THANK YOU FOR ALLOWING US THIS
OPPORTUNITY TO MEET WITH YOU. >> FIRST A FEW WORDS TO CLEAR
UP ANY MISCONCEPTIONS ABOUT THIS APPEAL.
IT WAS FILED NOT TO STOP A DEVELOPMENT FROM BEING BUILT,
NOT TO INTENTIONALLY DELAY THE PROJECT FROM MOVING FORWARD
AND NOT TO SHOW DISAPPROVAL OF NEW HOUSING IN OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD. AS B AND C THE DEVELOPER HAS
BEEN FRAMING THIS AS A QUOTE A FRIVOLOUS APPEAL BY A FEW
HOMEOWNERS WHO WANT TO STOP AFFORDABLE SENIOR HOUSING
UNQUOTE. THAT IS SIMPLY NOT TRUE.
IN FACT IT IS A GROSS MISREPRESENTATION OF THE TRUTH
CALCULATED TO MANIPULATE PUBLIC OPINION AND GET PEOPLE TO SIGN
A PETITION TO DROP THIS APPEAL. B AND C WILL BE ADDING 105 NEW
UNITS OF HOUSING AND THERE IS A PROPOSED 370 UNIT DEVELOPMENT
ON THE SITE OF THE SAFEWAY AT 30TH IN MISSION TOGETHER.
THAT IS 475 NEW UNITS OF HOUSING ALL JUST ONE BLOCK AWAY
FROM THE CURRENT COLA STREET PARK.
AS OUR IMMEDIATE NEIGHBORHOOD WILL BECOME DENSER B AND C IS
PROPOSING A SMALLER PARK BY A SIGNIFICANT AMOUNT OVER 42%
SMALLER. >> WE CANNOT AFFORD TO LOSE
OPEN SPACE THAT HAS BEEN PART OF THE COMMUNITY FOR ALMOST 40
YEARS WHILE MANY MORE PEOPLE WILL BE MOVING IN.
AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS ONE OF THE BIGGEST ISSUES FACING SAN
FRANCISCO TODAY. BUT IT MUST BE DONE WITH THE
INTENTION OF IMPROVING THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
IT IMPACTS AND NOT BY TAKING AWAY WHAT IT BADLY NEEDS OPEN
PARK SPACE FOR CHILDREN AND FAMILIES, FOR NEIGHBORS
YOUNG AND OLD AND FOR FUTURE GENERATIONS.
WHILE HNC FIRST PRESENTED THIS PLANS TO US WHEN THEY PRESENTED
THIS PLAN TO US IT WAS A SIX STORY 70 UNIT PROJECT.
AFTER MUCH OUTRAGE AT HOW SIX STOREYS WAS IMPOSED UPON OUR
TWO STORY HOMES B AND C DID MAKE THE CONCESSION TO LOWER IT
THE FOUR STORIES BUT THEY WOULDN'T BUDGE ON MAKING THE
PARK LARGER. >> A PETITION WAS SIGNED A
PETITION WAS STARTED ON CHANGE.ORG BY THE COLERIDGE
STREET NEIGHBORS TO SAVE OUR PARK AND STILL ADD SENIOR
HOUSING. IT SPECIFICALLY SAYS THAT THE
SIGNEES OF THIS PETITION WELCOME AFFORDABLE SENIOR
HOUSING IN OUR COMMUNITY A GRASSROOTS EFFORT LED TO 360
SIGNATURES FROM A TWO BLOCK RADIUS COMING FROM RENTERS,
HOMEOWNERS, DAYCARE CENTERS, SENIORS, FAMILIES THAT HAVE
BEEN IN THE AREA FOR DECADES AND FAMILIES WHO HAVE JUST
MOVED IN. IT BECAME VERY APPARENT THAT WE
WOULDN'T BE ABLE TO SAVE THE PARK TO ITS ORIGINAL SIZE SINCE
B AND C WOULD BE DEVELOPING ON MUCH OF IT.
BUT THE INTENT OF THE PETITION REMAINS THE SAME SAVE OUR PARK.
>> IT IS WITH THIS SUPPORT FROM 360 SIGNATURES AND THE OVER 40
MEMBERS OF THE COLERIDGE STREET NEIGHBORS THAT THIS APPEAL WAS
FILED. THIS APPEAL IS SPECIFICALLY
ABOUT REZONING THE PARK PARCEL TO MAKE IT LARGER.
THE INTENTION IS TO GET AN AUDIENCE WITH CITY OFFICIALS
WHO HAVE NOT LISTENED TO OUR CONCERNS BECAUSE THEY SAY THEIR
HANDS ARE TIED BY SB 35. SB 35 ALLOWS ANY PROJECT FOR
AFFORDABLE HOUSING TO MOVE FORWARD PAST ANY MOVE PAST ANY
COMMUNITY REVIEW. WHILE THE INTENTION IS TO
EXPEDITE DEVELOPMENT, IT ALSO OVERLOOKS HOW IT COULD IMPACT
THE COMMUNITY AND IT SILENCES THE RIGHTS OF RESIDENTS TO
SPEAK OUT. FILING THIS APPEAL WAS THE ONLY
WAY TO GET OUR CONCERNS ABOUT THE PARK REDUCTION HEARD.
WITH ANY MEMBER OF CITY GOVERNMENT WE ARE HOPEFUL THAT
THE AGENCY CAN MAKE MINOR MODIFICATIONS TO THEIR PLANS TO
RETURN SOME OF THE PARK AND STILL RETAIN 70 UNITS OF
HOUSING. BY LOOKING AT THE PLANS.
WE FEEL STRONGLY THAT THAT CAN BE DONE AND THAT A LARGE PART
OF THE PARK CAN BE SAVED. WE HAVE LEFT COPIES OF THE
BUILDING PLANS WITH EACH SUPERVISOR SO THAT IT SO THAT
THEY CAN SEE HOW SMALL CHANGES AND SOME SHUFFLING OF UNITS CAN
SAVE A LARGE PART OF THE PARK. >> WE ARE RESIGNED TO NOT EVER
HAVING THE PARK RESTORED TO ITS ORIGINAL SIZE BUT WE FEEL
SAVING ANY PART OF IT IS WORTH NEGOTIATING FOR.
WE ARE HOPING FOR A SOLUTION THAT BOTH PARTIES CAN WALK AWAY
FROM AND FEEL ENTHUSIASTIC ABOUT SUPPORTING THIS
DEVELOPMENT. BUT THAT HASN'T HAPPENED
BECAUSE THERE'S NO ROAD TO NEGOTIATE UNDER SB 35 B AND C
HAS GATHERED A NUMBER OF SIGNATURES TO TELL THE
SUPERVISORS TO END THIS FRIVOLOUS APPEAL.
THIS IS NOT A FRIVOLOUS APPEAL. THIS IS THIS PARK HAS BEEN A
VITAL PART OF OUR COMMUNITY FOR DECADES.
WE ARE NOT A FEW HOMEOWNERS. WE ARE 365 BERNAL HEIGHTS
RESIDENTS AND WE ARE NOT TRYING TO STOP AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
FRANKLY, WE ARE DISAPPOINTED THAT A NONPROFIT IN BERNAL
HEIGHTS WOULD STOOP TO A DISHONEST CAMPAIGN LIKE THIS
AND USE THEIR LIES TO PROPAGATE AND INFLUENCE LOCAL POLITICAL
GROUPS AND CITIZENS. >> I DON'T MIND THAT THEY SAY I
AM AGAINST AFFORDABLE HOUSING. IT'S A LIE AND I KNOW IT.
I'M A MEMBER OF THE GREEN PARTY SO MY POLITICS LEAN QUITE FAR
TO THE LEFT. AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS ONE OF
THE ISSUES I SUPPORT ALONG WITH KEEPING THE VOICES OF THE
COMMUNITY COMMUNITY ALIVE AND HEARD.
BUT TO DRAG DOWN MY NEIGHBORS NEIGHBORS WHO ARE HOUSING
ACTIVISTS, NEIGHBORS WHO ARE SOCIAL WORKERS,
CONSERVATIONISTS, NONPROFIT WORKERS, TEACHERS AND TO INSIST
THAT THEY ARE ANTI AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS DOWNRIGHT SHAMEFUL.
A NEIGHBOR WHO IS PART OF THE COLOREDS STREET NEIGHBORS GROUP
WAS CONFRONTED BY ANOTHER BERNAL RESIDENT WHO CALLED HER
SELFISH AND ASKED HOW COULD SHE SUPPORT A HOUSE?
HOW COULD SHE BE AGAINST AFFORDABLE HOUSING?
>> MY NEIGHBOR IS IN HER 70S. SHE JUST CAME BACK FROM A NICE
DEMONSTRATION AND SHE HAD TO DEAL WITH THE BLOWBACK FROM
VANCE'S RHETORIC. TO THAT I SAY SHAME ON THE
AGENCY. SHAME ON GINA DAVIS AND SHAME
ON SOLOMON HYATT FOR PROPAGATING LIES LIES THAT
VILIFY OUR NEIGHBORS, LIES THAT DIVIDE OUR NEIGHBORS AND LIES
THAT INCITE CONFRONTATION. >> >> I BROUGHT THIS APPEAL
FORWARD IN THE NAME OF OUR GREATER COMMUNITY.
THIS APPEAL IS NOT INTENDED TO HALT THE PROJECT, HINDER ITS
PROGRESS OR IMPOSE ANY DELAY. AND WE ARE SORRY IF IT DOES.
IT IS SIMPLY A COMMON SENSE ASK FOR SAVING OUR OPEN SPACE.
WE DIDN'T WANT TO FILE THIS APPEAL BUT IT WAS THE ONLY WAY
TO GET THE CITY INVOLVED IN OUR STALEMATE WITH B AND C.
WE WANT THE CITY TO RECOGNIZE THE NEED FOR OPEN SPACE AT A
TIME WHEN THE DENSITY OF THE CITY IS INCREASING IMMENSELY.
THIS SHOULD NOT BE OVERLOOKED AND IT'S SOMETHING THAT HAS
IMPLICATIONS IN ALL NEIGHBORHOODS, IN ALL DISTRICTS
THROUGHOUT THE CITY NOT JUST BRENNAN HEIGHTS.
DEVELOPERS OF ALL HOUSING DEVELOPMENTS AND THE CITY
SHOULD BE WORKING HAND IN HAND WITH THEIR NEIGHBORS TO ENSURE
THAT WE ARE NOT LIVING IN THE CANYON IN A CANYON OF CONCRETE
AND THAT'S SUFFOCATING FROM LACK OF SPACE.
IF RESOLUTIONS ARE UNSOLVED BETWEEN DEVELOPERS AND THE
COMMUNITY WITHOUT CITY INVOLVEMENT THE DEVELOPERS WILL
ALWAYS WIN. >> IT IS MY HOPE THAT THE CITY
CAN FIND A WAY TO FAST TRACK AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECTS
IN THE FUTURE BUT STILL ALLOW THE CONCERNS OF THE COMMUNITY
TO BE ADDRESSED. I ALSO HOPE THAT EACH
SUPERVISOR HERE CONSIDER THIS APPEAL HAPPENING IN THEIR
DISTRICT AS WELL AND NOT JUST DISTRICT NINE BECAUSE THIS IS
SOMETHING THAT CAN HAPPEN IN ANY DISTRICT AND IN FACT CAN
STITCH UNITS THROUGHOUT THE CITY.
>> THE APPEAL IS A CITYWIDE THIS APPEAL IS A CITYWIDE PLEA
TO SAVE EXISTING GREEN SPACE FROM BEING LOST OF DEVELOPMENT.
I'M OLD ENOUGH TO REMEMBER THE FIGHT FOR GREEN SPACE IN THE
70S. IT WAS IMPORTANT THEN AND IT'S
IMPORTANT NOW. PLEASE CONSIDER OUR APPEAL TO
REZONE THIS PARK. THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME.
THANKS. >> WE'RE GOING TO.
I DON'T SEE ANY COMMENTS OR QUESTIONS FROM COLLEAGUES SO
MR.. >> MR. PRESIDENT, MAY I JUST
ASK THE AUDIENCE TO HOLD THEIR APPLAUSE?
THERE IS A BROAD RULE THAT THERE IS NO AUDIBLE SOUNDS OF
SUPPORT OR AGAINST. IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO EXPRESS
YOURSELF JUST WAVE YOUR HANDS AS SUCH.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
ALL RIGHT. I'M SORRY, I.
WE'RE ENTERING INTO THE PUBLIC COMMENTS PHASE HERE AND SHOULD
I INTRODUCE THE NEXT SPEAKERS THIS SHOULD THE SPEAKERS JUST
COME UP? >> WE'LL TAKE CARE OF IT FIRST
BECAUSE WE'LL BE INVITED TO LINE UP ON THE RIGHT SIDE OR
YOUR YOU'RE RIGHT MY LEFT. AND THEN WE'LL BE GIVEN TWO
MINUTES EACH AND SO LET'S GO INTO PUBLIC COMMENT IN SUPPORT
OF THE APPEAL. >> MADAM CLERK, YOU WANT TO
CALL THE FIRST SPEAKER? THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
YOU MAY LINE UP ON YOUR RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER.
YES. COME TO THE PODIUM IF YOU ARE
IN SUPPORT OF THE APPELLANT OR THE REPRESENTATIVE.
YOU'LL HAVE TWO MINUTES TO SPEAK.
THIS IS FOR THE APPEAL FOR 3333 MISSION STREET AND 190
COLERIDGE STREET. >> SURE IF YOU USE THE PODIUM
WE THERE'S A TIMER ON THE PODIUM WHICH WILL HELP YOU KNOW
WHERE YOU ARE AT IN THE TWO MINUTES.
>> THAT'S SCARY. >> WHEN WHEN DO YOU TELL ME
WHEN TO START AND BEFORE YOU START I'LL JUST LET YOU KNOW
THAT EACH OF YOU MAY HAVE YOUR OWN TWO MINUTES OR YOU MAY
PRESENT AS A GROUP AND ONLY ONE OF YOU SPEAK AND THEN YOU'LL
HAVE A SEAT. >> ALL RIGHT.
I'M STARTING YOUR TIMER NOW. HI, MY NAME IS MARTHA HUDDLE
AND I'VE LIVED AT 180 ONE QUARTER STREET DIRECTLY ACROSS
FROM THE PARK FOR 23 YEARS. I RAISED MY FOSTER SON HERE
AND WE USE THE PARK REGULARLY FOR PLAY PICNICS AND MANY
BIRTHDAY PARTIES. I PERSONALLY CONSULTED TOO WITH
TWO DIFFERENT ARCHITECTS AND A REAL ESTATE ATTORNEY ABOUT THE
PLANS AND IT IS POSSIBLE TO RETAIN MOST OF THE CURRENT PARK
SIZE AND STILL BUILD 70 UNITS OF AFFORDABLE SENIOR HOUSING
WHICH IS WHAT THIS APPEAL IS ABOUT.
WE'VE BEEN ASKING FOR THE PROPOSED PARK SIZE TO BE
INCREASED FOR THE PAST TWO YEARS.
HOWEVER, DUE TO SB 35 NO COMMUNITY COLLABORATION IS
REQUIRED AND WITHOUT IT HISTORY AND LOCAL AREA KNOWLEDGE ARE
LOST AND MISGUIDED PLANS GET APPROVED.
>> THERE IS A TRAFFIC AND PUBLIC SAFETY CONCERN WITH
THE PLANNED LOADING ZONE ON COLERIDGE STREET.
COLERIDGE STREET BECOMES ONE WAY GOING NORTHBOUND AS
MIRALLAS STREET. THEREFORE ANY PASSENGER DROP
OFF PICK UP OR DELIVERY VEHICLE NEEDS A PLACE TO TURN AROUND TO
BE FACING THE LAWFUL DIRECTION ON THE STREET AND TO USE THAT
LOADING ZONE. CURRENTLY THERE IS A DRIVEWAY
FOR 190 COMMERCIAL PARK HOMES BUT WITH THAT TAKEN OUT, WHERE
WILL THESE VEHICLES TURN AROUND PRIVATE DRIVEWAYS?
IT SEEMS THAT BOTH THE CITY PLANNERS AND THE DEVELOPERS
MISSES TRAFFIC SAFETY ISSUE WHEN WHEN PLANNING THE LOADING
ZONE. >> THIS ISSUE COULD BE
MITIGATED AND AVOID POTENTIAL LAWSUITS AND FURTHER DELAYS OF
THE PROJECT IF THE DEVELOPERS WOULD CHANGE THE PLANS TO ADD
BACK SOME OF THE PARK PARCEL AND ADD A DRIVEWAY TO THE
LOADING ZONE AREA FOR A TURNAROUND SPACE AND FOR PARK
MAINTENANCE VEHICLE ACCESS. JUST BECAUSE THE PLANS HAVE
BEEN APPROVED BY THE CITY DOES NOT MEAN THAT THE AGENCY CAN'T
MAKE CHANGES INCLUDING ENLARGING PART PARCEL
AND SUBMITTING A NEW REZONING REQUEST.
IT IS NOT OUR FAULT THAT THIS MAY DELAY THE PROJECT A LITTLE
LONGER. IF THE AGENCY HAD BEEN WILLING
TO COLLABORATE WITH US WE WOULD NOT BE HERE TODAY.
A SMALL DELAY IN THE PROJECT IS WORTH THE LARGER GAIN OF PARK
SPACE AND THE SAFETY FOR THE COMMUNITY AND THE CITY.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
LET'S WELCOME OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
>> I'M READING THIS ON BEHALF OF A MAY I ASK YOU TO SPEAK
DIRECTLY INTO THAT MICROPHONE? >> THERE YOU GO.
THANK YOU. IS THIS BETTER?
>> YES. OKAY.
READING ON BEHALF OF AN ANONYMOUS RESIDENT I AM A
NEIGHBOR ON COLERIDGE DIRECTLY ACROSS THE PLANNED DEVELOPMENT
. >> I WAS BORN IN SAN FRANCISCO
TO A WORKING CLASS FAMILY AND EXCEPT FOR A FEW YEARS AWAY
FOR SCHOOL AND WORK I'VE BEEN A LIFELONG RESIDENT OF BERNAL
HEIGHTS ALL IN ALL 30 YEARS. I WANT TO START THIS MESSAGE TO
STATE THAT I AM A HOMEOWNER AND THAT I'M ALSO 100% PRO
AFFORDABLE HOUSING. >> SO BE AND SEES MESSAGE THAT
HOMEOWNERS ARE TRYING TO STOP THE BUILDING OF A NEW SENIOR
AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS AN UNTRUE BLANKET STATEMENT.
>> I SUPPORT THIS APPEAL FOR INCREASING THE PARK SQUARE
FOOTAGE THAN IS CURRENTLY PLANNED FOR BECAUSE IT IS THE
PEOPLE WHO CURRENTLY LIVE HERE WHO WILL BE THE ONES MOST
IMPACTED BY THE DEVELOPMENT WITH ONGOING AND PLANNED
DEVELOPMENT PROJECTS IN THE IMMEDIATE SURROUNDING AREA.
IT IS ONLY SENSIBLE THAT WE PRESERVE A FAIR BALANCE OF
DENSITY AND OPEN SPACE. THIS IS IN ACCORDANCE WITH GOOD
URBAN PLANNING, GOOD URBAN PLANNING.
GREEN SPACES ARE ESSENTIAL FOR ENVIRONMENTAL SOCIAL
AND PSYCHOLOGICAL WELL-BEING ENSURING THE LONG TERM AND LONG
TERM ENJOY ABILITY OF A NEIGHBORHOOD.
MORE AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS NEEDED BUT IT SHOULD BE DONE
IN CLOSE CONSULTATION WITH EXISTING NEIGHBORS FROM THE
OUTSET OF THE PROJECT BECAUSE AGAIN IT IS THEY WHO ARE MOST
IMPACTED. OTHERWISE IT DRIVES A RIFT
BETWEEN CURRENT SAN FRANCISCO NEIGHBORS ON THE ONE SIDE
AND THE CITY AND NEW NEIGHBORS ON THE OTHER.
AND FOR FOLKS WHO ARE OTHERWISE SYMPATHETIC TO THE CAUSE OF
AFFORDABLE HOUSING, THEY WILL BE SWAYED AWAY FROM THIS
POSITION. >> TO WRAP IT UP, I AM FOR THE
EXPANSION OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING ACROSS THE STREET.
I JUST WANT THE CITY AND SUPERVISORS AND DEVELOPERS
TO UNDERSTAND THAT OUR INPUT MATTERS TOO.
COMMUNITY CENTERED DEVELOPMENT IS THE ONLY SUSTAINABLE
SOLUTION THAT WOULDN'T RESULT IN DIVISION AND POLICY
WHIPLASH. THANK YOU FOR LISTENING.
>> COLERIDGE NEIGHBOR. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> HELLO, MY NAME IS LINDA KIT LENTZ AND I HAVE BEEN RESIDING
AS WELL AS BEING A HOMEOWNER FOR THE PAST 36.5 YEARS.
AT 193 COLERIDGE STREET I'M ALSO A BUSINESS OWNER.
>> I HAVE ALWAYS ENJOYED SEEING CHILDREN USE THE PLAYGROUND
WHICH IS ALMOST DIRECTLY ACROSS THE STREET FROM MY HOME.
>> THERE HAVE BEEN EVEN BIRTHDAY PARTIES AND OTHER
PUBLIC EVENTS HELD THERE AND AS FAR AS I KNOW I'VE ALWAYS
ENJOYED A MEETING FRIENDS AND FAMILY OVER THERE EVEN
HAVING A CUP OF COFFEE WITH A FRIEND AND JUST ENJOYING THE
OUTSIDE AIR. >> MY FRIENDS WHO VISITED ME
FROM OUT OF TOWN WOULD BRING THEIR CHILDREN AND GO AND ENJOY
THE PLAYGROUND AND IT MADE THAT MORE INVITING FOR THEM TO COME
AND VISIT ME. >> THEN COVID HAPPENED IN 2020
AND THE PARK HAD TO BE SHUT DOWN ONCE AGAIN WHEN COVID WAS
LIFTED. I WAS SURPRISED THAT IT WASN'T
REOPENED BACK OPEN TO THE PUBLIC.
JUST IT WAS JUST SITTING THERE. OPEN SPACE, WASTED LAND WASTED.
>> IT WAS REALLY VERY SAD INDEED.
I REALIZE THAT THE AGENCY IS PLANNING TO ADD ANOTHER 105
UNITS IN THAT AREA AND THERE IS A PROPOSAL TO ADD THOSE UNITS
ABOVE THE SAFEWAY ALL JUST A BLOCK AWAY.
>> WE CAN'T AFFORD TO LOSE PRECIOUS OPEN SPACE WHERE THERE
IS AIR. AND I'M NOT AGAINST AFFORDABLE
HOUSING. I'M IN FAVOR OF IT.
LIKE ANYBODY ELSE THAT'S GOT A MIND OF THEIR OWN.
>> BUT THIS IS A BIG CONCERN. I'M IN FAVOR OF ALL THIS
HAPPENING BUT I DON'T WANT TO LOSE THE PRECIOUS SPACE OF
MOTHER NATURE. PLEASE LISTEN TO US.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER. >> HI.
I'M MARY KEARNEY. I'LL BE 87 THIS APRIL AND I'VE
BEEN RESIDING AT COLLEGE PARK SINCE 2010 ALMOST 17 YEARS.
>> YOU COULD SAY I ARRIVED DURING THE GOLDEN AGE OF OUR
COMMUNITY PARK A TIME WHEN NANNIES BROUGHT THEIR CHARGERS
TO THE PLAYGROUND. WHEN NEW MOMS FOUND ON THE
BENCHES AND CHATTED WHILE ROCKING THEIR BABIES IN THEIR
PRAMS WHEN PRESCHOOLS BROUGHT THEIR ENTIRE CLASSES TO ENJOY
PLAYING KICKBALL IN THE GRASS OR SWING ON THE SWINGS OR CLIMB
THE JUNGLE GYM A TIME WHEN EACH OF MY GRANDCHILDREN I HAVE
THREE VISITED ME AND I HELPED EACH INTERN LEARN TO SWING FROM
THE OVERHEAD BARS. A TIME WHEN FAMILIES HAD
PICNICS ON THE PARK TABLES AND FATHERS TAUGHT THEIR
CHILDREN HOW TO PLAY CATCH ON THE GRASS.
>> I ENTERTAINED MY IN-LAWS WITH SNACKS ON A PARK TABLE
WHILE THE CHILDREN PLAYED. IT WAS A FUN PLACE WHERE
CHILDREN, PARENTS, GRANDPARENTS, TEACHERS
AND CAREGIVERS MINGLED. WHEN COVID CAME THE PARKS
CLOSED DOWN AND WAS ALLOWED TO GO INTO DISREPAIR.
>> MOST PEOPLE WHO ARRIVED AT 190 THAT'S COLLEGE SENIOR
HOUSING AFTER COVID HAD NO EXPERIENCE OF THE JOY THAT PARK
BROUGHT TO SO MANY RESIDENTS AND NEIGHBORS ALIKE.
>> IT IS MY UNDERSTANDING THAT WHEN THE SENIOR RESIDENT WAS
BUILT IN THE 1980S IT WAS SPECIFIED THAT IT MUST BE
INCLUDED IN THE PLANS. THE PARK MUST BE INCLUDED
IN THE PLANS. THE NEW PROPOSAL TO CUT THE
CONCRETE SITTING AREA AND REDUCE THE GRASSY AREA OF
THE NEWLY CONCEIVED PARK WOULD RUIN THAT ORIGINAL PURPOSE.
WHERE WOULD THE GROWN UPS SIT? WATCH THEIR CHILDREN AND MAKE
FRIENDS? HOW WOULD FRIENDS, WALKERS
AND WHEELCHAIRS NAVIGATE WITHOUT SOLID FOOTING?
>> WHERE IS IT? THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
APOLOGIES FOR CUTTING YOU OFF BUT WE ARE PROVIDING EVERYONE
THE SAME TWO MINUTES. >> NEXT SPEAKER HELLO MY NAME
IS HEATHER KAUFMAN. I LIVE ON VIRGINIA AVENUE
IN BERNAL HEIGHTS. I'M READING THIS FOR ANOTHER
RESIDENT AND THEY ARE ANONYMOUS.
WE ARE WRITING AS RESIDENTS OF COLERIDGE PARK HOMES.
THAT'S WHEN 90 COLERIDGE BEFORE THE PANDEMIC CLOSED OUR MUCH
USED AND MUCH BELOVED BERNAL COLERIDGE PARK IN BERNAL.
IT WAS A PLACE WHERE NEIGHBORS WOULD MEET EACH OTHER IN A
TYPICAL SAN FRANCISCO WAY. ONE DAY I WOULD SIT NEXT TO A
NEIGHBOR WHO RELIES ON A LOCAL FOOD BANK.
THE NEXT DAY I MIGHT SIT TO NEXT TO A NEIGHBOR WHO HAD JUST
PAID OFF HER HOUSE AND WAS LOOKING TOWARDS FORWARD TO
RETIREMENT FRIENDSHIPS AND NEIGHBORLY SUPPORT
FLOURISHED IN OUR PARK IN WAYS NOT POSSIBLE IN INDOOR SPACES
UNDER LED LIGHTS. WHEN OUR NEIGHBOR SAW AN ONLINE
PETITION WHICH READ SAVE OUR PARK HELP OPEN REOPEN COLERIDGE
PARK AND STILL ADD SENIOR HOUSING, MANY NEIGHBORS OLD
AND NEW RENTERS AND HOMEOWNERS SIGNED THE PETITION ESPECIALLY
AFTER UNDERSTANDING THAT 105 NEW SENIOR APARTMENTS WOULD BE
ADDED TO THE SQUARE BLOCK RADIUS OF 3300 AND THE PROPOSED
3333 MISSION STREET DEVELOPMENT.
IT SEEMED COMMON SENSE THAT WE RECOGNIZE THE NEED TO PRESERVE
AS MUCH OF THE PARK AS POSSIBLE.
NEARLY 400 NEIGHBORS INCLUDING OURSELVES NOT A SMALL NUMBER
MADE UP OF FAMILIES WITH SMALL CHILDREN, FIXED INCOME SENIORS,
RENTERS, WORKING SERVICE JOBS STUDENTS AND PEOPLE WITH TECH
JOBS. ALL AGREED THAT MORE PEOPLE
MEANS MORE NEED OF GREEN NATURAL OUTDOOR PARK SPACE
AND FRESH AIR. >> THE APPEAL IS FOR TWO REASON
THE REQUEST THE PNC SUBMITTED IS NOT FRIVOLOUS IT CONTINUES
THE NEIGHBORS DESIRE FOR FURTHER DIALOG ABOUT A BIGGER
PARK TO CALL IT FRIVOLOUS IS INSULTING AND DISMISSIVE.
PEOPLE IN THIS NEIGHBORHOOD SUPPORT EACH OTHER AND HAVE
BEEN DISAPPOINTED TO SAY THE LEAST THAT THE AGENCY HAS
CHOSEN TO FRAME THIS ISSUE IN THE AIR WITH US OR AGAINST
US WAY OF IMPLYING THAT ANYONE SIGNING THE PETITION OR
SUPPORTING THE APPEAL IS AGAINST AFFORDABLE SENIOR
HOUSING. THIS IS ABSOLUTELY THANK YOU
FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
HELLO I'M READING THIS ON BEHALF OF A RESIDENT OF THE
SAME PLACE OF THE COLERIDGE PARK WHO REMAINS ANONYMOUS.
>> I AM A RESIDENT OF COLLEGE PARK HOMES AND VOCIFEROUSLY
IN FAVOR OF SENIOR HOUSING. INDEED I LIVE IN SENIOR HOUSING
AND I'M GRATEFUL FOR THE OPPORTUNITY TO HAVE A BULWARK
AGAINST SPIRALING HOUSING COSTS RISING IN SAN FRANCISCO.
I HOPE MANY MORE SENIORS CAN BE SIMILARLY SHELTERED.
I'M ALSO GRATEFUL FOR THE VIVID COMMUNITY AT COLERIDGE PARK
HOMES WHICH HAS BECOME AN INTEGRAL PART OF MY LIFE.
I WANT TO CALL ATTENTION TO THE VERY NAME OF THIS RESIDENCE
PARK. >> IT'S RIGHT IN THEIR
COLERIDGE PARK HOMES. THE PARK IS IMPORTANT TO US
HERE AT COLERIDGE IN OUR LATER YEARS.
>> THE OPEN SPACE OUTSIDE LITERALLY THE FRONT YARD IS A
FOCAL POINT FOR THE IMMEDIATE NEIGHBORHOOD AND CERTAINLY A
HIT WITH CHILDREN. >> THE PARK HAS LAID FALLOW,
CLOSED FOR MANY YEARS SINCE THE PANDEMIC.
THE NEIGHBORHOOD WILL BE THRILLED BY ITS RETURN.
>> AS I UNDERSTAND IT, THE PROPOSAL BY THE AGENCY WITH THE
WORTHY AIM OF BRINGING AN ADDITIONAL 70 UNITS OF SENIOR
HOUSING WOULD RESULT IN THE EXISTING PARK EXITING THEIR
PLAN. MISSING QUITE A LARGE CHUNK AT
A TIME WHEN THE NEED FOR PARK CAN ONLY INCREASE WITH THE 335
NEW UNITS ACROSS THE STREET AT 3300 MISSION AND THE 17 NEW
UNITS PROPOSED FOR THE 3333 MISSION SITE YET ALTERATIONS TO
THE PLAN COULD PRESERVE BOTH THE 70 NEW SENIOR UNITS
AND MOST OF THE PARK. >> TO IMPLY OR TO STATE THAT
ANYONE OPPOSING THE TRIMMING DOWN OF THEIR NEIGHBORHOOD PARK
IS EXHIBITING EVIDENCE OF INHERENT OPPOSITION TO SENIOR
HOUSING SEEMS DISINGENUOUS AND NOT AT ALL THE CASE HERE.
>> YES, BUILDING PLANS WOULD NEED TO BE REWORKED AS WAS DONE
AT B H AND CS NEW SENIOR HOUSING PROJECT AT 3300 MISSION
AND A MORE HOMOGENOUS BUILDING HAS RISEN WHEN THERE WAS A LATE
MAJOR CHANGE WHICH RESULTED IN PLANS BEING REWORKED SO PLAN
CHANGES MIGHT BE VIEWED AS WHAT HAPPENS IN CONSTRUCTION.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. JUST A REMINDER WE'RE SETTING
THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES AND ON THE PODIUM THERE IS A
CLOCK SO YOU CAN SEE WHERE YOU'RE AT IN YOUR TWO MINUTE
PRESENTATION. >> WELCOME.
THANK YOU. MY NAME IS MARIA ALDUS.
I'VE BEEN LIVING ON COLERIDGE STREET SINCE 1963 AND SINCE I
WAS VERY SMALL AND HAVE ENJOYED THE PARK WHEN IT WAS BUILT
IN THE 80S ENJOYED THAT OPEN AREA, OPEN SPACE FOR US BECAUSE
IT WAS JUST A BIG BOWLING ALLEY PARKING LOT BEFORE.
>> THE PROBABLY THE ONLY SUPERVISOR HERE WHO'S FAMILIAR
WITH OUR PARK IS OUR SUPERVISOR.
>> BUT IT IS IT WAS A PARK THAT WAS VERY VISITED AS HAS BEEN
EXPLAINED BEFORE BY THE THE SENIORS IN THAT HOUSING.
>> THE DAY CARE PROVIDERS AROUND OUR NEIGHBORHOOD NANNIES
WOULD ALWAYS BE THERE EVERY DAY.
I MYSELF WOULD ENJOY IT WHEN I WAS YOUNGER AND I WOULD TAKE MY
DAUGHTER THERE WHEN SHE WAS SMALL.
>> THERE WAS ALWAYS BIRTHDAY PARTIES.
THERE WERE MEETINGS. IT WAS A PLACE TO JOIN AND MEET
OTHER PEOPLE. IT WAS TO THROW A BALL AROUND,
PLAY SOCCER. >> IT WAS JUST VERY USED
EVERYTHING ALL DAY BY EVERYBODY IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
IT'S NOT A FAMOUS PARK LIKE PRESIDIO TUNNEL TOPS LIKE
SUNSET DUNES LIKE ALL THESE NEW SPACES THAT THE SUPERVISORS
HAVE SUPPORTED. >> BUT IT IS A VERY IMPORTANT A
HUGELY IMPORTANT PART TO OUR NEIGHBORHOOD.
IT'S VERY IMPORTANT TO US. >> SO I HOPE THAT YOU HEARING
ALL OF THIS INFORMATION AND PEOPLE SPEAKING ABOUT THE
NEED FOR THIS PARK ESPECIALLY WITH MORE DENSITY WHICH WE ARE
NOT AGAINST THAT YOU WILL SUPPORT MAKING SURE THAT THIS
PARK REMAINS AN OPEN, VIABLE SPACE FOR EVERYONE IN THE
COMMUNITY AND SURROUNDING AREA AS A LARGE AREA NOT THE REDUCED
SPACE THAT THE AGENCY WANTS TO MAKE AND THE DEVELOPERS WANT.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME'S BARBARA HANDLER. I LIVE DIRECTLY ACROSS THE
STREET FROM THE PARK AND I DON'T HAVE PREPARED REMARKS SO
I'M GOING TO KEEP THIS VERY BRIEF.
I'VE LIVED IN MY APARTMENT THERE FOR SOME 24 YEARS
AND IT'S A VERY NICE NEIGHBORHOOD OF GENERALLY TWO
STOREY HOMES. QUITE NEIGHBORLY.
PLEASANT, RELATIVELY QUIET CONSIDERING ITS PROXIMITY TO
MISSION STREET. >> I FIND THE PORTRAYAL OF THE
PEOPLE PROTESTING THIS DEVELOPMENT AS HEARTLESS NIMBYS
IS VERY DISHEARTENING BECAUSE THAT'S NOT THE CASE.
>> I'M VERY CONCERNED ABOUT HOUSING IN SAN FRANCISCO BOTH
FOR THE HOMELESS AND FOR SENIOR CITIZENS ESPECIALLY AS I MYSELF
AM A SENIOR CITIZEN AND I'M NEWLY CONSCIOUS OF THE NEED FOR
BOTH AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND COMMUNITY.
>> PART OF MY CONCERN IS THE ADDITIONAL DENSITY AND THE
DESTRUCTION OF THE LOOK AT THE NEIGHBORHOOD WHICH IS A CLASSIC
SAN FRANCISCO GO NEIGHBORHOOD WITH BEAUTIFUL HOMES.
MOST OF THE PEOPLE WHO LIVE IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD ARE SENIOR
CITIZENS THEMSELVES NOT OPPOSED TO SENIOR HOUSING ONLY TO THE
SHAPE THIS DEVELOPMENT IS TAKING.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME. >> THE NEXT SPEAKER MEMBERS OF
THE BOARD. MY NAME IS BUDDY TATE CHOI.
I HAVE LIVED ON KOREA STREET FOR 49 YEARS.
>> THIS YEAR WILL BE 50. MY WIFE WILL TELL YOU THE
HISTORY OF OUR INVOLVEMENT IN THE COMMUNITY AND THE
BUILDING OF THE COLERIDGE PARK HOMES AND THE PLAY SPACE.
I ONLY HAVE TWO COMMENTS. ONE.
WE ARE 100% FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
TWO. WE ARE 100% FOR OPEN SPACE FOR
OUR COMMUNITY. AND FINALLY I JUST WANT TO
POINT OUT I'M A VERY OLD MAN BUT WHEN I WAS YOUNG I WAS A
SOCIAL WORKER AND I SPENT MY DAYS IN CHINATOWN WORKING
AND ONE OF THE PRIVILEGES I HAD WAS BEING ON THE BOARD OF THE
CHINATOWN DEVELOPMENT CENTER. AS YOU ALL KNOW, ONE OF THE
PREMIER HOUSING AFFORDABLE ORGANIZATIONS IN THIS CITY I
HAPPEN TO BE THE PRESIDENT FOR A COUPLE OF YEARS TO ONE OF THE
ROOMS THAT WE HAD AS BOARD MEMBERS WAS WE RESPECTED
EVERYONE EVEN THOSE WHO DID AGREE WITH US.
THERE WAS NO NAME CALLING. WE DIDN'T DO ANYTHING TO VILIFY
THEM. WE DID NOT PUT UP POSTERS OR
CALL MEETINGS. SO I WOULD ASK IF WE MAY
NEGOTIATE THIS WITH RESPECT I THINK WE CAN MAKE IT WORK.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
BEFORE THE NEXT SPEAKER, IS THERE ANY OTHER MEMBER OF THE
PUBLIC IN THE PUBLIC GALLERY WHO WOULD LIKE TO SUPPORT THE
APPELLANT FOR THE 3333 AND THE 190 COLERIDGE STREET PROJECT
FOR THE APPEAL SPECIFICALLY? >> ALL RIGHT.
WELCOME. I'M GOING TROY TATE.
>> YOU JUST HEARD MY HUSBAND WHEN WE MOVED INTO OUR HOME
IN COLERIDGE STREET IN 1977. ACROSS THE STREET WAS AN
ABANDONED LOT THAT WAS FENCED OFF WITH A CHAIN LINK FENCE
AND WAS FILLED WITH BROKEN GLASS AND TRASH.
>> SO WE WERE PARTICULARLY GLAD WHEN THE AGENCY PROPOSED
COLERIDGE PARK HOMES. >> AND SINCE MY HUSBAND AND I
HAD BEEN WORKING FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN CHINATOWN WE WERE
DELIGHTED TO COLLABORATE AS COLERIDGE STREET NEIGHBORS.
>> AND IN 19 1987 THE PARK WE DESIGNATED SINCE THEN HAS BEEN
AN IMPORTANT ASSET TO THE NEIGHBORHOOD AND WE HAD A MAJOR
PART IN DESIGNING THE PARK AND ARE GRATEFUL FOR THAT
OPPORTUNITY. UNFORTUNATELY THE PLAY
STRUCTURE WAS NOT MAINTAINED PROPERLY AND THE PARK CLOSED
IN 2020 WHEN THE AGENCY PROPOSED AN ADDITIONAL 70 UNITS
OF SENIOR HOUSING. WE WERE SUPPORTIVE AND WE
ASSUMED THAT WE WOULD HAVE A SIMILAR COLLABORATIVE
RELATIONSHIP. BUT THEN WE LEARNED THAT THE
PARK WOULD BE REDUCED BY 42%. >> WE WERE STUNNED THAT UNLIKE
OUR PREVIOUS COLLABORATION NOW B AND B AGENCY REFUSED TO WORK
WITH COLD STREET NEIGHBORS OR COMMUNICATE WITH THEM.
OUR QUESTIONS WERE NEVER ANSWERED.
>> FOR INSTANCE, WHY WITH TWO OTHER LOBBIES IS HAVING AN
EXCEPTIONALLY LARGE LOBBY OR ANCHORAGE PREFERABLE TO HAVING
ADDITIONAL OPEN SPACE? >> WE WANT ALL 70 UNITS OF
HOUSING. >> WE BELIEVE IT CAN HAPPEN
AND STILL INCREASE THE SIZE OF EVERY PART BY REDUCING THE
LOBBY. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> MR. PRESIDENT, THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. PUBLIC COMMENT IN SUPPORT OF
THE APPEAL IS NOW CLOSED AND NOW WE WILL GIVE THE
REPRESENTATIVES OF CITY DEPARTMENTS UP TO TEN MINUTES
AND I THINK WE'RE STARTING PLANNING OR PUBLIC WORKS OR
OKAY. >> THANK YOU, SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS ELIAS FRENCH. I'M HERE FOR PUBLIC WORKS AS
CITY AND COUNTY SURVEYOR, THE LEAD AGENCY THAT PROCESSES
SUBDIVISIONS IN SAN FRANCISCO. I'LL GIVE A BRIEF SUMMARY OF
THE PROJECT FROM OUR PERSPECTIVE THROUGH OUR AGENCY
. >> ON MAY 19TH, 2024 OR 2024 WE
RECEIVED A FINAL MAP APPLICATION FOR THE ABOVE
REFERENCE PROPERTY OR THE SUBJECT PROPERTY.
IN JUNE 2024 WE SUBMITTED IT TO CITY AGENCIES FOR CIRCULATION
AND FOR THEIR COMMENTS. >> THEN IN JUNE 2025 WE
RECEIVED A REVISED TENTATIVE MAP CHANGING THE PROJECT
ENTITLEMENTS PROPOSED SLIGHTLY AFTER A REFERRAL TO CITY
AGENCIES AND THEIR APPROVAL. WE ISSUED APPROVAL OF THE
SUBDIVISION TENTATIVE MAP ON OCTOBER 2025 FOLLOWED BY THIS
APPEAL. THE SUMMARY OF THE PROJECT IS
THE EXISTING SITE CONSISTS OF THREE AIRSPACE SUBDIVISION
PARCELS WHICH CORRESPOND TO THE EXISTING SENIOR HOUSING
BUILDING. THE PARK AND THE COMMERCIAL
SPACE AND GARAGE RESPECTIVELY. IT ALSO ENTITLES A CERTAIN
NUMBER OF CONDOMINIUM UNITS FIVE RESIDENTIAL AND COMMERCIAL
WITHIN LOT ONE WHICH IS THE PARCEL PROPOSED FOR NEW
CONSTRUCTION. WE FOUND THAT MAP SATISFIED THE
TECHNICAL REQUIREMENTS CONFORM AND CITY PLANNING FOUND THAT IT
CONFORMED WITH THE GENERAL PLAN AND ALL APPLICABLE CODES.
THE APPELLANTS LETTER RAISES CONCERNS ABOUT THE SIZE OF THE
REDUCTION IN SIZE OF THE PARK. THE MAP CONCERNS ITSELF
ENTIRELY WITH THE DELINEATION OF PARCEL BOUNDARIES WHICH ARE
NOT DO NOT PERTAIN TO THE APPROVAL OF THE BUILDING SIZE
AND SHAPE WHICH WERE ALREADY APPROVED.
MINISTERIAL LETTER BY PLANNING .
ACCORDINGLY AND AS MUCH AS THE MAP CONFORM TO THE SUBDIVISION
MAP ACT REQUIRED FINDINGS TO APPROVE TENTATIVE MAPS.
WE APPROVE WE HAD APPROVED THE MAP AND AND AS MUCH AS THE
APPEAL ADDRESSES CONCERNS WHICH ARE NOT RELEVANT TO THE MAP
AND AREN'T WEREN'T BEFORE OUR OFFICE FOR REVIEW.
WE BELIEVE THE MAP APPROVAL SHOULD STAND AS ISSUED.
>> THANK YOU. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS
AUDREY MALONEY, ACTING MANAGER OF LEGISLATIVE AFFAIRS FOR THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT. ON OCTOBER 28TH OF 2025 THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT APPROVED THE PROPOSED SUBDIVISION
REFERRAL FROM THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS.
THE APPROVAL WAS BASED ON OUR DETERMINATION SHOWN THAT THE
SUBDIVISION IS CONSISTENT WITH THE PROJECT THAT WAS PREVIOUSLY
APPROVED BY THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT ON APRIL 16TH OF
2025 AND THAT IT ALIGNS WITH BOTH THE PLANNING CODE AND THE
GENERAL PLAN. WE'D LIKE TO ADDRESS A KEY
CONCERN RAISED BY THE APPELLANTS REGARDING COLERIDGE
PARK. THEIR CLAIM IS THAT THE
SUBDIVISION WILL REDUCE THE SIZE OF THE PARK.
IN FACT THE SUBDIVISION DOES NOT REDUCE THE SIZE OF
COLERIDGE PARK. RATHER IT REFLECTS THE
RECONFIGURATION AND REDUCTION IN SIZE THAT WAS ALREADY
APPROVED UNDER THE SB 35 DEVELOPMENT APPLICATION.
THE TENTATIVE MAP APPLICATION SIMPLY UPDATES THE LOT
BOUNDARIES OF EXISTING LOT 1 TO 1 TO MATCH THAT PREVIOUSLY
APPROVED RECONFIGURATION. FOR THESE REASONS AND AS
DETAILED IN OUR WRITTEN RESPONSE AND THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT CASE FILE WE RECOMMEND THAT THE BOARD UPHOLD
THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS DECISION TO APPROVE THE
TENTATIVE MAP APPLICATION FOR THIS PROJECT.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
MS. MALONEY. I DON'T SEE ANY BUT I DO.
>> SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANKS PRESIDENT MIDDLEMAN.
I HAVE SOME QUESTIONS FOR A FEW DEPARTMENTS.
SO MR. FRENCH FOR PUBLIC WORKS JUST TO MAKE IT CLEAR, DID YOU
CONSIDER ANY OF THE DESIGN CONCERNS BROUGHT UP BY THE
APPELLANTS IN APPROVING THE MAP HERE AND WHY OR WHY NOT?
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FIELDER.
THE DESIGN CONCERNS RAISED BY THE APPELLANT AND THE DESIGN OF
THE SHAPE SIZE MASSING OF THE BUILDINGS AND PARK ARE NOT PART
OF THE SCOPE OF REVIEW FOR SUBDIVISION APPROVAL.
IN THIS INSTANCE THE BUILDING AND DEVELOPMENT FORM WAS
ALREADY APPROVED BY PLANNING AND WE REVIEW THE PROPOSED
BOUNDARY LINE DELINEATIONS WITH RESPECT TO THE APPROVED
BUILDINGS NOT THE SHAPE SIZE FORM OF THE BUILDINGS
THEMSELVES. >> THANK YOU.
AND MS.. MALONEY FOR PLANNING.
WAS THERE ANY OPPORTUNITY FOR NEIGHBORHOOD FEEDBACK
IN REVIEWING THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING APPLICATION FOR 3333
MISSION STREET? >> WHY ARE WE NOT?
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FIELDER AUDRA
MALONEY FOR THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT.
BECAUSE THIS IS AN SB 35 PROJECT OR NOW MORE COMMONLY
UNDERSTOOD TO BE SB FOR 23. STATE LAW RESTRICTS THE CITY'S
ABILITY TO MODIFY OR EVEN GIVE FEEDBACK TO CODE COMPLIANT
PROJECTS ESPECIALLY IF THOSE MODIFICATIONS WOULD INHIBIT OR
CHILL THE APPROVAL OR IF THE MODIFICATIONS WOULD INCREASE
PROJECT COSTS. >> AND WHERE SHOULD NEIGHBORS
BRING FEEDBACK REGARDING THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECT?
>> AGAIN SUPERVISOR. UNFORTUNATELY STATE LAW
RESTRICTS THIS IS A STATE LAW PROJECT.
IT IS TRULY OUT OF THE BOUNDS OF OUR JURISDICTION.
>> THE ONLY THING THAT THE LOCAL JURISDICTION HAS CONTROL
OVER IS DETERMINING WHETHER THE PROJECT IS CODE COMPLIANT WHICH
WE DID DETERMINE IN THIS CASE. >> THANK YOU.
FOR OUR CITY ATTORNEY, I JUST WANT TO BE CLEAR ABOUT WHAT WE
SHOULD CONSIDER WHEN REVIEWING THIS MAP APPEAL.
>> DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY BRAD ROSSI THE QUESTION BEFORE THE
BOARD IS WHETHER THE MAP COMPLIES WITH THE SUBDIVISION
OF THE STATE LAW AND IT LIMITS WHAT THE BOARD CAN CONSIDER.
I THINK THE PUBLIC WORKS DEPARTMENT HAS LAID OUT SORT OF
THE FACTORS THAT ARE AT ISSUE BEFORE THE BOARD AND THAT'S THE
SCOPE OF WHAT YOU HAVE TO CONSIDER HERE.
>> OKAY. SO IF I'M UNDERSTANDING
CORRECTLY, THE BOARD SHOULD NOT CONSIDER QUESTIONS AROUND THE
PRODUCT DESIGN. >> THE BOARD CAN CONSIDER
COMPLIANCE WITH STATE LAW AND I THINK THAT THERE WAS DESIGN OF
THE PROJECT. QUESTIONS ARE NOT PART OF WHAT
THE STATE LAW REQUIRES FOR YOUR CONSIDERATION UNDER THIS
APPEAL. >> THANK YOU.
THAT'S ALL MY QUESTIONS FOR THE DEPARTMENTS.
>> ALL RIGHT THEN WE WILL GO TO THE PROJECTS SPONSOR FOR UP TO
TEN MINUTES AND I THINK THAT'S LAUREN CHANG AND GINA DACUS.
THAT'S JUST. >> GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT
MANDOLIN AND SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS GINA DACUS AND I AM
THE CEO OF BERNAL HEIGHTS NEIGHBORHOOD CENTER IN BERNAL
HEIGHTS HOUSING CORP. >> WE ARE ALSO A NONPROFIT
SERVICE PROVIDER AND COMMUNITY BASED HOUSING DEVELOPER THAT
HAS SERVED THE BERNAL HEIGHTS COMMUNITY FOR CLOSE TO 50
YEARS. THIS APPEAL IS BEING HELD AS A
RESULT OF NEIGHBORS CONCERNS ABOUT OUR PROPOSAL FOR
COLERIDGE NEIGHBORHOOD PARK. IT'S A PRIVATELY OPERATED PARK
THAT HAS BEEN CLOSED SINCE 2020 AND REQUIRES SIGNIFICANT
REPAIRS. IT IS OUR INTENTION TO REOPEN
THE PARK FOR THE ENJOYMENT OF THE PUBLIC WITH THE REDUCED
SQUARE FOOTAGE TO ALLOW FOR 70 NEW UNITS AT 100% AFFORDABLE
SENIOR HOUSING AS WELL AS A NEW 1000 SQUARE FOOT COMMUNITY ROOM
SPACE THAT ALLOWS SENIOR RESIDENTS AND NEIGHBORS ALIKE
THAT THEY WILL ALL BE ABLE TO USE.
I AM DISAPPOINTED THAT DESPITE OUR MANY INTENTIONS TO REOPEN
THE PARK AS SOON AS PHYSICALLY POSSIBLE AS WELL AS THE
EXTENSIVE COMMUNITY OUTREACH AND CONCESSION TO MAKE 3333 A
MORE WELCOME ADDITION TO THE NEIGHBORHOOD INCLUDING
INCLUDING LOWERING THE INITIAL UNIT COUNT.
AS HAS BEEN SHARED FROM 108 UNITS TO 70 UNITS AND IN
ADJUSTING THE DESIGN AT A SIGNIFICANT EXPENSE TO THE
OWNERSHIP TO REDUCE IMPACT ON NEIGHBORS BACKYARDS, WE STILL
FIND OURSELVES HERE TODAY. THIS PROJECT HAS ALREADY
RECEIVED MINISTERIAL APPROVAL TWICE AND YET WE HAVE BEEN
ASKED TO WASTE PRECIOUS TIME, MONEY AND RESOURCES PREPARING
FOR THIS APPEAL WHICH HAS NO BEARING ON THE PARK DESIGN
BECAUSE NEIGHBORS ARE UPSET ABOUT WHAT IS LOSING WHAT IS
CURRENTLY UNUSABLE CONCRETE AND BUSHES.
IN FACT THIS APPEAL ONLY SERVES TO DELAY THE ENTIRE PROCESS
AND PROLONG BOTH THE PARK CLOSURE AND THE TIMELINE FOR
DELIVERY DELIVERING AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
>> OVER THE PAST TWO YEARS WE HAVE WORKED CLOSELY WITH THE 33
THREE MISSION NEIGHBORS THAT EXTEND BEYOND THE APPELLANTS
REPRESENTED IN THIS ROOM INCLUDING THEM TO HEAR THEIR
CONCERNS AND SHARE TIMELY INFORMATION REGARDING THE
PROJECT. >> THIS INCLUDED TWO COMMUNITY
OPEN HOUSES, SMALL GROUP MEETINGS IN PERSON AND ON ZOOM
AND ONE ON ONE MEETINGS WITH THE NEIGHBORS AT THEIR HOMES TO
SEE EXACTLY HOW THE DEVELOPMENT MIGHT IMPACT THEM.
OUR COMMUNITY ORGANIZER EVEN WENT TO INDIVIDUAL HOMES
IN THEIR BACKYARDS INCLUDING THE APPELLANTS AND WE HAVE MADE
OUR ENTIRE DEVELOPMENT TEAM INCLUDING THE ARCHITECTS
AND THE LATE LANDSCAPE ARCHITECTS AVAILABLE TO ANSWER
QUESTIONS AT ALL OF THESE MEETINGS.
IN ADDITION, WE DID A SURVEY AND SENT IT OUT TO OVER 2000
BERNAL HEIGHTS NEIGHBORS TO DETERMINE WHAT ELEMENTS THE
COMMUNITY WOULD LIKE TO SEE INCLUDED IN THE NEW DESIGN.
AND NONE OF THIS REQUIRED S.B. 35.
WE VOLUNTARILY INITIATED A PROACTIVE COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT
EFFORT WITH A DEDICATED EMAIL TO RECEIVE NEIGHBORS INQUIRIES
AND ON PROJECT WEBSITE. >> DESPITE THESE EFFORTS
AND OUR CONTINUED REASSURANCE THAT WE WOULD SHARE RELEVANT
INFORMATION WITH THE COMMUNITY WHEN WE WERE ABLE TO DO SO,
NEIGHBORS CONTINUE TO ALLEGE THAT WE WERE NOT DOING ENOUGH
AND THAT WE WERE INTENTIONALLY KEEPING THE PARK CLOSED.
>> COACH NEIGHBORHOOD PARK DID CLOSE IN 2020 DUE TO COVID 19
MANDATES AND REMAINS CLOSED NOW BECAUSE OF THE SIGNIFICANT
MAINTENANCE AND SAFETY CONCERNS, SAFETY CONCERNS SUCH
AS THE TREE ROOTS THAT THE CITY OWNS GROWING INTO OUR PARK.
LIFTING OF STIGMA THAT HAVE NOT BEEN ADDRESSED.
AND BY UTILIZING THIS FINDING TIED TO THIS PROJECT WE HAVE
PROPOSED A MORE OFFICIALLY DESIGNED PARK THAT REMOVES THE
2000 OR SO EIGHT. >> LET ME BE SPECIFIC TO TWO
THOUSAND 835FT2 OF CONCRETE AND BUSHES.
AND IT MAINTAINS 3885FT2 OF PARK SPACE WHICH WILL INCLUDE
GRASS AND A PLACE STRUCTURE AREA.
AND WE'RE ALSO ADDING AGAIN THE 1000 SQUARE FOOT COMMUNITY ROOM
INTENDED FOR MULTI-GENERATIONAL USE.
AND THIS SOLUTION OFFERS BENEFITS FOR THE ENTIRE
COMMUNITY, NOT JUST ONE GROUP OF NEIGHBORS ALLOWING US TO
REOPEN THE PARK WHILE CREATING MORE AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
AND THE APPELLANTS INSISTING THAT WE MAINTAIN THE ENTIRETY
OF THE PARK SPACE ALTHOUGH HAS ALREADY BEEN APPROVED
IN DESPITE OUR EXPLANATIONS. THAT MEANS THAT WE WOULD BE
REMOVING 36 UNITS OF AFFORDABLE SENIOR HOUSING NO SPACE FOR
PRIVATE OFFICE SPACE IN AND FOR SERVICES AND PROPERTY
MANAGEMENT AND THE DESIGNATED LOBBY AREA.
AND WHILE WE HOPE THAT THIS PROJECT WILL BRING BENEFITS FOR
ALL, WE CANNOT IN GOOD CONSCIENCE REDUCE THE UNIT
COUNT IN ORDER TO SAVE A SMALL AMOUNT OF CONCRETE AND DIRT.
AND IN RECENT DISCUSSION EVEN WITH THE APPELLANTS REPRESENTED
WHEN I ASKED WHAT THEIR PLANS WERE THEY HAD NO PLANS.
>> THEY DIDN'T EVEN CONSIDER VISIONING AND IN DREAMING WITH
THE REST OF THE NEIGHBORS OF HOW WE CAN TAKE A 35 YEAR OLD
PARK AND BRING IT TO TODAY'S STANDARDS IN TERMS OF PARK
AND PROGRAMING. AND FURTHERMORE, THEY HAVE
AGAIN NOT DELIVERED A PLAN TO RETAINING THE PARK SPACE.
AND OUR PROPOSAL CREATES AN OPPORTUNITY TO REDESIGN THE
PARK THAT IS COMMUNITY BASED, A COMMUNITY DRIVEN WITH THE MOST
EFFICIENT USE OF THE SPACE ENSURING THAT THERE IS PUBLIC
SPACE FOR COMMUNITY AND CRITICAL NEEDED LOW INCOME
HOUSING THAT IS DEFINITELY NEEDED IN BERNAL HEIGHTS.
WE'RE OUR SENIORS ARE BEING PRICED OUT OF SAN FRANCISCO
AND THIS APPEAL ALSO ALLEGES THAT THERE IS NO OPEN SPACE
IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD. ON THE CONTRARY.
THERE ARE 24 PARKS WITHIN 1.1 MILES OF THE PROJECT SITE.
EIGHT OF THEM ARE A HALF A MILE AWAY WALKING DISTANCE OR LESS
AND PROVIDE SUBSTANTIALLY AND READILY ACCESSIBLE OPEN
SPACE TO OUR RESIDENTS WHILE WE FIGURE THIS OUT.
AND IT IS MY HOPE THAT THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WILL TAKE
INTO CONSIDERATION NOT ONLY THE AGENCY'S DEMONSTRATED
COMMITMENT TO THE COMMUNITY FOR THE PAST 50 YEARS THROUGH OUR
OUTREACH PROCESS FOR NOW BUT ALSO THIS IS A FRIVOLOUS APPEAL
WHICH DOES NOT HAVE THE POWER TO ADVANCE THE APPELLANTS GOAL
OF REOPENING THE PARK AT ITS CURRENT SIZE.
>> AND THANK YOU AGAIN FOR YOUR CONSIDERATION.
GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISOR HOURS TO THE SPEAKER JUST ONE MOMENT.
I'LL JUST REMIND THOSE OF YOU WHO WERE POTENTIALLY NOT HERE
EARLIER NO SUPPORT NOISES. IF YOU DO SUPPORT SOMEONE JUST
SORT OF WAVE YOUR HANDS IN THE AIR AS SUCH.
THANK YOU KINDLY. WELCOME TO OUR SPEAKER.
>> THANK YOU. GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS LAUREN CHANG. >> I'M LAND USE COUNSEL FOR THE
PROJECT SPONSOR. >> THIS APPEAL INVOLVES AN
ALREADY APPROVED 100% AFFORDABLE 70 UNIT SB 35
PROJECT. THE CITY APPROVED THE SB 35
ENTITLEMENTS ON OCTOBER 30TH 2024 AND THEN AGAIN ON APRIL
16TH 2025. THE MATTER BEFORE YOU TODAY IS
ONLY ON THE TENTATIVE MAP APPROVAL WHICH WAS ALSO
PROCESSED UNDER SB 35 AND NOT THE SCOPE AND AND NOT THE SCOPE
OF THE PROJECT OR PROPOSED USES LIKE THE PARK.
THE ENTITLEMENTS ARE FINAL AND CANNOT NOW BE SUBJECT TO AN
APPEAL PROCESS UNDER STATE LAW. >> THE TIMELINE FOR THE CITY TO
DETERMINE WHETHER THE PROJECT IS IN CONFLICT WITH OBJECTIVE
STANDARDS OR MEETS THE ELIGIBILITY CRITERIA UNDER SB
35 HAVE ALSO LONG ELAPSED. >> THE TENTATIVE MAP AT THIS
POINT IS DEEMED APPROVED. AN APPEAL OF THE TENTATIVE MAP
AND ANY OTHER FUTURE PERMITS COVERED UNDER THE PROJECT'S SB
35 APPLICATION IS INCOMPATIBLE WITH THE STREAMLINED
MINISTERIAL APPROVAL PROCESS AND IS UNLAWFUL.
>> ON BEHALF OF THE APPLICANT WE RESPECTFULLY REQUEST THAT
THE BOARD DENY THE APPELLANT'S APPEAL FOR THE FOLLOWING
REASON. NEXT SLIDE PLEASE.
FIRST THIS APPEAL SHOULDN'T BE HEARD AT ALL.
THE STATE IMPOSED STRICT TIMELINES FOR THE CITY TO
REVIEW THE MAP WHICH HAVE ALREADY EXPIRED.
>> THE 90 DAY TIMELINE INCLUDES APPEALS BECAUSE OUR LAWMAKERS
EXPRESSLY STATE THAT PUBLIC OVERSIGHT CANNOT INHIBIT CHILL
OR PRECLUDE THE MINISTERIAL PROCESS.
>> THAT TIME PERIOD EXPIRED ON OCTOBER 12TH, 2025, 114 DAYS
AGO. >> THE APPLICANT SUBMITTED ITS
MAP APPLICATION LAST SUMMER IN JULY 2025.
PUBLIC WORKS APPROVED THE MAP ON NOVEMBER 7TH, 2025 WHICH WAS
ALREADY BEYOND THE 90 DAY REVIEW WINDOW.
TODAY'S APPEAL IS 204 DAYS AFTER THE APPLICANT SUBMITTED
ITS APPLICATION WHICH IS FAR BEYOND THE 90 DAY PERIOD UNDER
SB 35. >> SECOND, EVEN IF THIS APPEAL
WERE NOT TIME BARRED, THE CITY HAS FAILED TO MAKE ANY FINDINGS
THAT THE MAP IS NOT CONSISTENT WITH OBJECTIVE STANDARDS OR ANY
FINDINGS. FACT UNDER GOVERNMENT CODE
SECTION 66474 THAT WOULD MANDATE DENIAL OF THE MAP.
>> THIRD, AS YOU HEARD FROM FROM GINA THE APPLICANT WHILE
NOT REQUIRED BY STATE LAW ALSO COMPLETED EXTENSIVE COMMUNITY
OUTREACH EFFORTS INCLUDING TO THE APPELLANT DIRECTLY.
THE APPLICANT HAS A DEEP DESIRE TO WORK WITH THE COMMUNITY
AND THE CITY TO BRING THIS PROJECT INTO REALITY
AND THEY'VE WORKED INCREDIBLY HARD TO DO SO UP TO THIS POINT.
THE REDESIGN THAT RESULTED IN THE APRIL 2025 APPROVAL WAS
DUE TO INCORPORATING FEEDBACK FROM THE COMMUNITY AND IT'S
IMPORTANT TO HIGHLIGHT THAT COLERIDGE PARK IS PRIVATELY
OWNED AND I HIGHLIGHT THAT BECAUSE AS YOU'VE HEARD THE THE
MAIN ISSUE OF THE APPEAL IS THE PARK.
>> HOWEVER, THE APPLICANT IS COMMITTED TO REDESIGN THE PARK
IN A MORE EFFICIENT, SAFE AND IN BEING MORE ENGAGING FOR
THE COMMUNITY. THE REDUCTION IN THE OVERALL
PARK SIZE WAS NECESSARY TO ACCOMMODATE ADDITIONAL
AFFORDABLE HOUSING UNITS AND MAKE THE PARK MORE USABLE.
>> RETAINING THE PARK SITE IS DIRECTLY AFFECTS THE NUMBER OF
AFFORDABLE UNITS AND THIS PROJECT IS EXACTLY THE TYPE OF
PROJECT THAT WE NEED TO SEE MORE OF IN THE STATE.
IT'S 100% AFFORDABLE. IT PROVIDES HOUSING FOR SENIORS
. IT USED STREAMLINING TOOLS
CREATED BY OUR LAWMAKERS THAT EXEMPTS IT FROM SECURE
AND REQUIRES SHORTENED REVIEW TIME.
>> IT'S NEAR TRANSIT AND IT ALSO ALLOWS IT IT'S TAKING
ADVANTAGE OF THE DENSITY AND HEIGHT INCENTIVES TO
INCREASE THE NUMBER OF AFFORDABLE UNITS.
AND THE DEVELOPMENT TEAM IS MADE UP OF MEMBERS OF THE
COMMUNITY WHO CARE DEEPLY ABOUT THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
>> SO I IMPLORE YOU TO UPHOLD STATE LAW AND DENY THE APPEAL.
THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK
YOU, PRESIDENT BERMAN. >> I HAVE JUST A COUPLE OF
QUESTIONS FOR THE PROJECT SPONSOR.
I CAN I CAN ATTEST THAT THERE WERE COMMUNITY WORKSHOPS THAT
WERE WIDELY PUBLICIZED AND MY LEGISLATIVE TEAM WENT OUT THERE
AS WELL. I'M JUST WONDERING WAS THE
DECISION AROUND PARKSIDE AND AFFORDABLE UNITS AND THAT
TRADEOFF COMMUNICATED IN THE IN THE WORKSHOPS?
>> AND I WANT TO REITERATE THAT THIS IS NOT A REQUIREMENT UNDER
SB 35 AND SO THIS IS GOING BEYOND THE REQUIREMENT OF THE
LAW. >> ABSOLUTELY.
SO WE COMMIT THROUGHOUT SEVERAL MEETINGS WE COMMUNICATED
AND ACTUALLY I THINK BELIEVED THE JULY MEETING WHEN WE AGREED
BASED ON THE APPELLANT'S FEEDBACK ON THE VIRGINIA
NEIGHBORS TO GIVE THEM ABOUT 10,000FT2 OF A SETBACK ON THE
PROPERTY LINE SO THAT THE SITE DIDN'T IMPOSE ON THEIR
BACKYARDS. >> WE COMMUNICATED WHAT ALL THE
CHANGES MEANT INCLUDING THE PARK SIZE.
>> WE WERE ALSO TOLD WHEN WE GAVE ALL THE CONCESSIONS THAT
IT REALLY DIDN'T EVEN MATTER BECAUSE THEY DIDN'T WANT IT
THERE. AND THEY SUGGESTED WE SHOULD
JUST LOOK DOWNTOWN. >> SO THAT'S HOW THAT
DISCUSSION ENDED. AND THERE WASN'T ANY OTHER TIME
TO WE COULD MOVE ON FROM THAT. >> AND YOU TOUCHED ON IT
IN YOUR PRESENTATION BUT I WANTED TO HAVE IT CLARIFIED.
ANY FURTHER DESIGN CHANGES WOULD REQUIRE YOU TO RESUBMIT
AND BASICALLY GO THROUGH A LOT OF MORE PROCESS.
AND ALSO WHAT IS THE RELATIONSHIP TO THE FUNDING FOR
THIS PROJECT? >> OKAY.
SO WHEN WE WHEN WE INITIALLY LOOKED WELL SO LET ME JUST
EXPLAIN TO YOU THE PARK IS A PODIUM PARK.
IT'S NOT A REGULAR PARK. AND I'VE NOW KNOWN PODIUM PARKS
HAVE PROBABLY SHOULD BE BANNED FROM SAN FRANCISCO BASED ON
THIS EXPERIENCE BUT IN EITHER CASE IT'S A PODIUM PARK.
SO IT'S CONNECTED TO ALL THE PROPERTIES.
AND SO IN ORDER FOR US TO ADDRESS THE PARK AND THE PODIUM
AND THE DEVELOPMENT WE WERE COMBINING IT TO CREATE TO
ADDRESS THE FUNDING THAT WOULD COME WITH IT.
AND SO BECAUSE THE PODIUM WOULD HAVE TO BE REPLACED WE COULD
REPLACE THE PARK AT THE SAME TIME AS WE BUILT THE HOUSING.
SO THAT'S HOW THAT CAME INTO PLAY.
THE OTHER PIECE IS IS THAT WHEN THE ARCHITECT SAID THAT THEY
WOULD NEED A PORTION OF THE PARK THEY ORIGINALLY HAD IT
EXTENDED EVEN SMALLER. >> AND I CHALLENGED THEM TO
MOVE IT BACK AND IF THE PARK AND THE UNITS WERE CLOSE TO THE
PARK WE WOULD EXPLAIN THAT THOSE UNITS PEOPLE THAT MOVED
TO THOSE UNITS WOULD UNDERSTAND THAT THEY LIVE BY A PARK.
SO WE ONLY TOOK WHAT WE ABSOLUTELY NEED IT.
SO ANY CHANGES THAT ARE STARTING TO MAKE THAT WE START
TO MAKE TO ADJUST THIS VERY COMPLICATED SPACE THAT SHAPED
LIKE AN L WOULD CAUSE A LOT OF DIFFERENT CHALLENGES AND IT
WOULD IMPACT DOWNSTAIRS AND IT WOULD IMPACT EVERY FLOOR.
AND IT WOULD REMOVE ABOUT 36 UNITS AND IT WOULD NOT ALLOW US
TO HAVE THE COMMUNITY ROOM. AND IT WOULD NOT ALLOW US TO
HAVE THE SPACE THAT IS NOW CALLED THE LOBBY BECAUSE IT WAS
A SHELL. BUT THAT'S ALSO GOING TO
CONSIDER PRIVATE SERVICES OFFICES WHICH WE DON'T HAVE.
THE OTHER SITE AT THE OTHER SITE NEXT DOOR AND OTHER
AMENITIES FOR THE RESIDENTS THAT WILL LIVE HERE.
THESE RESIDENTS AT OUR COVID SITE ARE FROM 70 TO 100 YEARS
OLD. SO THIS ABILITY FOR THINKING IS
CRITICAL FOR SENIOR HOUSING IN SAN FRANCISCO.
BUT WE ALREADY HAVE AN EXAMPLE NEXT DOOR.
SO THE AMENITIES THAT WE DESIGNED IN THIS SPACE ARE TO
BENEFIT THE PEOPLE THAT LIVE THERE.
>> AND IS THERE MORE OPPORTUNITY IN THE NEAR FUTURE
FOR NEIGHBORS TO CONTRIBUTE TO THE EXISTING DESIGN
AND PRESERVATION AND JUST GENERAL ONGOING UPKEEP OF THE
PARK ITSELF? >> ABSOLUTELY.
WE INVITED THE COMMUNITY TO VISION WITH US ABOUT WHAT COULD
BE IN THIS SPACE AND THEN WE BROUGHT OUR LANDSCAPE
ARCHITECTS OUT WITH PICTURES OF WHAT THOSE THINGS WOULD LOOK
LIKE AND PEOPLE WITH DOTS NEXT TO THE THINGS THAT THEY WANTED
TO SEE LIKE MULTIGENERATIONAL INDOOR ACTIVITIES AND EXERCISE
EQUIPMENT FOR THE SENIORS AND SPACE FOR THE TODDLERS.
AND WE TOLD THE COMMUNITY THAT ONCE WE GET THROUGH ALL THE
ENTITLEMENT AND WE START MOVING DOWN THE FUNDING PATH LINE
AND WHEN IT'S TIME FOR THE REQUIREMENTS OTHER DESIGN FOR
THE PARK WE WOULD INVITE THE COMMUNITY BACK IN.
WE DON'T HAVE A VESTED INTEREST ON TELLING THE COMMUNITY WHAT
THIS PARK SHOULD LOOK LIKE. >> IT'S BEEN SAID THAT WE'RE
VACANCY BUT WE ARE BERNAL. >> WE'VE BEEN HERE FOR 49
YEARS. OUR BOARD MEMBERS ARE RESIDENTS
OF THIS COMMUNITY. SO WE ARE PART OF THE PROCESS
WITH COMMUNITY. >> AND THEN JUST LASTLY, THE
PARK WAS CLOSED DURING COVID AND HAS NOT BEEN REOPENED
SINCE. DUE TO SAFETY CONCERNS IS THAT
BECAUSE IT IS A PLATFORM PARK THAT'S BECAUSE THE TREES HAVE
ALSO GROWN INTO THE PLATFORM PARK AND HAVE LIFTED UP THE
CEMENT. I INVITED PARK AND REC OUT TO
THE SITE. I HAD A DREAM THAT THEY WOULD
TAKE THIS PARK FROM ME AND HELP SOLVE THIS PROBLEM.
BUT AS WE KNOW PARK AND REC IN THE CITY DOES NOT HAVE ANY
MONEY FOR PARKS BUT THEY WERE GOOD BECAUSE THEY BROUGHT THE
ENTIRE TEAM OUT AND POINTED THINGS THAT I NEEDED TO
CONSIDER AROUND SAFETY OF OUR OWN WHEN WE TOUCHED ONE ITEM
HOW WE WOULD TRIGGER ADA AND ALL THE OTHER ITEMS AND SO
THAT'S WHEN THIS PARK DISCUSSION AND THE DOLLARS
ASSOCIATED IT STARTED MOVING INTO THE MILLIONS.
BUT WE ARE INVITING THE COMMUNITY TO COME BACK COME OUT
WITH US. WE'VE ASKED PARK AND REC COULD
THEY COME INSTEAD OF THE TABLE JUST TO GIVE US INPUT
AND ADVICE AND THEY HAVEN'T COMMITTED TO IT BUT THEY SAID
THEY WOULD THINK ABOUT IT BUT WE ARE A LITTLE WAYS AWAY FROM
THAT. WE STARTED THIS DISCUSSION A
MONTH AFTER WE CLOSED ON THE PROPERTY THAT IS SO EARLY TO
PLAN ALL THESE VERY DETAILS OUT AND WE TRIED TO BE AS
TRANSPARENT AS WE COULD BASED ON WHERE WE ARE IN THE PROCESS.
BUT YES, THE COMMUNITY IS INVITED BACK TO THE TABLE
AND WE WANT TO DESIGN IN ANOTHER AMAZING PARK
IN BERNAL HEIGHTS. >> AND JUST LASTLY, I WOULD SAY
THE SIZE OF THE PARK IS ABOUT HALF THE SIZE OF THIS ROOM
AND IT WOULD IT WOULD TAKE MILLIONS TO TO GET IT TO WHERE
WHERE FOLKS WANT IT. >> IF WE'RE IF WE ARE JUST
CONSIDERING THE PARK BY ITSELF THIS MEANS THAT WE WOULD BE
REPLACING THE PODIUM. THAT IS WHERE THE EXPENSE IS
NOT THE EXPENSE OF REPLACING THE PLAY EQUIPMENT THAT STILL
STARTS ABOUT 100 K RIGHT? >> IT'S THE ACTUAL PODIUM
ITSELF AND EVERYTHING THAT CAME WITH THAT WHICH IS WHY THE
CONVERSATION BECAME COMPLICATED AND THIS IS SOMETHING THAT WE
HAVE SHARED REPEATEDLY. >> THANK YOU.
THOSE ARE MY QUESTIONS. THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT. SEEING NO ONE ELSE ON THE
ROSTER, WE WILL OPEN UP PUBLIC COMMENT IN OPPOSITION TO THE
APPEAL AND IN SUPPORT OF THE PROJECTS.
AND SO IF FOLKS WOULD SAY SO MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE
WELCOME PEOPLE? >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU.
YOU'RE ALREADY LINING UP ON THE RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER.
THANK YOU, BILL BARNES FOR GUIDING PEOPLE IN THAT
DIRECTION. >> IF YOU'LL USE THE TALLER
PODIUM IT DOES HAVE A CLOCK ON IT WHICH WILL TELL YOU WHERE
YOU ARE AT IN YOUR TWO MINUTE PRESENTATION.
AT FIRST YOU'LL HEAR A SOFT BELL THAT LETS YOU KNOW YOU'VE
GOT ABOUT 29 SECONDS LEFT TO FINISH.
WE ALWAYS HATE INTERRUPTING PEOPLE.
>> SO WELCOME. THANK YOU.
>> MY NAME IS EMILY HAGAN. I LIVE IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD
ABOUT A TWO MINUTE WALK AWAY FROM THE SITE ON WINFIELD
STREET. AND I AM AGAINST THIS APPEAL.
>> I HAVE TWO KIDS WHO ARE NINE AND SIX.
>> SO WHEN MY OLDEST WAS THREE I THINK ONE WAS WAS WHEN THIS
PARK CLOSED WE NEVER GOT TO TRY IT OUT.
>> BUT WE'RE REALLY EXCITED TO SEE THE PARK RENOVATED TO SEE
THE WHOLE SENIOR HOUSING BUILT AND I DON'T SEE ANY REASON TO
DELAY THIS FURTHER. >> I WANT IT TO GET DONE SO
THAT WE CAN ENJOY IT AND I THINK THE 3000 SQUARE FOOT
PUBLIC SPACE AMENITY SPACE IS ALSO GOING TO BE A GREAT
FEATURE THAT WE'RE EXCITED TO USE.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU.
WELCOME. THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HI EVERYONE. MY NAME'S MELANIA GREEN.
I HAVE BEEN LIVING IN BRNO FOR TEN YEARS.
MY HUSBAND AND I OWN A HOME AND ARE RAISING OUR TODDLER
IN BRNO. I LIVE JUST OFF OF COLERIDGE
STREET AND I AM HERE TO STRONGLY SUPPORT THIS PROJECT
AND URGE YOU TO REJECT THE APPEAL.
>> MY FAMILY IS DEEPLY COMMITTED TO THIS NEIGHBORHOOD.
WE'RE MOVING IN MY 78 YEAR OLD MOTHER TO LIVE IN A
MULTIGENERATIONAL HOME AND THAT'S WHY I FEEL SO
STRONGLY ABOUT THIS PROJECT. MOST FAMILIES DON'T HAVE THE
SPACE OR THE RESOURCES TO DO SOMETHING LIKE THIS AND THAT'S
WHY THIS MATTERS SO MUCH TO ME. >> THIS PROJECT IS 100%
AFFORDABLE SENIOR HOUSING FOR VULNERABLE SENIORS.
THESE ARE SENIORS WHO HELP BUILD THIS NEIGHBORHOOD, HELP
BUILD THIS CITY AND ARE NOW BEING PRICED OUT OF IT.
MANY CAN'T AFFORD TO LIVE WITH THEIR ADULT CHILDREN AND COULD
BE FORCED OUT OF OUR COMMUNITY. THIS APPEAL BEFORE YOU CLAIMS
TO RAISE CONCERNS BUT IN REALITY IT BLOCKS A FULLY
APPROVED AND THOUGHTFULLY REDESIGNED PROJECT.
>> THE BUILDING HEIGHT WAS ALREADY LOWERED, UNITS WERE
REDUCED AND EXTENSIVE COMMUNITY OUTREACH WAS DONE.
THIS APPEAL ISN'T ABOUT IMPROVING THE PROJECT IT'S
ABOUT BLOCKING IT. >> MY SON AND HIS FRIENDS NEED
PLAYGROUNDS. THERE'S NO ARGUING ABOUT THAT.
BY BLOCKING THIS PROJECT DOESN'T PROTECT THE PARK.
THE ONLY MECHANISM TO RESTORE AND REOPEN THE PARK IS TIED TO
THIS PROJECT. BERNAL'S BUILT VERY LITTLE BY
LITTLE AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN RECENT DECADES AND THE
CONSEQUENCES ARE CLEAR BLOCKING HOUSING FOR SENIORS IS NOT
PROGRESSIVE AND OUR SENIORS ARE WORTH MORE THAN PROPERTY VALUES
AND PARKING SPOTS AND VIEWS AND DENYING HOUSING LEAVES
VULNERABLE SENIORS WITHOUT SECURE HOUSING AND PUTS THEM AT
RISK OF HOMELESSNESS. AS A HOMEOWNER, A PARENT AND A
NEIGHBOR, I URGE YOU TO REJECT THIS APPEAL.
THIS IS THE RIGHT DECISION FOR BERNAL IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME. THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HI, GOOD AFTERNOON. MY NAME IS OSCAR BENITEZ ABOUT
FOUR BLOCKS AWAY FROM THE PARK. MY DAY TO DAY WORK I'M AN
ADVISOR TO STATE AND COUNTY GOVERNMENTS ON HOUSING
AND HOMELESSNESS. IT'S SUFFICE TO SAY THAT THE
EXAMPLE THAT B AND C IS SETTING SHOULD BE HELD AS A STANDARD.
NOT ONLY HAS THIS PROJECT LATE AND THE PARK SHOULD BE OPENED
BUT THEY ALSO PROVIDED THE CONCESSIONS ON TAKING AWAY
HOUSING THAT SHOULD BE AVAILABLE FOR SENIOR CITIZENS
THAT REQUIRE IT. NUMBER TWO, YOU KNOW THERE'S
BEEN A LOT SAID ABOUT OUTREACH AND COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT JUST
BECAUSE FOLKS DON'T AGREE WITH THE RESULTS OF COMMUNITY
ENGAGEMENT DOES NOT MEAN THAT COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT DID NOT
OCCUR. I THINK IT'S AN IMPORTANT FACT
THAT JUST CONTINUES TO BE RESTATED OVER AND OVER AGAIN.
NUMBER TWO, THERE ARE A NUMBER OF PARKS IN FACT THERE'S A PARK
THAT'S ABOUT HALF A BLOCK AWAY. MY THREE YEAR OLD AND HIS
GRANDMOTHER WALK UP THERE CURRENTLY USE IT
IN ANTICIPATION FOR THIS PARK TO OPEN.
>> I WANT TO END MAYBE WITH JUST ONE OTHER POINT WHICH IS I
SPENT ABOUT ALMOST 15 YEARS AS A BROADCASTER FOR THE NFL.
THIS IS WHAT A HAIL MARY LOOKS LIKE.
THIS DECISION HAS ALREADY BEEN APPROVED.
WE ARE SPENDING A LOT OF TIME, EFFORT AND RESOURCES TO
LITIGATE SOMETHING THAT ISN'T REQUIRED.
SO PLEASE WE ARE LOOKING FORWARD FOR B AND C TO CONTINUE
TO SET A STANDARD FOR OTHER NONPROFIT AFFORDABLE DEVELOPERS
AND WE ENCOURAGE YOU ALL TO ENSURE THAT LOOPHOLES THAT
COULD BE APPROVED LIKE THIS ONE DOES NOT CONTINUE WITH THE TYPE
OF LEGISLATION THAT WAS INTRODUCED AT THE STATE.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR SUPPORT. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME. NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS SAM MOSS ON THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF MISSION
HOUSING DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION.
WE'RE A 55 YEAR OLD NONPROFIT AFFORDABLE HOUSING DEVELOPER
AND A LONG TIME ALLY AND SUPPORTER OF BERNAL HEIGHTS
NEIGHBORHOOD CENTER. I CANNOT STRESS HOW AWESOME
THEY ARE WHAT THEY DO. I'M HERE TO SPEAK IN AS MUCH
OPPOSITION AS HUMANLY POSSIBLE TO THIS APPEAL AND AS MUCH
SUPPORT AS HUMANLY POSSIBLE FOR LOW INCOME SENIOR HOUSING.
>> I HAVE THIS WHOLE SPEECH AND I JUST I CAN'T.
>> HOW ARE WE NOT MORE OUTRAGED THAT WE LOST 38 UNITS FOR
SENIORS? YOU KNOW BERNAL'S ALREADY MADE
CONCESSIONS AND HERE WE ARE AGAIN THE SECOND TIME IN SIX
MONTHS THAT 100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING BUILDINGS MAP ISSUANCE
IS BEING APPEALED NOT THE BUILDING, NOT THE DESIGN, THE
ISSUANCE OF A NEW MAP. >> YOU HAVE THE POWER OF THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. YOU HAVE THE POWER TO PLUG THIS
LOOPHOLE. YOU CAN DO IT.
YOU ARE DULY ELECTED. YOU CAN DO IT AND ANY TIME YOU
WANT TO. >> THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING
COMMUNITY IS HERE TO WORK WITH YOU AND I JUST HOPE THAT YOU
REJECT THIS APPEAL BECAUSE HAVING IT IN THE FIRST PLACE
SENDS A MESSAGE THAT WHEN 100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS APPROVED
IT'S STILL NOT REALLY APPROVED AND THAT'S NOT GOOD FOR ANYONE
ESPECIALLY THE SENIORS WHO MAY NOT HAVE A HOME NOW BECAUSE OF
IT. >> AND I JUST AGAIN I WANT TO
APPLAUD BERNAL HEIGHTS NEIGHBORHOOD CENTER AND THANK
THEM FOR THEIR PATIENCE AND THEIR PERSEVERANCE AND TO
EVERYONE WHO SUPPORTS THEM BECAUSE HOUSING IS ACTUALLY A
HUMAN RIGHT. >> SO THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO YOUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HI, MY NAME IS BRIAN BRUNSWICK.
I AM A MEMBER OF DISTRICT NINE NEIGHBORS FOR HOUSING AND I'M
SPEAKING TODAY AND I LIVE IN BERNAL HEIGHTS.
I'M SPEAKING TODAY BOTH IN SUPPORT OF 3333 MISSION
AND VEHEMENTLY AGAINST THIS APPEAL.
>> WELL, HOUSING IN THE CITY DOES DRAW STRONG REACTIONS WITH
MANY PERSPECTIVES A DESIRE TO BUILD MORE SUBSIDIZED
AFFORDABLE HOUSING HAS IN MY EXPERIENCE UNITED VIRTUALLY ALL
SAN FRANCISCANS. AS YOU'VE HEARD TODAY.
BUT MANY WHO CLAIM TO SUPPORT AFFORDABLE HOUSING SEEM ONLY TO
OFFER SURFACE LEVEL THEORETICAL SUPPORT AND THEY DON'T
ACKNOWLEDGE OR CONSIDER THE WAY THAT BOTTLENECKS LIKE THESE
PREVENT THAT HOUSING CONSTRUCTION.
APPEALS LIKE THIS ONE ARE ONE OF THE MOST SUBSTANTIAL
BOTTLENECKS PREVENTING AFFORDABLE HOUSING
CONSTRUCTION. THIS APPEAL OF COURSE IS
DELAYED 3333 MISSIONS CONSTRUCTION BUT IT IS ALSO
DRIVEN UP THE COST OF EACH NEW HOME.
THEY'RE FUNNELING MONEY TOWARD SUBSIDIZING LAWYERS IS FIGHTING
APPEALS RATHER THAN CONSTRUCTION WORKERS BUILDING
SUBSIDIZED HOMES. IT'S NO WONDER IT TAKES TWO
YEARS LONGER AND COSTS MORE THAN TWICE AS MUCH TO PER
SQUARE FOOT TO BUILD AFFORDABLE HOUSING HERE COMPARED TO STATES
LIKE COLORADO. APPEALS LIKE THIS ALSO HAVE A
CHILLING EFFECT ON FUTURE AFFORDABLE HOUSING THROUGHOUT
THE CITY, HIGHLIGHTING YET ANOTHER LOOPHOLE A NEW OBSTACLE
AFFORDABLE HOUSING DEVELOPERS MUST CONSIDER A PLAN IN BUDGET
FOUR WHEN DECIDING WHETHER TO MOVE FORWARD WITH THE PROJECT.
IT DOES NOT JUST MAKE IT HARDER TO BUILD AFFORDABLE HOUSING
IN BERNAL HEIGHTS. IT PROVIDES A ROADMAP FOR
DRIVING UP COSTS AND PREVENTING AFFORDABLE HOUSING ACROSS THE
CITY. IN THE MEANTIME, IT'S CAUSED
NEARLY FOUR MONTHS OF DELAYS TO THIS PROJECT THAT'S FOUR MONTHS
WITH 70 FEWER HOMES FOR LOW INCOME SENIORS IN MY
NEIGHBORHOOD. IT'S ALSO A FOUR MONTH DELAY TO
OUR NEIGHBORS GETTING THEIR PARK BACK ON COLERIDGE.
TOO OFTEN IN THE CITY WE LET PERFECT BE THE ENEMY OF GOOD
AND WE END UP WITH SOMETHING BAD.
THIS APPEAL IS BAD AND I IMPLORE THE BOARD TO REJECT IT
. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME.
THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON BILL BARNES
ON BEHALF OF THE NONPROFIT HOUSING ASSOCIATION OF NORTHERN
CALIFORNIA. SINCE 1979 WE'VE BEEN THE PROUD
VOICE OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN THE BAY AREA.
>> THIS APPEAL IS SUCH A VERY DANGEROUS PRECEDENT.
PUBLIC WORKS TOOK MORE THAN 90 DAYS TO EVEN APPROVE THE MAPS
SUBMITTED BY THE APPLICANT. AFTER THAT IT WAS APPEALED.
NOW IT'S BEEN HERE AT THE BOARD CONTINUED AND BEING HEARD THERE
ARE FUNDING ROUNDS IN THE STATE THAT GROUPS LIKE BERNAL HEIGHTS
NEIGHBORHOOD CENTER ARE NOT AS COMPETITIVE FOR BECAUSE THERE
ARE SMALL NONPROFIT ORGANIZATION HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. THEY'RE MISSING THOSE FUNDING
ROUNDS AS THESE DELAYS CONTINUE AND PEOPLE SAY THEY'RE FOR
AFFORDABLE HOUSING, IT REALLY DISADVANTAGES BUILDING THE
PROJECT, GETTING THE FUNDING BECAUSE WE'RE NOT ACTUALLY
WORKING ON THE SPIRIT OF SB 35 WHICH IS LET'S MAKE SURE 100%
AFFORDABLE GETS APPROVED AT THIS TIME.
SO THERE ARE LOTS OF ISSUES THAT WERE RAISED BUT I DID WANT
TO ASSOCIATE WITH THE PROJECT SPONSOR IN TERMS OF THE
QUESTION OF WHETHER THE MATTER SHOULD EVEN BE BEFORE THE BOARD
OR WHETHER IT'S TIME BARRED. I THINK THAT'S AN IMPORTANT
PRECEDENT. I WOULD NOTE THAT BERNAL
HEIGHTS DOES A REALLY GOOD JOB OF COMMUNITY OUTREACH.
NOT EVERY DEVELOPER WHO'S A MEMBER OF OURS HAS COMMUNITY
MEETINGS THAT EVERY MEMBER AGREES TO CONCESSIONS
AND THEY'RE NOT REQUIRED TO. >> BUT IN THIS INSTANCE THEY
DID AND WE'RE STILL CONTINUING TO BE HERE FOR IT.
>> APPEAL. LAST THING I WOULD NOTE IS THE
RENO GOALS ARE REAL. WE NEED TO BUILD 100%
AFFORDABLE VERY LOW LOW INCOME HOUSING IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> WE'RE NOT MEETING THOSE GOALS.
WE CERTAINLY DON'T MEET THEM WHEN WE HAVE A PROJECT STARTED
AT 108 UNITS THAT THEN ARRIVES AT 70 UNITS AND AS WE TRY TO
MEET OUR READING GOALS ACROSS ALL OF THE INCOME LEVELS IT
BECOMES CRUCIAL THAT WE APPROVE PROJECTS LIKE THIS THAT ARE SO
NEEDED AS EVERETT DISCUSSED. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
. >> HELLO, MY NAME IS MIKE.
I LIVE IN BERNAL HEIGHTS. DOWN THE STREET FROM THIS
PROJECT AND I SPEAK ONLY FOR MYSELF WHEN I SAY HOW SHAMEFUL
IT IS TO HAVE AN APPEAL AND TO TREAT US ALL LIKE WE'RE STUPID.
LIKE WE CAN'T SEE WHAT'S HAPPENING HERE.
WHEN THE APPEAL HAS ALREADY TAKEN AWAY 38 UNITS FROM THE
PROJECT IN A NEIGHBORHOOD THAT HAS BUILT SEVEN UNITS OF
AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN THE LAST 20 YEARS, IT'S UNBELIEVABLE.
AND FURTHERMORE, HOW SELFISH IT IS TO COME UP HERE IN FRONT OF
ALL OF US AND SAY THAT THE PEOPLE WHO ARE MOST AFFECTED BY
THIS HOUSING PROJECT ARE THE HOMEOWNERS THAT LIVE NEARBY
AND NOT THE PEOPLE THAT INTEND TO MOVE INTO THE PROJECT.
>> THAT'S ALL I HAVE TO SAY. YOU SHOULD BE ASHAMED OF
YOURSELF. >> PLEASE REJECT THIS APPEAL.
OKAY. SO LET'S HAVE OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> WELCOME. >> HELLO.
MY NAME IS RUTH FERGUSON. I'M A TRUSTEE FOR THE CITY
COLLEGE OF SAN FRANCISCO. >> TODAY I'M HERE SPEAKING IN A
PERSONAL CAPACITY. >> EVERY DAY I TAKE THE BUS OR
HIT UP MY FAVORITE RESTAURANTS ON MISSION STREET.
I PASS BY THIS VACANT LOT. IT IS JUST A FEW BLOCKS AWAY
FROM MY HOUSE. RIGHT NOW WE HAVE AN
OPPORTUNITY TO FILL IT WITH 100% AFFORDABLE LOW INCOME
SENIOR HOUSING. MY HEART SWELLS EVERY TIME I
SEE IT FOR WHAT IT CAN BECOME AND IT REPRESENTS FOR OUR
COMMUNITY. >> RIGHT NEXT DOOR TO THIS
VACANT SITE, 56 LOW INCOME SENIORS CURRENTLY CALL OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD HOME IN A BUILDING OPERATED BY THE BERNAL HEIGHTS
NEIGHBORHOOD CENTER. >> THE SAME NONPROFIT DEVELOPER
WHO'S READY TO BUILD THIS PROJECT.
56 SENIORS WHO HAVE CONTRIBUTED TO THE FABRIC OF OUR CITY, OUR
COMMUNITY, THE PEOPLE WHO LIVE HERE ARE MY NEIGHBORS, SOME OF
WHOM ARE LIVING AT THE POVERTY LINE.
THIS HOUSING GIVES THEM THE OPPORTUNITY TO BUILD A STABLE
FUTURE. >> WE SHOULD BE CELEBRATING
THIS SPECIAL OPPORTUNITY TO WELCOME 80 MORE LOW INCOME
SENIORS TO OUR COMMUNITY IN BERNAL HEIGHTS
IN NEIGHBORHOODS LIKE OURS. >> NEWCOMERS AND YOUNG FAMILIES
WHO WANT TO PURCHASE A HOME ARE REQUIRED TO SPEND AN AVERAGE OF
1.7 MILLION DOLLARS. THIS IS BECAUSE OF SCARCITY OF
RESOURCES. BECAUSE BERNAL HEIGHTS
CONSISTENTLY RANKS DEAD LAST ACROSS THE ENTIRE CITY FOR NEW
HOUSING BUILT BERNAL HEIGHTS ALSO RANKS DEAD LAST
IN AFFORDABLE HOUSING CONSTRUCTION.
>> THIS ISN'T A COINCIDENCE. IT'S A POLICY CHOICE.
>> BUILDING AFFORDABLE HOUSING CHANGES PEOPLE'S LIVES.
THE ABILITY TO AGE IN PLACE CHANGES PEOPLE'S LIVES.
IT IS NOT SOMETHING WE SHOULD TAKE FOR GRANTED.
>> THIS IS OUR COMMUNITY AND THESE ARE OUR PEOPLE.
LET'S SHOW UP FOR EACH OTHER ESPECIALLY RIGHT NOW WHEN THE
WORLD IS SO DARK. LET'S COME TOGETHER AND BUILD A
BETTER WORLD IN THIS VACANT LOT IN BERNAL HEIGHTS.
>> LET'S BUILD A BETTER FUTURE FOR OUR ELDERS AND A COMMUNITY
THAT STANDS UP FOR EACH OTHER WHEN WE NEED IT MOST.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. GOOD AFTERNOON BOARD.
MY NAME IS HONEST CHARLIE BODKIN AND I'M ON THE
LEADERSHIP OF THE DISTRICT FIVE DEMOCRATIC CLUB.
MARCEAU, THE CO-FOUNDER OF SAN FRANCISCANS FOR SOCIAL HOUSING
. >> EXCUSE ME.
SENIORS MAKE UP A DISPROPORTIONATE SHARE OF
HOMELESSNESS IN SAN FRANCISCO AND ACROSS OUR STATE.
THAT'S WHY PROJECTS LIKE 3333 MISSION AND THE WORK OF THE
AGENCY ARE CRITICAL. >> ABOUT A THOUSAND SAN
FRANCISCANS FOR SOCIAL HOUSING HAVE RECENTLY SIGNED A PETITION
CALLING ON THIS BOARD TO FUND SOCIAL HOUSING INCLUDING
HOUSING BUILT AND MAINTAINED BY NONPROFITS.
IT'S REASONABLE TO SAY THAT THESE SAN FRANCISCANS STAND
IN SOLIDARITY WITH AFFORDABLE HOUSING DEVELOPMENTS LIKE 33
MISSION PARTICULARLY FOR SENIORS IN MY NEIGHBORHOOD
HAIGHT ASHBURY WE ADDED A 100% AFFORDABLE HOUSING DEVELOPMENT
AT 730 STANTON AND IT'S ENHANCED MY NEIGHBORHOOD
IN BOTH MEASURABLE AND IMMEASURABLE WAYS.
AND I KNOW THAT WHEN THIS PROJECT IS BROUGHT TO
COMPLETION AND NEIGHBORS MEET THEIR NEW NEIGHBORS, THERE WILL
BE SMILES, JOY AND A SENSE OF A STRONGER, MORE UNITED SENSE OF
COMMUNITY JUST AS WE ABOUT IN THE HEAT.
WHEN I SPOKE TO THIS BOARD DURING THE UP ZONING HEARINGS
IN THE FALL, SUPERVISOR MELGAR REMINDED US THAT THE CITY LACKS
A DEDICATED FUND FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
THIS IS WHY WE NEED THIS PROJECT.
I'M URGING YOU TO REJECT THE APPEAL AND SUPPORT THIS
PROJECT. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
. >> GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS.
WORKED WITH MISSION HOUSING DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION URGING
YOU TO DENY THE APPEAL AND SUPPORT THE AFFORDABLE
HOUSING AT 3333 MISSION STREET. >> YOU KNOW, WE REALLY HAVE TO
STOP CALLING INTO QUESTION THE ISSUE AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
ALONG WITH SAM WHO WAS UP HERE EARLIER AND A FEW OTHER FOLKS
WE WERE HERE JUST SIX MONTHS AGO DEFENDING AFFORDABLE
HOUSING AND WE'RE BACK IN THE SAME DISTRICT ON MISSION STREET
ABOUT 20 BLOCKS UP. SAN FRANCISCO NEEDS THOUSANDS
OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING UNITS. NOT HUNDREDS BUT THOUSANDS.
NOT JUST TO MEET OUR GOALS BUT MOST IMPORTANTLY TO MEET THE
NEEDS OF THE PEOPLE WHO ARE DESPERATELY SEEKING HOUSING
SOLUTIONS IN THIS CITY STRUGGLING FAMILIES, SENIORS,
PEOPLE ON THE STREET, THOSE LIVING IN SORROWS, FAMILIES
IN OVERCROWDED CONDITIONS ALL NEED THOUSANDS OF UNITS OF
AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> WE ALREADY UNDERSTAND THE BENEFITS OF SUPPORTING PROJECTS
LIKE 3333 MISSION AND WE ALSO UNDERSTAND THE CONSEQUENCES
WHEN WE DON'T SUPPORT THESE PROJECTS AND WHEN WE DON'T HAVE
STRONG CITY POLICY THAT DOESN'T ALLOW FOR DELAYS LIKE THIS TO
OCCUR OVER AND OVER AGAIN. >> SO JUST PLEASE DENY THIS
APPEAL AND SUPPORT THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER .
>> HELLO SUPERVISORS PETER STEVENS.
BUILD AFFORDABLE FASTER CALIFORNIA JUST TO HEAR HERE TO
SAY PLEASE REJECT THE APPEAL AND SUPPORT THE HOUSING.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME. HELLO SUPERVISORS.
I'M SARA ROGERS WITH DISTRICT NINE NEIGHBORS FOR HOUSING.
WE URGE YOU TO REJECT THIS APPEAL.
THE SUBDIVISION APPEAL IS NOT ISN'T A VALID MECHANISM TO
REHASH ARGUMENTS AGAINST THE PROJECT.
BERNAL HEIGHTS HAS A LONG PROGRESSIVE HISTORY AND A
WELL-DESERVED REPUTATION FOR NEIGHBORLINESS.
BUT OVER THE PAST 20 YEARS, ACCORDING TO THE CITY'S HOUSING
INVENTORY DATA, IT HAS BUILT JUST 230 UNITS OF HOUSING TOTAL
AND ONLY SEVEN UNITS OF AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
>> DURING THAT TIME IT HAS MOVED FROM MAJORITY RENTER TO
MAJORITY HOMEOWNER. WE NOW REGULARLY SEE HOMES SELL
FOR 3 TO 4 MILLION AND EVEN QUAINT LITTLE BERNAL COTTAGES
ARE THE OBJECT OF BIDDING WARS AND GO FOR EYE POPPING PRICES.
>> PEOPLE WHO BOUGHT THEIR HOMES DECADES AGO AND HAVE SEEN
THE VALUES MULTIPLY MANY TIMES OVER MAY NOT FULLY APPRECIATE
HOW HARD IT IS TO AFFORD TO LIVE HERE.
>> OVER MY 18 YEARS IN BERNAL I'VE HEARD MY OTHERWISE REALLY
AMAZING AND WONDERFUL NEIGHBORS OBJECT TO HOUSING OVER AND OVER
BECAUSE OF TRAFFIC, PARKING SHADOWS, THE HILLS BEING TOO
STEEP, THE SIDEWALKS TOO NARROW .
PERHAPS MOST MEMORABLY I HEARD THAT BUILDING TWO NEW HOMES
WOULD CAUSE A PGE AND A PIPELINE TO EXPLODE
AND INCINERATE THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
>> IT WAS APPROPRIATE FOR STATE LAW TO INTERVENE AND STREAMLINE
APPROVALS FOR A PART FOR DEVELOPMENTS LIKE THIS WHEN WE
GET SO FOCUSED ON WHAT WE THINK WE WILL LOSE IN TERMS OF USER
PARKING WE FAIL TO SEE ALL THAT WE WILL GAIN BY HAVING NEW
NEIGHBORS AND BY WELCOMING OUR ELDERS FROM PRESERVING THE
REMAINING DIVERSITY OF OUR COMMUNITY AND BOLSTERING ITS
VIBRANCY. >> THIS PARTICULAR DEVELOPMENT
IS IN A GREAT LOCATION ON ONE OF THE ONE OF THE BEST TRANSIT
CORRIDORS IN THE CITY. HOUSING LIKE THIS IS LONG
OVERDUE AND SHOULD REALLY MAXIMIZE THE NUMBER OF
NEIGHBORS WHO CAN LIVE IN THE COMMUNITY.
THERE SHOULD BE NO FURTHER DELAYS.
WE URGE THE BOARD TO REJECT THIS APPEAL AND THE PROJECT
SPONSOR IN THE FUTURE TO MAXIMIZE THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING
ALLOWED UNDER STATE LAW ON SIMILAR SITES.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME AND CONSIDERATION.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT
MANDOLIN AND BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS LAUREL MUNIZ AND I MOVED INTO BERNAL HEIGHTS
IN 1975. >> BEFORE THAT I LEARNED TO
BOWL ON THAT VERY PROPERTY THAT WE'RE DISCUSSING TONIGHT.
SO I GO WAY BACK. >> RAISED TWO SONS IN BERNAL
HEIGHTS AND WATCHED ONE NIGHT BEING BUILT.
I WANT TO ENCOURAGE YOU TO VOTE AGAINST THIS APPEAL.
WE NEED THIS AFFORDABLE HOUSING .
>> UNFORTUNATELY IT'S ALREADY BEEN REDUCED TO 70 UNITS WHEN
WE COULD HAVE BUILT WHEN THEY COULD HAVE BUILT 108 UNITS ON
THE PROPERTY. AND THE WAY IT GOT REDUCED WAS
LISTENING TO THE COMMUNITY, LISTENING TO THE APPELLANT WHO
DIDN'T WANT A CERTAIN HEIGHT OF A WALL BUILT NEAR HIS HOME.
WE LOST THE PROJECT LOST 10,000 SQUARE FEET BY PULLING BACK THE
PROPERTY LINE. >> I ALSO WANT TO SPEAK TO THE
PEOPLE THAT WERE TALKING ABOUT THE PARK.
>> I WANT TO ENCOURAGE THEM TO COME TO THE NICE MEETINGS THAT
BERNAL HEIGHTS NEIGHBORHOOD CENTER HAS AND GIVE THEIR
INPUT. >> WE CAN MAKE THIS A TOP NOTCH
PARK FOR OUR COMMUNITY. >> WITH YOUR INPUT WHAT'S
HAPPENING IS WE'RE GOING TO THE PROJECT WON'T HAVE THE BROKEN
UP CONCRETE OR THE LITTLE POSTAGE STAMP GRASS AREA THAT
NOBODY COULD PLAY SOCCER ON. >> TRUST ME, THERE'S ALSO GOING
TO BE A COMMUNITY SPACE, AN INDOOR COMMUNITY SPACE WHICH
OUR NEIGHBORHOOD REALLY, REALLY NEEDS VERY LITTLE PLACE WHERE
WE CAN COME TOGETHER AND HAVE MEETINGS, HAVE BIRTHDAY
PARTIES, THAT KIND OF THING. >> SO AGAIN, PLEASE DENY THIS
APPEAL. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON, PRESIDENT. GENTLEMEN AND MEMBERS OF THE
BOARD. I HADN'T PLANNED TO BE HERE
TODAY. I WAS AT AN EXECUTIVE BOARD
MEETING OF THE UNITED EDUCATORS OF SAN FRANCISCO, RETIRED
DIVISION AND WHEN BUT I LISTENED TO IT ON THE RADIO SO
I FIGURED I HAVE TO GET UP HERE.
I HAVE TO SOME OF MY FRIENDS AND NEIGHBORS ARE PART OF THE
APPEAL AND I SYMPATHIZE WITH SOME OF THEIR CONCERNS.
BUT I AM ASKING YOU TO REJECT IT.
>> I COULD DO NO OTHER. WHEN I FIRST MOVED INTO THE
MISSION BERNAL AREA IN 1980 THERE WAS A MOVEMENT AGAINST
GENTRIFICATION BECAUSE IN THE MISSION BEFORE BERNAL I THINK
THERE WAS A STEEP RISE IN THE COST OF HOUSING AND MANY PEOPLE
WERE BEING DRIVEN OUT OF THE CITY BECAUSE OF THAT ROUND OF
GENTRIFICATION. >> I SAID I JUST LEFT THE US
AFTER RETIRED DIVISION ME EXECUTIVE BOARD MEETING.
>> WELL YOU KNOW WHAT? >> IT'S DARN HARD FOR TEACHERS
IN THE CLASSROOM NOW TO AFFORD TO LIVE IN SAN FRANCISCO EVEN
ON THEIR SALARIES. AND MAYBE THAT'S ONE OF THE
REASONS WE HAVE A LITTLE CRISIS IN THE CITY.
BUT NUMBER TWO, CONSIDER A TEACHER OR PARA EDUCATOR TRYING
TO STAY IN SAN FRANCISCO ON THEIR RETIREMENT.
NOT GOING TO HAPPEN. IT IS NOT GOING TO HAPPEN.
SO I JUST THINK ON THE MORAL WAY YOU HAVE TO PUSH THE
PROJECT FORWARD. >> AND I THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
GOOD AFTERNOON. MY NAME IS VINCENT IS.
I'M A LONG TIME SAN FRANCISCO RESIDENT.
BEEN LIVING HERE FOR 73 YEARS. I'M A NATIVE.
>> AND YEARS AGO ABOUT 12 YEARS AGO MY WIFE WE WERE ALL EVICTED
TO ALWAYS ACT. SO BASICALLY WE HAD NOWHERE TO
LIVE. OVER A YEAR WE STRUGGLE LOOKING
FOR HOUSING. FORTUNATELY WE CAME UPON ONE I
NICOLE RICH WHICH I FELT WAS TRULY BLESSED.
VERY HAPPY THERE. AND I LIKE TO SAVE FOR OTHER
PEOPLE IN MY SAME POSITION TO BE ABLE TO AFFORD AND STAY HERE
IN THE CITY. BECAUSE THIS IS THE CITY WE
LOVE SAN FRANCISCO. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS QUINTIN MACKIE WITH
THE COUNCIL OF COMMUNITY HOUSING ORGANIZATIONS OF WHICH
RENTAL HEIGHTS NEIGHBORHOOD CENTER IS A LONG STANDING
MEMBER. >> WE SHOULD BE REALLY CLEAR
ABOUT THIS. NO PART OF THIS PROCESS SHOULD
MAKE ANY OF US HAPPY. >> OUR MEMBER AGENCIES ARE ON
THE THINNEST OF THREADS RIGHT NOW ECONOMICALLY.
CONSTRUCTION COSTS, LABOR COSTS, LAND ACQUISITIONS TO
EVEN PUT TOGETHER A SUCCESSFUL CAPITAL STACK TO PUT TOGETHER
THIS TYPE OF DEVELOPMENT TAKES TIME, EFFORT AND MONEY.
AND THE CONCESSIONS THAT BERNAL HEIGHTS NEIGHBORHOOD CENTER
MADE IN GOOD FAITH 35% OF THE UNITS THAT WERE ORIGINALLY
PROPOSED AND WHERE DID THEY GET THEM?
>> AN APPEAL THAT SITS BEFORE YOU NOW FOR THE SECOND TIME YOU
ALL SET FOR AN APPEAL OF THE DPW MAP IN THE MISSION?
WE'RE DOING IT AGAIN HERE. THIS NEEDS TO BE THE ABSOLUTE
LAST TYPE OF THIS APPEAL THAT IS ALLOWED IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
THEY FOLLOWED EVERY PART OF THE PROCESS THAT WE HAVE BEEN ASKED
TO FOLLOW. >> THEY WILL DEALT WITH THE
NEIGHBORS. THEY COLLABORATED AND YET STILL
WE'RE HERE TRYING TO SATISFY SOME LAST MINUTE REQUESTS.
AND IT'S COST MONEY. IT'S DELAYED HOUSING AND 38
UNITS ARE NOW NO LONGER GOING TO BE BUILT FOR SENIORS
IN BERNAL HEIGHTS. THEY'RE NOT GOING TO BE MADE UP
SOMEPLACE ELSE. THIS WAS THE OPPORTUNITY TO
HAVE THEM. WE'RE NOT GOING TO HAVE THEM.
BUT MOVING FORWARD IT IS INCUMBENT ON THIS BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS TO CLOSE THIS LOOPHOLE.
THERE SHOULD BE NO MORE DPW YOU MAP APPEALS.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS WITH
TURNER ON BEHALF OF THE HOUSING ACTION COALITION IN STRONG
SUPPORT OF THE PROJECT AND STRONG OPPOSITION TO THIS
APPEAL. THIS IS A CRITICAL MOMENT FOR
D9 TO SUPPORT AFFORDABLE HOUSING FOR OUR SENIORS BEING
LED BY THE GREAT RENTAL HEIGHTS NEIGHBORHOOD CENTER.
THIS HAS BEEN A TRUSTED LOCAL PARTNER FOR ALMOST 50 YEARS.
THE APPEALS BEFORE YOU TODAY IS MERITLESS AND INTENDED ONLY TO
OBSTRUCT. WHILE A SMALL GROUP OF
NEIGHBORS HAVE RAISED CONCERNS ABOUT THE PARK.
THE REALITY IS THAT THIS PROJECT WILL PROVIDE THE
NECESSARY FUNDING TO REDEVELOP AND REOPEN A PARK THAT HAS BEEN
SHUTTERED SINCE 2020. >> IT'S RECEIVED MINISTERIAL
APPROVAL TWICE. THE APPEAL DOES NOT CHALLENGE
THE PROJECT'S ENTITLEMENTS. THIS IS JUST A TACTICAL DELAY
TARGETING A TENTATIVE MAP THAT SIMPLY JUST PARCEL LINES TO
REFLECT CITY OF ABUSES. WHAT ARE WE DOING?
WHY ARE WE NOT SUPPORTING OUR SENIORS?
WE URGE YOU TO OPPOSE THIS APPEAL.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
>> WE'D HAVE TO DO. MY NAME IS NOVIA MARSHALL AND I
WORK WITH BERNAL HEIGHTS NEIGHBORHOOD CENTER FOR 12
YEARS AND THE CEO, MS.. GINA JACOBS HAS SUPER I HEADED
THE BERNARD HEIGHTS NEIGHBORHOOD CENTER FOR 30
YEARS AND SHE'S WORKED HARD TO GET THE ORGANIZATION WHERE IT
IS TODAY AND SHE HAS A GREAT TEAM OF STAFF IN BOARD MEMBERS
WHO SUPPORT HER KEEP TO KEEP THE ORGANIZATION RUNNING
SMOOTHLY AS WE KNOW HARVEST THIS CONTINUES TO BE A BIG
PROBLEM. PEOPLE CONTINUE TO BE PUSHED
OUT OF THE CITY WITH NO SOLUTION.
WELL, BERNAL HEIGHTS NEIGHBORHOOD CENTER COMBATS
THAT PROBLEM HOMELESSNESS WHICH IS TO PROVIDE AFFORDABLE HOW
THE IN SAN FRANCISCO THIS IS 2026 AND TIMES ARE ROUGH FOR
EVERYBODY. >> ANY OF US COULD BE ON THE
OTHER SIDE OF HOMELESSNESS AT ANY TIME.
I'M HONORED TO WORK WITH THE ORGANIZATION WHO ADVOCATES FOR
PEOPLE IN NEED AND KEEP AFFORDABLE HOUSING IN THE
FOREFRONT. >> THIS PROJECT OF 3333 MISSION
BY BERNAL HEIGHTS NEIGHBORHOOD CENTER SHOULD BE A WIN WIN
SITUATION FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND THE COMMUNITY TO
ALL WORK TOGETHER. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER WHAT ARE WHAT ARE
WE DOING HERE TONIGHT WITH AN APPEAL IS LIKE SHOOTING FISH
IN THE DOUGH DOBERMAN GUY MARKET THE GREAT OUR OWN RANDY
SHAW AND HIS BOOK GENERATION PRICED OUT NOTES THAT THE TWO
PRIME REASONS WE DON'T HAVE ENOUGH HOUSING OUR NUMBER ONE
BABY BOOMERS SITTING ON VAST APPRECIATION AND PROFITS.
>> AND NUMBER TWO NEIGHBORHOOD ACTIVISTS.
WHAT DO THE APPELLANTS LOOK LIKE TO YOU?
>> I THINK SOME OF THEM ARE EVEN OLDER THAN BABY BOOMERS.
>> THIS IS 20TH CENTURY THINKING.
I WANT YOU TO THINK ABOUT SOMETHING.
>> SINCE I CAME INTO THE WORLD 14 BILLION PEOPLE HAVE FOLLOWED
ME INCLUDING EVERYONE ON THIS BOARD AND YOU KNOW, PERHAPS THE
PROBLEM IS THAT ONLY SEVEN BILLION HAVE DIED.
>> GOD BLESS THE BILLION WHO HAVE DIED IN CHILDBIRTH OR
CHILDHOOD 2 BILLION THERE WE GOT TO BUILD HOUSING.
>> WE'VE GOT TO BUILD AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
WHY DON'T WE JUST LET OUR SUCCESSORS, THE PEOPLE WHO COME
AFTER US DECIDE WITH WHETHER OR NOT WHAT WE DID WAS UP
AND QAISER, THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> ARE THERE ANY OTHER INDIVIDUALS WHO WOULD LIKE TO
SPEAK IN OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL AND IN SUPPORT OF THE
PROJECT? >> SEE NONE.
MR. PRESIDENT, THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU PUBLIC COMMENT
IN OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL IN SUPPORT OF THE PROJECT IS
NOW CLOSED. >> LASTLY, THE APPELLANT WILL
HAVE UP TO THREE MINUTES TO PRESENT A REBUTTAL ARGUMENTS.
YOU KNOW IT'S IRONIC BECAUSE I BELIEVE IN EVERYTHING YOU GUYS
ARE SAYING EVERYTHING WE DO NEED MORE HOUSING.
WE SHOULDN'T STOP. WE SHOULDN'T GET IN THE WAY OF
MORE AFFORDABLE HOUSING AND WE SHOULDN'T HAVE THINGS LIKE
APPEALS THAT CAN DELAY THAT. I AM NOT LOOKING FORWARD TO THE
I DID NOT LOOK FORWARD TO CROSSING YOUR TIME.
>> IF YOU COULD ADDRESS THE BOARD TO SUPERVISE I KNOW BUT I
KIND OF WANT TO ADDRESS THEM TO DO THAT.
THANK YOU. THIS IS ADDRESSING THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS SO YES I AGREE WITH EVERYTHING YOU'RE SAYING
AND THERE'S A LOT OF SENSE TO WHAT WHAT YOU'RE SAYING.
BUT THESE COMMENTS CAME OUT STATING THAT ALMOST EVERYTHING
THAT WE'RE SUGGESTING IS THAT WE'RE TRYING TO BLOCK
AFFORDABLE SENIOR HOUSING AND THAT WAS NOT THE CASE AND I
MADE A COMMENT IN MY INITIAL STATEMENT SAYING WE DID NOT
WANT TO FILE THIS BECAUSE WE KNEW IT WAS GOING TO DELAY THIS
PROCESS AND WE DON'T WANT TO DELAY THIS PROCESS.
WHAT WE DO WANT WHAT AND WHAT WE DID WANT FOR TWO YEARS WAS
AN OPPORTUNITY TO SPEAK ABOUT A MYRIAD OF THINGS ABOUT THESE
ISSUES THAT WE NEVER GOT A CHANCE TO TALK ABOUT AND MAYBE
THAT'S NOT THE APPEALS PART. >> MAYBE THAT'S SB 35.
BUT THERE IS SOMETHING HERE WHERE I JUST BECAUSE YOU'RE
PRESENTING A CASE FOR AFFORDABLE SENIOR HOUSING WHICH
I THINK IS VERY STRONG I WOULD DO THAT MYSELF.
BUT THEY ARE DOING SOMETHING TO A COMMUNITY.
THEY ARE IMPACTING A COMMUNITY AND THEY CAN IMPACT IT IN A
NEGATIVE WAY. THEY'RE GOING TO DO MUCH BETTER
THINGS FOR THE COMMUNITY BUT THE THINGS THAT THEY DO IMPACT
THE THINGS THAT THAT THAT ONLY WE FEEL NEED TO BE ADDRESSED
SOMEHOW AND WE NEVER EVER GOT THAT OPPORTUNITY WITH THIS PARK
THERE'S THERE'S I'VE HEARD COUNTLESS STORIES FROM FROM OUR
CITY FROM OUR NEIGHBORS THAT SAID HOW MUCH THIS PARK MEANS
TO THEM AND YES YOU ARE GOING TO FIX THE PARK, YOU ARE GOING
TO MAKE IT BETTER AND WE DO BELIEVE THAT AND WE DO I KNOW I
KNOW AND WE DO WANT THAT BUT BUT WE WANTED TO NOT HAVE TO
SACRIFICE SUCH A LARGE PART OF IT.
AND SHE SAYS 36 UNITS WERE GOING TO BE LOST BY THAT
AND THAT'S NOT TRUE IF YOU IF YOU LOOK AT THE ACTUAL PLANS,
IT'S ABOUT THREE UNITS AND THOSE THREE UNITS CAN BE
REINCORPORATED TO THE INTO THE PLAN VERY EASILY BY BY MAKING
SMALL CHANGES TO WHAT THEY HAVE IN THOSE PLANS.
>> SO I DISAGREE WITH 36 UNITS. I ALSO DISAGREE WITH THE FACT
THAT THEY SAID IT WAS 108 UNITS AND THEY GOT IT DOWN TO 70.
THEY NEVER CAME TO US AND SAID IT WAS 138 OR 108 WHATEVER IT
WAS. THAT WAS NEVER WHAT WE HEARD.
WE ONLY HEARD 70 AND WHEN THEY DID BUILD 70 THEY WERE BUILDING
SIX STOREYS JUST TEN FEET AWAY FROM OUR BEDROOMS.
NOW I KNOW THAT SOUNDS LIKE A SELFISH THING.
>> AFFORDABLE HOUSING IS MORE IMPORTANT RIGHT?
>> THIS PUBLIC HEARING HAS BEEN HELD AND YEAR THAT YOU WERE
THAT WAS YOUR THAT WAS THE THREE MINUTES OF REBUTTAL SO
THEY HIT THEY NOTE THE HEARING THIS HEARING HAS UNLESS US SO
THE SUPERVISOR FIELDER IS YOUR COMMENT FOR AFTER THE PUBLIC
HEARING OR YES ALL RIGHT SO THE PUBLIC HEARING HAS BEEN HELD
AND IS NOW FILED AND WE ARE NOW GOING TO CONSIDER WHETHER TO
APPROVE OR CONDITIONALLY DISAPPROVE THE DECISION OF
PUBLIC WORKS AND THE TENTATIVE PARCEL MAP SUPERVISOR FIELDER
THANK YOU, PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN ,COLLEAGUES, I HAVE MET WITH
BOTH THE APPELLANTS AND THE REPRESENTATIVES FROM BERNAL
HEIGHTS NEIGHBORHOOD CENTER OR BEACH AND SEE THE PROJECT
SPONSOR. I'VE MET WITH BOTH PARTIES
SEVERAL TIMES. >> I MET WITH MR. LUCCHESI, THE
LEAD APPELLANT AND SOME OF HIS NEIGHBORS AT THE SITE ITSELF
LAST MONTH WHERE I LISTENED TO THEIR PROPOSED CHANGES TO THE
NEW COLLEGE PARK DESIGN AND THE REMAINING CONCERNS WITH THE
DESIGN OF THIS AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECT SPECIFICALLY
THE SIZE OF THE PARK AS THEY SHARED IN THEIR PRESENTATION
TODAY. >> HOWEVER, TODAY'S APPEAL IS
NOT AND LEGALLY CANNOT BE AN APPEAL OF THE PROJECT'S DESIGN
OR THE PARK'S DESIGN AS WE'VE HEARD FROM THE CITY ATTORNEY
AND OUR CITY DEPARTMENTS INCLUDING THE NUMBER OF UNITS
OR THE SIZE OF THE PLAYGROUND THIS APPEAL AND HEARING ARE NOT
THE PROPER VENUE FOR ANY OF THESE DESIGN CONCERNS.
THOSE CONCERNS SHOULD HAVE BEEN DISCUSSED WITH THE PROJECT
SPONSOR THEMSELVES INCLUDING DURING THE SEVERAL OUTREACH
MEETINGS THAT B AND C ORGANIZED AS THEY SHARED TODAY.
>> THE APPEAL DIRECTLY BEFORE US IS CHALLENGING THE
MINISTERIAL SUBDIVISION OF THE PARCEL MAP A PROCEDURAL STEP
MANAGED BY THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS AND REQUIRED FOR
THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECT TO PROCEED.
>> THE APPELLANT'S CONCERNS WOULD BEST BE HEARD BY OUR
PLANNING DEPARTMENT WHEN REVIEWING THE PROJECT AND AS
PLANNING EXPLAINED THEY MINISTERIAL APPROVE THIS
AFFORDABLE HOUSING APPLICATION UNDER STATE LAW REVIEWING
SOLELY OBJECTIVE CRITERIA THAT THE PROJECT SPONSOR HAS MET.
>> I UNDERSTAND AND I DO HEAR THE APPELLANT'S FRUSTRATION IS
THAT COLLEGE PARK HAS BEEN INACTIVE FOR OVER FIVE YEARS
NOW AND I SHARE THESE CONCERNS AND ECHO THE NEED TO ACTIVATE
AND UTILIZE THE GREEN PUBLIC SPACES IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
THE FACT IS THAT ADVANCING THE AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECT HERE
IS THE MOST VIABLE PATH TO FINALLY REACTIVATING THE PARK
NOT FURTHER STALLING THE PROJECT.
I WON'T REITERATE ALL THE REASONS THAT ARE PARK
DEPARTMENT HAS DECLINED ANY INTEREST IN ACQUIRING THE PARK
BUT SUFFICE IT TO SAY THAT DESPITE MY EFFORTS AND DESPITE
THOSE OF MY PREDECESSORS, THE ONLY REALISTIC PARK OPERATOR
REMAINS B, H AND C WHO HAS FOUND A PATH TO DO SO THROUGH
THIS PROJECT WHICH WILL INCLUDE FINANCING NEEDED FOR THE
NECESSARY FIXES TO MAKE IT SOUND AND SAFE FOR THE
COMMUNITY'S PUBLIC ACCESS. >> ALL OF THAT SAID, I BELIEVE
IN THE IMPORTANCE OF COMMUNITY OUTREACH AND ENGAGEMENT WHEN
UNDERTAKING ANY MAJOR PROJECTS IN OUR COMMUNITIES.
I TOOK THE APPELLANT'S ITS CONCERNS SERIOUSLY AND IN GOOD
FAITH WHEN THEY AFFIRMED THEIR SUPPORT FOR PROVIDING DOZENS OF
AFFORDABLE HOMES TO LOW INCOME SENIORS AT 3333 MISSION
AND SOLELY WANT TO ENSURE ACTIVATION OF COLLEGE PARK AT
ITS CURRENT SIZE SO THAT CAN BE ENJOYED BY THE ENTIRE COMMUNITY
AND THAT IS WHY I MET WITH MR. JESSE AND HIS NEIGHBORS AT
COLLEGE PARK AND WHY I BROUGHT THEM TOGETHER WITH THE PROJECT
SPONSOR IN THE HOPES OF REACHING A RESOLUTION THAT
WOULD NOT NECESSITATE TODAY'S HEARING.
>> I WAS ACTUALLY PLEASED TO SEE FOR MYSELF ACCORDING TO B
AND C DESIGN PLANS AND WE SAW EARLIER IN THEIR PRESENTATION
THAT THE MAJORITY OF THE SQUARE FOOTAGE OF USABLE EXISTING PARK
WOULD BE PRESERVED IN OTHER WORDS THE APPELLANT'S IS
ESTIMATES INCLUDES SQUARE FOOTAGE THAT IS UNUSABLE FOR
EXAMPLE SHRUBS AS WELL BEACH AND C SHARED TODAY THEY HAVE
MADE SEVERAL CONCESSIONS TO SOME OF THE CONCERN NEIGHBORS
INCLUDING THESE 70 UNITS OF PROPOSED AFFORDABLE HOUSING
FROM A MAXIMUM ALLOWANCE OF 108 UNITS BRINGING THE BUILDING
DOWN TO FOUR STORIES FROM SIX STORIES ON MISSION STREET ALONG
WITH OTHER MODIFICATIONS WITH THE PROJECT'S SETBACKS.
>> LASTLY, I DO BELIEVE THAT THE AGENCY MADE GOOD FAITH
EFFORTS TO CONSIDER DESIGN ALTERNATIVES DESPITE HAVING NO
NO LEGAL OBLIGATION TO DO SO. AND THE REALITY IS THAT
AFFORDABLE HOUSING FINANCING IS EXTREMELY CHALLENGING
AND FURTHER DESIGN ALTERATIONS AND APPROVALS MAKE THE PROJECT
DELIVERY HERE LESS AND LESS LIKELY MEANING DELIVERING
AFFORDABLE HOMES TO SENIORS AT RISK OF HOMELESSNESS LESS
AND LESS LIKELY AS WELL AS WE ALL KNOW WE ARE IN AN
AFFORDABLE HOUSING CRISIS WITH HIGH COSTS OF LIVING FOR THOSE
ON FIXED INCOMES, LACK OF A HEALTH CARE ACCESS AND THE
CONTINUING DISMANTLING OF OUR SOCIAL SAFETY NET.
IT'S NO SURPRISE THAT HOMELESSNESS AMONG OLDER ADULTS
IS ON THE RISE TODAY NEARLY HALF OF ALL SINGLE HOMELESS
ADULTS HERE ARE 50 YEARS OR OLDER AND MANY OF THEM ARE
EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS FOR THE FIRST TIME.
I AM PROUD THAT DISTRICT NINE AND SPECIFICALLY BERNAL HEIGHTS
IS WORKING TOWARDS SOLUTIONS FOR ADDRESSING THIS CRISIS
INCLUDING THE SENIOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING PROJECT AT 3333 MISSION
THAT IS AT THE HEART OF THIS APPEAL.
>> I WOULD ALSO LIKE TO NOTE THAT I AM LOOKING INTO WHETHER
THE CITY CAN REFORM THE TYPES OF MAPS THAT CAN BE APPEALED.
FINALLY, I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE LARGE NUMBERS OF BERNAL
NEIGHBORS WHO WROTE AND CAME IN IN SUPPORT OF THIS PROJECT
AND NOTE THAT THE APPELLANTS HAVE ALSO EXPRESSED THEIR
SUPPORT FOR THIS CRITICAL AFFORDABLE HOUSING DEVELOPMENT.
I WANT TO TAKE EVERYONE UP ON THEIR GOOD FAITH.
WE ALL WANT TO PROVIDE AFFORDABLE HOMES FOR OUR
NEIGHBORING SENIORS TO AGE IN PLACE WITH DIGNITY AND I
HOPE THESE SHARED VALUES CONTINUE TO GUIDE PRODUCTIVE
DIALOG AROUND THIS PROJECT. AND WITH THAT COLLEAGUES I'M
MOVING TO APPROVE ITEM 34 AND TABLE ITEMS 35 AND 36.
>> IS THERE A SECOND FROM SUPERVISOR MELGAR AND I DON'T
SEE ANYONE ELSE IN THE QUEUE. I DO WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR
FIELD FOR YOUR EFFORTS TO TRY TO BRING THE PARTIES TO A
RESOLUTION. THAT'S ALWAYS SOMETHING WE HOPE
FOR WHEN THERE ARE APPEALS TO THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
I DON'T FAULT THE APPELLANT'S FOR TAKING ADVANTAGE OF A
PATHWAY THAT IS THERE TO ADDRESS SOMETHING THAT THEY SEE
AS WRONG AND A PROBLEM. IT IS PECULIAR FOR THOUGH THAT
WE HAVE THIS PATHWAY. IT'S KIND OF A PATHWAY TO
NOWHERE AND THIS IS THE SECOND TIME WE'VE SEEN THIS AT THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND THE LEGISLATURE HAS BASICALLY TAKEN
AWAY I THINK THE ABILITY OF THIS BOARD TO DO MUCH
IN SITUATIONS LIKE THIS WHETHER OR NOT WE WOULD WANT TO.
AND SO AND SO I'M ALSO GRATEFUL THAT YOU'RE TAKING A LOOK AT
WHETHER THERE MAY BE SOME WAY OF NOT PROVIDING THIS SORT OF
FALSE HOPE AND OPPORTUNITIES FOR NEIGHBORHOOD CONFLICT WHEN
WHEN AND BY THE TIME IT GETS TO THIS BOARD IT'S PRETTY
IMPOSSIBLE FOR US TO DO ANYTHING OTHER THAN WHAT WE'RE
DOING HERE TODAY. >> SO WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK,
COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MOTION TO APPROVE ITEM
34 AND TABLE ITEMS 35 AND 36 SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES
SUPERVISOR WONG HAI WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI RANDLEMAN EYE SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR EYES SUPERVISOR SADR SADR EYE AND SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL EITHER ARE 11 EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION ITEM 34 IS
APPROVED AND ITEMS 35 AND 36 ARE TABLED.
>> MADAM CLERK THAT CONCLUDES OUR FIRST 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER.
LET'S GO TO OUR NEXT SPECIAL ORDER PLEASE CALL ITEMS 37
THROUGH 40 TOGETHER ITEM 37 THROUGH 40 COMPRISE THE PUBLIC
HEARING OF PERSONS INTERESTED IN THE CERTIFICATION OF A FINAL
ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT FOR THE PROPOSED SFO ARE ADP
RECOMMENDED AIRPORT DEVELOPMENT PLAN ISSUED BY THE PLANNING
COMMISSION AND DATED NOVEMBER 20TH 2025.
THE PROPOSED PROJECT WOULD IMPLEMENT THE ALREADY P WHICH
INVOLVES A LONG RANGE PLAN TO GUIDE THE SAN FRANCISCO
INTERNATIONAL AIRPORTS DEVELOPMENT THE R&D SERVES AS A
FRAMEWORK FOR FUTURE DEVELOPMENT AND IDENTIFIES
VARIOUS PROJECTS. ITEM 38 THIS MOTION AFFIRMS THE
PLANNING COMMISSION CERTIFICATION OF THE FINAL
ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT. ITEM 39 IS THE MOTION TO
CONDITIONALLY REVERSE THE COMMISSION'S FINAL
ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT AND THAT WOULD BE SUBJECT TO
THE ADOPTION OF WRITTEN FINDINGS BY THE BOARD AND ITEM
40 IS THE MOTION TO DIRECT THE PREPARATION OF FINDINGS.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. >> SUPERVISOR CHERYL, YOUR
STAFF IS TRYING TO GET YOU OUT OF HERE TO OTHER OBLIGATIONS SO
I UNDERSTAND THAT. DISTRICT TWO SUPERVISOR CHERYL
IS GOING TO HAVE TO LEAVE US AND I WILL MAKE A MOTION AFTER
YOU GO TO HAVE YOU EXCUSED FROM THE REMAINDER OF THE MEETING.
>> GET OUT OF HERE. CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO EXCUSE
SUPERVISOR CHERYL FROM THE REMAINDER OF THE MEETING MADE
BY SUPERVISOR ADVISOR MAHMOOD SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR CHEN.
I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL IS EXCUSED FOR THE REMAINDER OF THE
MEETING. >> COLLEAGUES, AS THE AS OUR
CLERK INDICATED WE HAVE BEFORE US A HEARING ON THE APPEAL OF A
FINAL AIR CERTIFICATION AND FOR THE SFO RECOMMENDED AIRPORT
DEVELOPMENT PLAN. AFTER OUR HEARING THE BOARD
WILL VOTE ON WHETHER TO AFFIRM OR CONDITIONALLY REVERSE THE
PLANNING COMMISSION'S CERTIFICATION OF THE FINAL
ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT. UNLESS THERE ARE OBJECTIONS WE
WILL PROCEED AS WE HAVE PROCEEDED BEFORE WITH UP TO TEN
MINUTES FOR PRESENTATION BY THE APPELLANTS OR THEIR
REPRESENTATIVE. FOLLOWED BY PUBLIC COMMENT TWO
MINUTES PER SPEAKER IN SUPPORT OF THE APPEAL.
THEN WE'LL GIVE THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT UP TO TEN MINUTES
FOR THE PROJECT SPONSOR. WELL I GUESS PLANNING
DEPARTMENT AND AIRPORT GETS TEN MINUTES AND THEN TWO MINUTES
PER SPEAKER IN OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL.
AND THEN FINALLY WE'LL HAVE REBUTTAL AND FROM THE YOU KNOW
I MISSTATED THAT WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TEN MINUTES FOR A
PRESENTATION FROM THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT.
THEN WE GO TO THE AIRPORT. THE PROJECT SPONSOR FOR AN
ADDITIONAL TEN MINUTES. THEN WE DO PUBLIC COMMENT OF
ABOUT TWO MINUTES PER SPEAKER IN SUPPORT OF IN OPPOSITION TO
THE APPEAL. AND THEN WE GO BACK FOR THREE
MINUTES OF REBUTTAL BY THE APPELLANT OR THEIR
REPRESENTATIVE. ANY OBJECTIONS?
I DON'T SEE OBJECTIONS FROM COLLEAGUES SO SEEING NO
OBJECTIONS. THE PUBLIC HEARING WILL PROCEED
AS INDICATED AND IS NOW OPEN. I WILL INVITE THE APPELLANT TO
COME FORWARD AND PRESENT THEIR CASE.
OH MY GOSH IT'S MY OLD BOSS RICK DAVIS 20 YEARS AGO.
>> GOOD TO SEE YOU. YOU TOO, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> TAKE IT AWAY. OKAY.
SO I'M HERE FOR THE CITY OF PALO ALTO.
>> I'M THEIR SECURE NERD COUNCIL AND I'M HERE TO
CHALLENGE THE ADEQUACY OF THE ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT
THAT THE SAN FRANCISCO STAFF HAS PREPARED TO EVALUATE THE
LONG TERM DEVELOPMENT PLAN FOR SFO THAT PLANS FOR FUTURE
EXPANSION AND IMPROVEMENTS AT THE AIRPORT OVER THE NEXT 20
YEARS TO INCREASE THE CAPACITY WHICH WILL INCLUDE A NEW
TERMINAL WITH I DON'T KNOW HOW MANY PASSENGER GATES I'VE SEEN
NUMBERS BETWEEN EIGHT AND 13. >> PALO ALTO IS PRIMARY CONCERN
IS THAT THE AIR DOES NOT ANALYZE THE IMPACTS TO THE CITY
OF PALO ALTO OF THE INCREASE IN NOISE FROM THE GREATER
NUMBER OF FLIGHTS THAT WILL BE ACCOMMODATED BY THE ADP.
THERE'S ALSO CONCERNS ABOUT NOISE BUT I'M GOING TO FOCUS ON
ABOUT AIR QUALITY BUT I'M GOING TO FOCUS ON NOISE HERE AND I
SAY THAT IT DOESN'T ANALYZE IT AT ALL.
I DIDN'T SAY IT WAS NOT ADEQUATE.
THERE IS NO ANALYSIS OF NOISE IMPACTS ON PALO ALTO OR ANYBODY
IN THE YEAR 2045 AND I'M GOING TO SORT OF DO JUMP CUT TO THE
CHASE HERE AND DO THE SPOILER ALERT.
>> THE THERE'S A FUNDAMENTAL LEGAL FLAW IN THE AIR.
THE AS WE'RE GOING TO TALK ABOUT THE AIR TAKES THE
POSITION THAT IT CAN USE THE YEAR 2045 AS THE BASELINE EVEN
THOUGH NORMALLY YOU'RE SUPPOSED TO USE EXISTING CONDITIONS AS A
BASELINE FOR ITS ENVIRONMENTAL ANALYSIS AND IT DOES THAT FOR
OTHER TYPES OF TRAFFIC AIR QUALITY AND NOISE OR AT LEAST
IT PURPORTS TO DO THAT BECAUSE IF YOU'RE GOING TO DO A 2045
BASELINE ANALYSIS, THE STARTING POINT OF THAT ANALYSIS IS
YOU'RE SUPPOSED TO ACTUALLY DESCRIBE NOISE CONDITIONS
IN THE YEAR 2045 WITHOUT THE PROJECT AND YOU COMPARE THAT TO
THE IMPACTS THAT THE PROJECT WOULD CAUSE.
THAT THRESHOLD PRESENTATION OF BASELINE 2045 NOISE IMPACTS IS
COMPLETELY MISSING FROM THE DOCUMENT.
THE DOCUMENT THE CHAPTER ON NOISE IMPACTS HAS A DISCUSSION
OF SUMMARY OF NOISE CONDITIONS THAT EXISTED IN THE YEAR 2019
THROUGH 2023. >> THERE'S A CHART THAT TALKS
ABOUT DECIBEL LEVELS NOT OVER PALO ALTO BUT IN AREAS IN THE
VICINITY OF THE AIRPORT. BUT THERE IS ZERO DISCUSSION
ANYWHERE OF FUTURE NOISE IMPACTS FROM AIRPORT FLIGHTS
IN 2045. AND IF YOU'RE REALLY GOING TO
DO A BASELINE ANALYSIS OF 2045 CONDITIONS, YOU HAVE TO INCLUDE
START WITH A SUMMARY OF WHAT THOSE ACTUAL IMPACTS ARE
AND THAT'S COMPLETELY MISSING FROM THE DOCUMENT.
>> THAT'S A FUNDAMENTAL FATAL FLAW.
EVEN IF YOU DISAGREE WITH MY OUR OTHER POINTS IT WOULD BE A
VIOLATION OF SECRET TO APPROVE CERTIFICATION OF THAT DOCUMENT
WITHOUT THAT MISSING PIECE. SO I'M GOING TO TALK ABOUT THIS
A LITTLE BIT MORE IN SYSTEM BUT I WANTED TO SORT OF CUT TO THE
CHASE FIRST. NOW AS WE EXPLAINED IN OUR
MATERIALS, THE CITY OF PALO ALTO AS COMPARED TO SURROUNDING
COMMUNITIES IS UNIQUELY IMPACTED BY NOISE FROM FLIGHTS
DUE TO THE CONFLUENCE OF THREE MAJOR ARRIVAL ROUTES THAT
CONVERGE AT A LOW ALTITUDE RIGHT OVER THE CITY OF PALO
ALTO BEFORE VEERING OUT ACROSS THE BAY AND THEN INTO THE
AIRPORT. THAT'S WHY PALO ALTO IS HERE.
BUT REDWOOD CITY OR SAN MATEO OR OTHER CITIES ARE NOT HERE.
THERE'S A UNIQUE IMPACT ON PALO ALTO.
OUR EVIDENCE THAT WE SUBMITTED PICTURES WORTH A THOUSAND
WORDS. YOU CAN LOOK AT THE MAP THAT
WE'VE ATTACHED AND INCLUDE IT IN OUR MATERIALS.
IT SHOWS HOW THESE THESE PALO ALTO IS UNIQUELY IMPACTED
BECAUSE THESE FLIGHTS GO RIGHT OVER THE CITY OF PALO ALTO
AND IMPACT OUR COMMUNITY. >> AND ALL WE'RE ASKING FOR IS
FOR ANALYSIS AND DISCLOSURE OF NOISE IMPACTS INCLUDING THE
NOISE IMPACTS FROM THE FUTURE GROWTH IN FLIGHTS THAT WILL
OCCUR AS ACCOMMODATED BY THE ADP.
>> NOW THE AIR SEEKS TO RATIONALIZE ITS REFUSAL TO
PROVIDE ANY INFORMATION TO THE PUBLIC ON FUTURE NOISE
INCREASES BASED UPON A FICTION. AND IT IS STATING THAT THE ADP
WILL NOT CAUSE THE DEVELOPMENT OF THESE APPROVE OF THESE
FUTURE EXPANSION PROJECTS, WILL NOT CAUSE AN INCREASE
IN FLIGHTS BUT THEY'RE REALLY ONLY GOING TO ACCOMMODATE THE
FLIGHTS WHEN THEY OCCUR AND THAT THESE FLIGHTS WILL
THIS FLIGHT INCREASE WILL HAPPEN REGARDLESS OF WHETHER
THE ADP IS DEVELOPED AND THE APPROACH IT TAKES.
IT LOOKS AT A 2014 ESTIMATE. THE FAA AND SFO PREPARED AS TO
THE MAXIMUM POTENTIAL CAPACITY OF THE AIRPORT AND THEN IT
ASSUMES THAT WELL THAT CAPACITY IS GOING TO BE REACHED
REGARDLESS OF WHETHER THESE PROJECTS ARE APPROVED.
>> AND NOTHING IN THE ADP IS GOING TO EXPEDITE OR CHANGE THE
TIMING OF WHAT'S GOING TO HAPPEN.
REGARDLESS, IT'S A VERY PASSIVE AND REACTIVE POSITION THAT IT'S
TAKING. >> AND THEREFORE IT SEEKS TO
ARGUE THAT IT DOESN'T NEED TO ANALYZE OR DISCLOSE NOISE
IMPACTS FROM FUTURE FLIGHTS BECAUSE THE ADP IS NOT CAUSING
THOSE ALWAYS IMPACTS. THAT'S THE RATIONALE IT USES.
SO THE MAJOR QUESTION FOR THE BOARD IS WHETHER YOU FIND THAT
POSITION TO BE FACTUALLY PERSUASIVE.
>> THE STAFF'S RESPONSE TO WHAT WE'VE SAID FOCUSES ON THE LEGAL
QUESTION OF SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE.
IT ARGUES WELL THERE'S SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE SUPPORTING
THE CONCLUSION AND THEREFORE THE BOARD SHOULD UPHOLD OUR
CONCLUSION. IF WE WERE IN COURT CHALLENGING
THIS THAT WOULD BE THE STANDARD OF REVIEW.
THAT WOULD BE THE QUESTION FOR THE JUDGE.
THE JUDGE WOULD DEFER TO THE BOARD'S FACTUAL DETERMINATION
LOOK WELL, IS THERE ENOUGH EVIDENCE TO SUPPORT IT?
THAT'S NOT THE QUESTION BEFORE YOU.
THE QUESTION BEFORE YOU IS DO YOU ACTUALLY AGREE THAT THESE
IMPROVEMENTS WILL NOT HAVE ANY CONTRIBUTING EFFECT TO FUTURE
NOISE INCREASES? AND I WOULD URGE YOU TO APPLY
LOGIC AND COMMON SENSE AND CONCLUDE THAT NO, DESPITE
THE ATTEMPTED RATIONALE THAT THEY'RE TRYING TO PROVIDE
IN THE AIR THAT THERE WILL NOT BE ANY FUTURE FLIGHTS RESULTING
FROM THE PROJECT. AS A MATTER OF COMMON SENSE
AND LOGIC YOU CAN SEE THAT IT WILL.
>> SO THINK ABOUT THIS. THE PURPOSE OF THE SFO
MANAGEMENT IS TO MAKE THE AIRPORT AS SUCCESSFUL AS
POSSIBLE. OF COURSE THEY'RE DOING
WHATEVER THEY CAN TO INCREASE BUSINESS USE OF THE END
AND PASSENGER USE OF THE AIRPORT.
THEY'RE DOING IT. THAT'S THEIR MISSION.
THAT'S THEIR GOAL. THAT'S WHY THEY'RE SUING THE
PORT OF OAKLAND OVER ITS ATTEMPT TO USE SFO AS ITS NAME
. I MEAN EVERY STEP THAT THEY
TAKE THEIR THEIR THEIR THEIR MISSION IS TO MAKE SURE THAT
THEY ARE DOING WHATEVER THEY CAN TO MAXIMIZE PASSENGER USE
OF THE TERMINAL. AND THE ADP IS A PART OF THAT.
IN FACT IF IF THE SFO MANAGEMENT WAS SERIOUS THAT
THEY WEREN'T TRYING TO DO THAT AND I WERE IN YOUR POSITION,
I'D WANT TO REPLACE THEM WITH SOMEBODY WHO WOULD BE TRYING TO
ACTUALLY MAKE THE AIRPORT AS ECONOMICALLY SUCCESSFUL AS
POSSIBLE. AND THEY ADMITS THAT POINT
IN THE AIR AND THE SECRET FINDINGS ALL THROUGHOUT THEIR
ANALYSIS. >> AND I'M GOING TO QUOTE
SOMETHING HERE THE THE FINDINGS AND THE AIR STATE THAT THE
ADP'S CENTRAL PURPOSE IS QUOTE TO GUIDE THE AIRPORT'S
DEVELOPMENT AS THE PREMIER LONG HAUL AND INTERNATIONAL GATEWAY
OF CHOICE FACILITATING ECONOMIC GROWTH OF THE BAY AREA.
THEY ADMIT IN THE DOCUMENT THAT THE PURPOSE OF THE ADP IS TO
ENCOURAGE PEOPLE TO CHOOSE TO FLY THERE.
THEY'RE THUS ADMITTING THAT THEY'RE TRYING TO INCREASE
FLIGHTS. THAT'S NOT SO SHOULDN'T BE A
SURPRISING OR SHOCKING CONCLUSION BUT BUT THAT'S
RIGHT. THERE THEY HAVE SOME RATIONALE
AND THEIR APPENDIX C I'M RUNNING OUT OF TIME SO I'M NOT
GOING TO GO TOO MUCH INTO IT. BUT THEY CITE FEDERAL CASES
INVOLVING NEPA. THAT'S A WELL IF YOU BUILD IT
IT'S NOT NECESSARILY TRUE. IT WILL YOU KNOW THEY WILL COME
INTO CONTEXT OF AIRLINE AIRPORT FACILITIES.
BUT EVEN THOSE CASES AS I QUOTED IN OUR SUPPLEMENTAL
MATERIALS ACKNOWLEDGE THAT WELL YEAH, THESE IMPROVEMENTS WILL
HAVE SOME TENDENCY TO INCREASE PASSENGER USE OF THE AIRPORT.
AND THEY SORT OF EVEN THAT LANGUAGE REFUTES THE ARGUMENT
BEING MADE IN THE AIR. >> SO UNDER SECURE IT'S NOT
ENOUGH FOR THEM TO LET'S LET'S SAY WE AGREE LET'S SAY YOU
AGREE WITH THEM AND THAT THIS WILL NOT HAVE A TENDENCY TO
INCREASE AIRPORT FLIGHTS. THAT'S NOT ENOUGH TO MEET THE
STANDARD FOR USING 2045 AS THE BASELINE.
SECRET GENERALLY MANDATES THAT ANALYZING A PROJECT'S IMPACTS
THE ANALYSIS MUST START FROM THE EXISTING CONDITIONS EXCEPT
IN VERY RARE CIRCUMSTANCES AND AND THE GUIDELINES SAY THAT
IN ORDER TO JUSTIFY USING A FUTURE BASELINE HERE THEY'RE
TRYING TO JUSTIFY 2045 THEY HAVE TO DEMONSTRATE AND MOSTLY
QUOTING FROM THE GUIDELINES HERE WITH SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE
THAT USE OF EXISTING CONDITIONS WOULD BE EITHER MISLEADING OR
WITHOUT INFORMATIVE VALUE TO DECISION MAKERS AND THE PUBLIC
AND THEY FURTHER STATE THE GUIDELINES TO STATE USE OF
PROTECTED FUTURE CONDITIONS AS THE ONLY BASELINE MUST BE
SUPPORTED BY RELIABLE PROJECTIONS BASED ON
SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE IN THE RECORD.
AND SO THERE IS THE REQUIREMENT RIGHT THERE YOU HAVE TO HAVE
PROJECTIONS AS TO THE FUTURE WHICH ARE COMPLETELY MISSING.
YOU LOOK IN THE AIR THEY'RE NOT THERE AS TO FUTURE NOISE IF YOU
IF YOU COMPARE IT TO THE TRAFFIC CHAPTER, THE TRAFFIC
CHAPTER DOES HAVE A SECTION ON THAT.
BUT THE SEA AIR DOES NOT WE DON'T WANT TO BE HERE.
>> WE WOULD THE CITY OF PALO ALTO WE WOULD HAVE LOVED TO
HAVE A MEETING WITH SFO. WE TRIED TO HAVE THAT MEETING
TO TRY TO RESOLVE OUR CONCERNS WITHOUT HAVING TO HAVE THIS
BOARD TO DECIDE OUR APPEAL. WE'RE CONTINUE TO BE OPEN TO
THAT AND I'M ON. ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU COLLEAGUES. ANY COMMENTS OR QUESTIONS FOR
THE APPELLANTS? I DON'T SEE ANY.
SO THEN WE WILL OPEN UP PUBLIC COMMENT SPECIFICALLY FOR THOSE
WHO WOULD LIKE TO SPEAK IN SUPPORT OF THE APPEAL.
IF THERE'S ANYONE HERE TO SPEAK IN SUPPORT OF THE APPEAL,
PLEASE LINE UP. LOOKS LIKE WE DON'T HAVE ANYONE
SO THEN WE WILL CLOSE WHEN ONE PERSON MR. PRESIDENT?
YEP. >> HI.
MY NAME IS JENNIFER LANDESMAN AND I'M A RESIDENT OF THE CITY
OF PALO ALTO AND I'VE ACCOMPANIED THE SITUATION WITH
THE IMPACTS ON PALO ALTO FROM WHEN SEVERAL CHANGES HAPPENED
IN 2014 STARTING IN 2014 I NOTICED THAT SAN FRANCISCO
PROVIDED A POWERPOINT SAYING LISTING THINGS THAT THEY HAVE
DONE TO ADDRESS NOISE. >> WELL ALL OF THEM ARE
INACCURATE AND AS MISLEADING AS THE CURRENT EIA IS ABOUT
IMPACTS OR WHAT THE AIRPORT IS DOING THEY MENTIONED THAT AS A
ROUNDTABLE PALO ALTO HAS BEEN REJECTED SEVEN TIMES FROM THAT
BODY. >> THEY MENTIONED NOISE
MONITORING. THEY DON'T DO NOISE MONITORING
IN PALO ALTO EXCEPT ON A TEMPORARY BASIS.
SO I'VE BECAUSE ONE OF OUR GRANT I AM PART OF A GRASSROOTS
GROUP I SEE A LOT OF THE PEOPLE THAT ARE IMPACTED ELDERLY YOUTH
,YOUTH AND IT'S PRETTY SERIOUS ESPECIALLY REGARDING NIGHTTIME
. SO THE WORST PART OF THIS IS
THAT THERE IS NO CONVERSATION ABOUT ACTUALLY DOING THAT ARE
THE SOLUTIONS THAT EXIST AND THAT THE FAA HAS EVEN
PROPOSED. >> SO THERE'S NO CONVERSATION.
>> I AM AMONG THE PEOPLE WHO ARE SADDENED THAT SFO
MANAGEMENT DID NOT MEET WITH OUR CITY AND I HOPE YOU WILL
ASK YOUR PLANNING DEPARTMENT TO TAKE A LOOK AT THIS REPORT
AGAIN AND TO DO THE ADEQUATE ANALYSIS PER THE APPEAL.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. DO WE HAVE ANY OTHER SPEAKERS
IN SUPPORT OF THE APPEAL? >> ALL RIGHT.
SEEING NONE PUBLIC COMMENT AND SUPPORTING THE APPEAL IS
NOW CLOSED AND THEN I THINK WE WILL HAVE UP TO TEN MINUTES FOR
REPRESENTATIVES OF THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT.
GOOD AFTERNOON, PRESIDENT. GENTLEMEN, MEMBER OF THE BOARD.
MY NAME IS CASEY. I'M A SENIOR PLANNER WITH THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT JOINING ME TODAY ARE LISA GIBSON,
ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW OFFICER AND TANYA SENIOR PRINCIPAL
PLANNER. ALSO IT WAS THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT. >> THE PROJECT SITE IS THE SAN
FRANCISCO INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT OR SFO LOCATED PRIMARILY
IN UNINCORPORATED SAN MATEO COUNTY.
APPROXIMATELY 30 MILES SOUTH OF DOWNTOWN SAN FRANCISCO SFO, ONE
OF THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO AGENCIES PROPOSES TO
IMPLEMENT THE RECOMMENDED AIRPORT DEVELOPMENT PLAN OR THE
PROJECT. THE PROJECT IS A MAJOR LONG
TERM CAPITAL FACILITIES PLAN WITH AN ANTICIPATED
CONSTRUCTION AND IMPLEMENTATION PERIOD OF 20 YEARS EXTENDING
THROUGH 2045. THE PROJECT INCLUDES THREE MAIN
COMPONENTS. FIRST INCLUDE IMPROVEMENTS
AND DEVELOPMENT OF TERMINAL FACILITIES ALLOWING AS A FULL
TO MODERNIZE AND BETTER SERVE FUTURE PASSENGER NEEDS.
>> SECOND, THE PROJECT INVOLVES MODIFICATIONS TO CERTAIN NON
MOVEMENT AREAS OF THE AIRFIELD. THESE ARE AREAS NOT USED FOR
AIRCRAFT TAKEOFF AND LANDING BUT USED FOR SUPPORTING OVERALL
AIRPORT OPERATIONS. >> FINALLY, THE PROJECT
INCLUDES IMPROVEMENTS TO LANDSIDE FACILITIES SUCH AS
ROADWAYS AND SUPPORT INFRASTRUCTURE TO ACCOMMODATE
LONG TERM AIRCRAFT OPERATIONS AND ANTICIPATED PASSENGER
ACTIVITY LEVELS AT SFO. THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT
PREPARED A PROGRAM ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT OR
AIR ANALYZING ALL COMPONENTS OF THE PROJECT.
THE PLANNING COMMISSION CERTIFIED THE EIA ON NOVEMBER
20TH, 2025. SUBSEQUENTLY THE AIRPORT
COMMISSION APPROVED THE PROJECT ON DECEMBER 16TH, 2025.
>> THE DEPARTMENT'S KEY RESPONSES TO THE APPEAL
SUMMARIZED ON THIS SLIDE AND DISCUSSED IN OUR JANUARY
26TH AND FEBRUARY 2ND APPEAL RESPONSES.
>> FIRST, WHILE THE CITY ACKNOWLEDGES THAT LIVED
EXPERIENCES OF RESIDENTS AFFECTED BY AIRCRAFT ON
COMMUNITIES SUCH AS PALO ALTO, THESE BROADER AIRPORT RELATED
CHALLENGES THAT ARE NOT ATTRIBUTABLE TO THE PROJECT ARE
NOT ISSUES REQUIRED TO BE ADDRESSED IN THE EIA AND THE
SECURE. RESPECTFULLY, THIS SECURE
APPEAL CONSTITUTES AN IMPROPER USE OF SECURE AND CONFLICTS
WITH THE STATE LEGISLATURES EXPLICIT DIRECTIVE PROVIDED
IN SENATE BILL 131 PASSED IN 2015 2025 EXCUSE ME THAT
SEEK WILL NOT BE USED TO GAIN COMPETITIVE EDGE OR DELAY A
PROJECT FOR REASONS UNRELATED TO ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION
HERE AS STATED IN THE APPELLANTS LETTER THE APPELLANT
FILED A SECURE APPEAL TO GAIN LEVERAGE IN THEIR ONGOING
REQUEST TO SFO REGARDING THE FEDERAL AVIATION ADMINISTRATION
ACTIONS KNOWN AS METROPLEX CASE TAKEN IN 2015.
THE MODIFIED CERTAIN FLIGHT PATHS OVER THE CITY OF PALO
ALTO BECAUSE THE PROJECT WOULD NOT RESULT IN ANY CHANGES TO
AIRCRAFT OPERATIONS PATHS OR NOISE OR AIR QUALITY EMISSIONS
. THE APPELLANT'S RELIANCE ON
SECRET TO RAISE CONCERNS REGARDING THE FAA FLIGHT PATH
MODIFICATIONS IN 2015 IS INCONSISTENT WITH THE
LEGISLATURE'S EXPLICIT DIRECTIVE.
THE SEEK WILL NOT BE USED TO DELAY OR CHALLENGE PROJECTS FOR
REASONS UNRELATED TO ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTIONS.
THE APPELLANT DISREGARDS SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE IN THE
RECORD THAT THE PROJECT WOULD NOT INDUCE AIRCRAFT PASSENGER
DEMAND AND OPERATIONS AT SFO AS DISCUSSED THROUGHOUT THE AIR AS
WELL AS THE DEPARTMENT'S JANUARY 26 AND FEBRUARY 2ND
APPEAL RESPONSES IMPLEMENTATION OF THE PROJECT WOULD NOT INDUCE
ADDITIONAL PASSENGER DEMAND OR AIRCRAFT OPERATIONS AT SFO
AIRPORTS ARE UNIQUE TRANSPORTATION FACILITIES WHOSE
OPERATIONS ARE HIGHLY REGULATED BY FEDERAL AGENCIES INCLUDING
THE FAA AS DETAILED IN APPENDIX C TWO DRAFT E AIR WHICH
CONTAINS AN EXPERT TECHNICAL MEMORANDUM PREPARED BY RE
CONDOR, A NATIONALLY RECOGNIZED AIRPORT CONSULTING FIRM.
RUNWAY CAPACITY IS THE PRIMARY FACTOR THAT LIMITS THE NUMBER
OF AIRCRAFT THAT CAN TAKEOFF AND LAND AT SFO BECAUSE THIS
PROJECT WOULD NOT ALTER THE RUNWAY CAPACITY IT WOULD NOT
INDUCE ADDITIONAL PASSENGER DEMAND OR AIRCRAFT OPERATIONS
SFO THE APPELLANT HAS NOT PROVIDED ANY SUBSTANTIAL
EVIDENCE DEMONSTRATING OTHERWISE.
>> RATHER THIS APPEAL REFLECTS A DISAGREEMENT WITH THE
DEPARTMENT'S RESPONSES TO THE APPELLANT'S PREVIOUS COMMENTS
WHICH DOES NOT CONSTITUTE THE BASIS FOR RECIRCULATION UNDER
SECURE EXCUSE ME THE APPELLANT MISSTATES THE LAW REGARDING THE
USE OF FUTURE BASELINES IN ERS SECRET GUIDELINE SECTION 15125
ALLOWS THE AGENCIES TO EVALUATE PROJECT IMPACTS USING BOTH
EXISTING AND FUTURE BASELINES WHEN DOING SO PROVIDES THE MOST
MEANINGFUL FRAMEWORK FOR EVALUATING A PROJECT'S
ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACTS. AS EXPLAINED IN THE DRAFT YEAR
IN THE DEPARTMENT'S FEBRUARY SECOND APPEAL, THIS BARS THE
APPELLANT'S RECOMMENDED APPROACH COMPARING CERTAIN
ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACTS OF THE PROJECT AGAINST EXISTING OR
2019 CONDITIONS WOULD BE MISLEADING TO THE PUBLIC
AND DECISION MAKERS. THE EIA USES APPROPRIATE
BASELINES CONSIDERING THE NATURE AND SCOPE OF THE
PROJECT'S ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACTS AS REQUIRED BY SEQUOIA.
THE ALREADY IS A MAJOR LONG TERM CAPITAL FACILITIES PLAN
WITH AN ANTICIPATED CONSTRUCTION IN THE
IMPLEMENTATION PERIOD OF 20 YEARS EXTENDING THROUGH 2045.
FOR THIS REASON, COMPARING THE ADP'S AIR QUALITY NOISE
AND TRANSPORTATION OPERATIONAL IMPACTS AGAINST A FUTURE 2045
BASELINE PROVIDES A REALISTIC AND INFORMATIVE ASSESSMENT OF
THE PROJECT'S INCREMENTAL EFFECTS.
>> IN SUMMARY, THE EIA FULLY COMPLIES WITH SEQUEL THE
APPELLANT HAS NOT PROVIDED ANY SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE
DEMONSTRATING OTHERWISE. THUS THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT IS
NOT REQUIRED TO RECIRCULATE THE AIR FOR PUBLIC REVIEW.
>> FINALLY THE APPELLANT MISSTATES THE LAW REGARDING
PROCEDURAL REQUIREMENTS APPLICABLE TO THE AIRPORT
COMMISSION'S PROJECT APPROVAL ON DECEMBER 16TH, 2025.
>> CONTRARY TO THE APPELLANT'S ASSERTION, THE AIRPORTS
COMMISSION'S DECEMBER 16TH, 2025 PROJECT APPROVAL COMPLIED
WITH ALL APPLICABLE APPLICABLE REQUIREMENTS UNDER SEQUOIA
GUIDELINES SECTION 15090B THE SECTION DOES NOT LIMIT THE
AUTHORITY TO CERTIFY A FINAL AIR TO A LOCAL AGENCY ELECTED
DECISION MAKING BODY SUCH AS THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
IT ALLOWS THE CITY AGENCY SUCH AS THE PLANNING COMMISSION TO
CERTIFY AT THE AIR. >> IN ADDITION, THE AIRPORTS
COMMISSION'S DECEMBER 16TH, 2025 PROJECT APPROVAL COMPLIED
WITH SAN FRANCISCO ADMINISTRATOR CODE SECTION 31.1
6B3 THE SECTION DOES NOT PROHIBIT A CITY AGENCY SUCH AS
THE AIRPORT COMMISSION FROM APPROVING A PROJECT BEFORE THE
CLERK OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS SCHEDULES AN APPEAL
HEARING RELATED TO THE PROJECT. >> HERE THE AIRPORT COMMISSION
APPROVED THE PROJECT ON DECEMBER 16TH, 2025 BEFORE THE
APPELLANT FILED THIS SEEKING APPEAL ON DECEMBER 19TH, 2025.
>> THUS THE AIRPORTS COMMISSION'S PROJECT APPROVAL
COMPLIED WITH SECTION 31.1 6B3 .
>> THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT THEREFORE RESPECTFULLY
RECOMMENDS THAT THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS APPLY THE PLANNING
COMMISSION'S CERTIFICATION OF THE FINAL EIA AND DENY THE
APPEAL. THANK YOU.
STAFF ARE AVAILABLE HERE TO ANSWER ANY QUESTIONS YOU MAY
HAVE. IN ADDITION WE HAVE A
REPRESENTATIVE HERE FROM RE CONDOR THE CONSULTING FIRM THAT
PREPARED APPENDIX C TO THE DRAFT AIR.
>> THANK YOU. >> COLLEAGUES QUESTIONS I WILL
MAYBE JUST MAKE SURE I UNDERSTAND THE THE ISSUE
AND WHAT I THINK OUR RESPONSES .
SO IT IT SOUNDS LIKE THE ISSUE THAT PALO ALTO IS RAISING IS
THAT THIS PLAN WOULD ALLOW FOR SAN FRANCISCO TO ACCOMMODATE
ADDITIONAL FLIGHTS OVER PALO ALTO AND THAT THAT WOULD
POTENTIALLY CREATE A SIGNIFICANT NOISE IMPACT FOR
PALO ALTO RESIDENTS. AND THE CITY'S RESPONSE TO
AND THAT HAS NOT BEEN ANALYZED IN THE AIR.
AND THE CITY'S RESPONSE TO THAT IS IS WHAT?
>> GOOD AFTERNOON, MR. PRESIDENT.
MY NAME IS STEVE CULBERTSON AND WITH OUR CONTENT ASSOCIATES
WE ARE AN AVIATION PLANNING FIRM.
WORK AT U.S. AIRPORTS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY.
SO WE SO THAT IS CORRECT. SO THE THE PROJECT ITSELF
BECAUSE IT'S NOT CHANGING THE RUNWAY CAPACITY, IT'S NOT
CHANGING THE CONFIGURATION. IT'S NOT ALLOWING MORE AIRCRAFT
TO LAND AT SFO. IT IS NOT GOING TO INDUCE ANY
ADDITIONAL FLIGHTS. SAN FRANCISCO ALREADY OPERATES
IT HAS HISTORICALLY OPERATED ABOUT 470,000 ANNUAL
OPERATIONS. >> THE AP DID A VERY EXTENSIVE
MODELING ANALYSIS OF THE RUNWAY SYSTEM AND DETERMINED THAT ITS
CAPACITY IS ABOUT 505,000 ANNUAL OPERATIONS.
SO THEY'VE ALREADY HISTORICALLY OPERATED AT ABOUT 93% OF WHAT
THE RUNWAY SYSTEM CAN SUSTAINABLY ACCOMMODATE ON AN
ANNUAL BASIS. SO THE DELTA WE'RE TALKING
ABOUT IS IS PRETTY SMALL AND THE DEMAND FOR AIR FLIGHTS
FOR PASSENGERS OR FOR AIR SERVICE HERE IS BASED ON
DEMOGRAPHIC FACTORS. IT'S NOT BASED ON IF YOU BUILD
A TERMINAL MORE PEOPLE ARE GOING TO COME TO YOUR AIRPORT.
IT'S BASED ON THE ECONOMIC FACTORS THAT'S GOING TO OCCUR
WHETHER YOU IMPLEMENT THIS PROJECT OR NOT.
IF YOU DON'T IMPLEMENT THE PROJECT WHAT WILL HAPPEN IS
YOU'LL HAVE MORE CONGESTED CONDITIONS AT THE AIRPORT.
SO TODAY DURING PEAK PERIODS YOU HAVE CONGESTED CONDITIONS.
IF YOU DON'T BUILD ADDITIONAL GATES OR OR TERMINAL FACILITIES
YOU'LL SEE THOSE CONDITIONS ON A MUCH MORE REGULAR BASIS.
AND SO THE PLAN YOU'RE SAYING THE PLAN TO ADDRESS THAT
POTENTIAL CONGESTION OF OPERATING ESSENTIALLY WHERE WE
ARE OR ADDING A LITTLE BIT TO IT WITHIN WHAT'S CURRENTLY
ALLOWED IS NOT GOING TO RESULTS IN ANY KIND OF INTENSIFICATION
OF FLIGHTS OVER PALO ALTO. THAT MIGHT CREATE NOISE.
SO THE FLIGHTS ARE GOING TO HAPPEN REGARDLESS.
SO THOSE FLIGHTS ARE GOING TO COME WHETHER THIS PROJECT IS
IMPLEMENTED OR NOT THAT THAT IS THE AND THIS PROJECT DOES NOT
ALLOW FOR IS NOT A PIECE OF ALLOWING FOR MORE FLIGHTS.
CORRECT? RIGHT.
I DON'T SEE ANY OTHER COMMENTS OR QUESTIONS.
SO WE WILL GO TO THE PROJECT SPONSOR THE AIRPORT FOR UP TO
TEN MINUTES. >> ALL RIGHT.
GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT MANDOLIN AND MEMBERS OF THE
BOARD. MY NAME IS AUDREY PARK SFO
ENVIRONMENTAL OF MZ PARK. >> CAN YOU SPEAK DIRECTLY AS
MUCH AS YOU CAN INTO THE MIC? ABOUT ENVIRONMENTAL AFFAIRS
MANAGER I'M JOINED TODAY WITH STEVE CULBERTSON SENIOR VICE
PRESIDENT OF RICARDO WHO PREPARED THE TECHNICAL MEMO
TITLED AIRPORT FACILITIES TO ACCOMMODATE AVIATION DEMAND.
THIS MEMO IS CONTAINED IN APPENDIX C OF THE AIR SFO IS
LOCATED AT SFO IS LOCATED ABOUT 13 MILES SOUTH OF CITY HALL
AND CONTAINED ENTIRELY ON LAND OWNED BY THE CITY AND COUNTY OF
SAN FRANCISCO AND UNINCORPORATED SAN MATEO
COUNTY. I SUPPOSE THE 13TH BUSIEST
AIRPORT IN THE U.S. SERVING OVER 50 MILLION PASSENGERS.
THIS IS REFLECTIVE OF A STRONG RETURN OF DEMAND FOR AIR TRAVEL
BY PEOPLE TO AND FROM THE BAY AREA AFTER THE COVID 19
PANDEMIC. THE AIRPORT IS A MAJOR EMPLOYER
AND CONTRIBUTES BILLIONS TO THE REGION AND DIRECT BUSINESS
REVENUE. AS A SELF FUNDED ENTERPRISE
DEPARTMENT OF THE CITY AND COUNTY THE AIRPORT
CONTRIBUTED 58 MILLION TO IN FISCAL YEAR 25 TO THE CITY'S
GENERAL FUND. TODAY OVER THE AIRPORT'S LONG
RANGE PLAN CALLED THE RECOMMENDED AIRPORT DEVELOPMENT
PLAN. >> SO WHAT IS THE RTP OR ADP?
CONTAINS THE VISION FOR HOW THE AIRPORT WOULD PROVIDE ORDERLY
DEVELOPMENT OF FACILITIES SIZE TO ACCOMMODATE 71 MILLION
PASSENGERS AT AN ELEVATED GUEST EXPERIENCE.
THE ODP IS A COMPREHENSIVE UPDATE TO THE 1989 MASTER PLAN
THAT PROVIDED FOR FACILITY SIZE TO ACCOMMODATE 51 MILLION
ANNUAL PASSENGERS. THE MASTER PLAN IS SUNSETTING
WITH IMPLEMENTATION OF LONG CONTEMPLATED PROJECT SUCH AS
THE AIRPORT HOTEL OPENED IN 2018 AND THE HARVEY MILK
TERMINAL ONE OPENED FULLY IN 2024.
>> SO WHAT'S IN THE RTP? AS KEY MENTIONED, IT'S
PRIMARILY LANDSIDE FACILITIES INCLUDING TERMINAL AND BOARDING
AREAS AND AN AIRPORT WORLD WE CALL EVERYTHING OUTSIDE OF THE
AIRFIELD LANDSIDE. DIFFERENT FROM AN URBAN CONTEXT
PARKING GARAGES AND OTHER LANDSIDE FACILITIES COLORED
AND TEAL. AS PASSENGER DEMAND FOR AIR
TRAVEL GROWS OVER DECADES, IT WOULD TRIGGER CERTAIN RTP
PROJECTS FOR DEVELOPMENT OVER THOSE DECADES.
THE RTP IS ABOUT AS THIS GROWTH IN PASSENGER DEMAND GROWS.
HOW CAN THE AIRPORT ACCOMMODATE BACK DEMAND IN A WAY THAT
ELEVATES PASSENGER AMENITIES AND SERVICES THAT IS REFLECTIVE
OF SAN FRANCISCO? UNDER THE RTP THERE WOULD BE NO
CHANGES TO THE EXISTING RUNWAYS WHICH DETERMINES AN AIRPORT
CAPACITY. IN FACT THESE PROJECTS ARE
SIZED TO MATCH THE CAPACITY OF THE EXISTING RUNWAY SYSTEM
AND THEIR EXISTING CONFIGURATION.
AND THERE WOULD BE NO CHANGES TO THE EXISTING AIRCRAFT FLIGHT
PATHS AND PROCEDURES AS ESTABLISHED AND MANAGED BY THE
FAA. >> THE NEW BOARDING AREA WHICH
IS ENVISIONED TO PROVIDE CONTACT GATES CAPABLE OF
ACCOMMODATING BOTH INTERNATIONAL AND DOMESTIC
FLIGHTS AND THE NUMBER OF AIRCRAFT THAT WE CAN
ACCOMMODATE DEPENDS ON THE SIZE OF IT WHERE OUR AIRPORT GUESTS
CAN CONVENIENTLY AND SAFELY BOARD AN AIRCRAFT BY PASSENGER
BOARDING BRIDGE. >> THIS IS A CONTACT GATE.
IF WE DID NOTHING A STUDY IN THE AIR THE AIRPORT WOULD
INSTEAD HAVE TO ACCOMMODATE FUTURE DEMAND THROUGH WHAT WE
CALL REMOTE GATES WHERE WE HAVE PASSENGERS BUSSED FROM THE
TERMINALS TO AN AIRCRAFT PARKED ON THE AIRFIELD TO THEN BOARD
BY AN EXTERIOR RAMP OR STAIRWAY.
REMOTE GATES ARE COMMON IN OTHER COUNTRIES BUT THIS IS
NOT THE GUEST EXPERIENCE WE WANT FOR OUR PASSENGERS.
BUSSING TO REMOTE GATES CAN BE TIME CONSUMING AND DIFFICULT
FOR SOME PASSENGERS, ESPECIALLY DURING INCLEMENT WEATHER.
AND WHILE CONTACT GATES IN THE U.S. ARE THE NORM, THEY ARE NOT
REQUIRED FOR AIRLINES TO SCHEDULE FLIGHTS AND OPERATE IF
AN AIRCRAFT CAN LAND ON THE RUNWAYS AND THE TOWER CLEARS
THEM TO LAND, THEN AIRPORTS MUST BY FEDERAL REGULATIONS
ACCOMMODATE THEM IF TO REJECT THEM IS DISCRIMINATION.
IT'S IMPORTANT TO NOTE CONTACT GATES DO NOT INCREASE AIRPORT
CAPACITY SO THE QUESTION HAS BEEN RAISED.
DOES ADDING AIRPORT GATES CREATE DEMAND OR INDUCE GROWTH?
THE ANSWER IS NO. PASSENGERS DRIVE DEMAND
AND ABSOLUTELY IF PEOPLE IN THE BAY AREA CHOOSE TO FLY, WE WANT
YOU TO PICK US. AND SOMETIMES YOU MAY NOT HAVE
A CHOICE BECAUSE AIRLINES HAVE SELECT ROUTES DEPENDING ON THE
AIRPORT. BUT IF THERE ARE CHOICES, WE
WANT YOU TO PICK US. >> SOCIOECONOMIC FACTORS ARE
THE PRIMARY INDICATORS FOR PEOPLE'S PROPENSITY FOR AIR
TRAVEL. BAY AREA RESIDENTS HAVE A
STRONG PROPENSITY FOR FLYING TO FLY AND TRAVEL.
THE BAY AREA ALSO HAS MANY DESTINATION LOCATIONS
AND EVENTS SUCH AS THE SUPER BOWL THAT INCREASES DEMAND.
>> AIRLINES ADD FLIGHTS IN RESPONSE TO THAT REALIZED
DEMAND. SIMILARLY, AIRPORTS DEVELOP
FACILITIES TO ACCOMMODATE BACK DEMAND.
THE OLD ADAGE OF BUILD IT AND THEY WILL COME IS NOT TRUE
FOR AIRPORTS. IN FACT ITS DON'T BUILD IT
AND THEY STILL COME. I WANT YOU TO CONSIDER YOUR OWN
TRAVEL EXPERIENCE PARTICULARLY IN THE EAST COAST WHERE WE HAVE
MORE POPULATION AND THERE ARE MANY U.S. AIRPORTS THAT ARE
CONGESTED AND PEOPLE STILL FLY. THE TERMINAL SPACE DOES NOT
HAVE SUFFICIENT PASSENGER LOUNGE AREAS.
YOUR INSUFFICIENT AGENT BATHROOMS.
ALL OF THOSE THINGS THAT DON'T MAKE TRAVELING PLEASANT.
SO THAT'S WHAT THE ALREADY PIECE ABOUT.
>> IT'S IMPORTANT TO NOTE THAT IF AN AIR AIRCRAFT LANDS U.S.
AIRPORTS MUST ACCOMMODATE THEM. WE CAN ACCOMMODATE PASSENGERS
WITH A SUBSTANCE ORDERED GUEST EXPERIENCE.
OR WE CAN PROVIDE EXCEPTIONAL GUEST EXPERIENCE AND THROUGH
THE RTP THE AIRPORT CAN PROVIDE EXCEPTIONAL GUEST EXPERIENCE.
AND THAT'S WHAT WE MEAN BY GUEST EXPERIENCE WITH WE DON'T
WANT CROWDED TERMINALS. WE WANT YOU TO HAVE COMFORTABLE
LOUNGE AREAS, SUFFICIENT SEATS SO YOU'RE NOT SITTING ON THE
GROUND. WE WANT YOU TO HAVE CHARGING
PORTS. ALL OF THOSE THINGS ARE
SUFFICIENT BATHROOMS TO UP AVAILABLE FOR ALL OF OUR
PASSENGERS. THAT'S WHAT WE MEAN BY GUEST
EXPERIENCE. THOSE ARE THINGS THAT WE HAVE
DIRECT CONTROL OVER. LASTLY, WHAT DOES THE AIRPORT
DO ABOUT EXISTING AIRCRAFT NOISE CONCERNS?
AND TO BE CLEAR THIS IS SEPARATE FROM THE RTP NOISE
CONCERNS HAVE BEEN RAISED MUCH FURTHER AWAY FROM THE AIRPORT
AND OUTSIDE THE FEDERAL AND STATE RECOGNIZED NOISE
IMPACT AREAS. THE AIRPORT WILL CONTINUE TO
ACTIVELY ENGAGE OUR NOISE IMPACTED AREAS AND ALSO INFORM
THE COMMUNITY ON WHAT THE AIRPORT CAN AND CANNOT DO UNDER
THE CURRENT LEGAL FRAMEWORK. SO FOR EXAMPLE LOCAL
GOVERNMENTS GOVERNMENT AGENCIES LIKE THE AIRPORT CANNOT CHANGE
FAA PRESCRIBED FLIGHT PATHS OR THE FREQUENCY OF AIRCRAFT
OPERATIONS THAT AIRLINES SCHEDULE.
BUT WE CAN CONTINUE TO FACILITATE DIALOG.
SFO HAS BEEN AT THE FOREFRONT SINCE ENABLING FEDERAL
LEGISLATION IN 19. IN THE EARLY 1980S TO
PROACTIVELY ENGAGE THE FAA AND LOCAL CITIES NEAR THE
AIRPORT AND NOISE IMPACT AREAS TO ABATE AND MITIGATE AIRCRAFT
NOISE. AND SOME OF THE AIRPORT'S LONG
STANDING ACTIVITIES ARE LISTED ON THIS SLIDE.
I ALSO WANTED TO CLARIFY THAT ALL ITEMS ON THIS SLIDE IS
ABSOLUTELY TRUE. WITH REGARD TO THE ROUNDTABLE
MEMBERSHIP, THAT WAS SOMETHING THAT ELECTED OFFICIALS OF SAN
MATEO COUNTY VOTED ON AND DECIDED NOT TO INCLUDE THE
CITY OF PALO ALTO IN THE ROUNDTABLE.
>> SFO IS ALSO A NON-VOTING MEMBER ON THE ROUNDTABLE.
>> WE JUST PROVIDE PULLED ON I'M PAUSING THE SPEAKER'S TIME
MR. PRESIDENT. OKAY GREAT.
THANK YOU. OKAY.
>> PLEASE CONTINUE. LAST SLIDE.
THE RTP IS A LONG RANGE PLAN TO ACCOMMODATE FUTURE DEMAND WITH
FACILITIES SIZE TO ACCOMMODATE 71 MILLION PASSENGERS AS THEY
OCCUR OVER DECADES WITH AN ELEVATED GUEST EXPERIENCE.
THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU.
I JUST WANTED TO CLARIFICATION ON THAT LAST POINT YOU MADE
ABOUT PALO ALTO NOT BEING INCLUDED IN THE COMMUNITY
ROUNDTABLE BECAUSE IT SEEMS LIKE THAT WAS A POINT OF
CONTENTION DURING THE PRESENTATION OF THE APPEAL.
SO PALO ALTO IS ACTUALLY IN SANTA CLARA COUNTY, RIGHT?
>> CORRECT. SO WHY WOULD SAN MATEO VOTE ON
THE INCLUSION OF PALO ALTO OR NOT?
>> THE CITY OF PALO ALTO REQUESTED MEMBERSHIP IN THE SFO
AIRPORT COMMUNITY ROUNDTABLE AND IT'S CHAIRED BY ALL OF THE
IT CONTAINS MEMBERS OF THE ELECTED LOCAL CITIES OF OF THE
COUNTY AND IT IS SUBJECT TO TO VOTE ACCORDING TO THEIR RULES
AND THE THE MEMBERS DECIDED TO NOT ACCEPT ALL OF THE SAN MATEO
COUNTY MEMBERS DECIDED TO VOTE NOT TO INCLUDE THE SANTA CLARA
COUNTY MEMBER. >> CORRECT.
I SEE. OKAY.
>> AND THE SFO IS A NON-VOTING MEMBER OF THAT ROUNDTABLE.
>> OKAY. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MELGAR, I GUESS I
WANT TO JUST THAT THAT PRESENTATION FELT A LITTLE I
THOUGHT THAT THE ANSWER OR AT LEAST THE PRESENTATION WAS
SLIGHTLY DIFFERENT FROM WHAT I UNDERSTOOD FROM MY PRIOR
QUESTION TO TO PLANNING. >> SO WHEN I HAD ASKED HOW IS
THIS PLAN NOT GOING TO BE PART OF ADDING TO THE
INTENSIFICATION OF FLIGHTS AND NOISE OVER PALO ALTO IF
THAT IS WHAT'S HAPPENING? IT SOUNDED LIKE THE RESPONSE
FROM PLANNING WAS WELL WERE OR FROM THE CONSULTANT WAS WELL
WE'RE PRETTY MUCH AT CAPACITY. WE'RE NOT GOING TO SEE MUCH
INCREASE IN USE. THIS IS SORT OF BETTER
ACCOMMODATING AND PLANNING FOR BASICALLY THE AIRPORT WE GOT
NOW BUT INTO THE FUTURE WITHOUT SIGNIFICANT CHANGES TO HOW MUCH
HOW MANY FLIGHTS ARE COMING IN AND OUT OR HOW MANY
PASSENGERS ARE COMING IN AND OUT.
>> BUT THE RESPONSE FROM THE AIRPORT WAS THAT THIS IS A PLAN
FOR GROWTH OR THAT WE NEEDED TO BE ABLE TO ACCOMMODATE MORE
PASSENGERS AND THAT IF WE DIDN'T HAVE THIS IMPLEMENT THIS
PLAN, WE WOULD ONLY WE WOULD BE HAVING TO LIKE WHEEL OUT NOT
THAT WE WOULDN'T BE HAVING THE GROWTH NECESSARILY BUT THE
GROWTH WOULD BE I DON'T KNOW MORE UNPLEASANT FOR PASSENGERS
. AM I RIGHT?
IS THERE IS THERE A DIFFERENCE BETWEEN THOSE TWO STATEMENTS OR
THOSE TWO PERSPECTIVES? >> SO THE FORECAST THAT SO
CONSTRAINED FORECAST WAS DONE BASED ON THE CAPACITY OF THE
RUNWAY SYSTEM AND THAT CONSTRAINED FORECAST LOOKED AT,
YOU KNOW, HOW MANY OPERATIONS YOU KNOW, THE RUNWAY SYSTEM
COULD ACCOMMODATE AND IT'S ABOUT 505,000 ANNUAL OPERATIONS
ON A SUSTAINED AND A SUSTAINABLE MANNER.
>> WE ALSO LOOKED AT THE FLEET MIX HOW YOU KNOW, WHAT ARE THE
TRENDS WITH THE AIRLINES, HOW ARE THE AIRCRAFT CHANGING?
>> HOW MANY SEATS ARE IN THE EACH AIRCRAFT?
WHAT ARE THE LOAD FACTORS IN TERMS OF HOW MANY PEOPLE ARE
ACTUALLY ON THOSE PLANES? AND WHEN YOU LOOK AT IN THE
FUTURE, WHEN YOU LOOK AT THE TRENDS AND WHAT THE AIRLINES
ARE FLYING STARTING TO FLY HERE STARTING GOING TO BE FLYING
IN THE FUTURE BASED ON THEIR AIRLINE ORDERS YOU COME UP WITH
A PASSENGER NUMBER THAT ACCOUNT THAT IS ASSOCIATED WITH THAT
505,000 ANNUAL OPERATIONS AND THAT'S THE 77.1 MILLION
THAT I REFER TO. SO THE PASSENGER GROWTH WILL
HAPPEN AND THAT IS WHAT WAS EVALUATED IN TERMS OF YOU KNOW,
SOME OF THE EMPLOYEE CHANGES AND STUFF WITH IN THE AIR.
BUT THE 77 MILLION PASSENGER VIEWS AND THE 505,000 ANNUAL
AIRCRAFT OPERATIONS ARE THE CONSTRAINED FORECAST.
SO THAT IS WHAT IS GOING TO COME REGARDLESS OF WHAT HAPPENS
WITH THIS PROJECT WHETHER YOU BUILD THIS PROJECT OR NOT.
THAT IS WHAT THE AIRPORT CAN ACCOMMODATE TO THAT AND THIS
PLAN JUST MAKES THAT A MORE PLEASANT EXPERIENCE.
>> YES. WHEN WITHOUT THIS PLAN YOU'LL
HAVE CROWDED TERMINALS YOU KNOW, CROWDED ROADWAYS, YOU
WON'T HAVE ENOUGH RESTROOMS, ENOUGH CONCESSIONS, ETC. BUT
YOU ARE SAYING THIS THIS PLAN IS IRRELEVANT TO WHETHER THAT
GROWTH WHICH YOU'RE DESCRIBING IS FAIRLY MODEST, HOW THE
GROWTH IS GOING TO COME. >> IF YOU LOOK AT THE LONG TERM
PROJECTIONS FOR THE REGION. >> THEY'RE WAY HIGHER.
I MEAN THE UNCONSTRAINED FORECAST FOR PASSENGER
AND AIRCRAFT OPERATIONS IS IS WAY HIGHER FOR THE REGION.
SAN FRANCISCO ITS CAPACITY IS THIS AND THIS IS WHAT THEY'RE
GOING TO BE ABLE TO ACCOMMODATE .
>> ALL RIGHT. IF THERE ARE NO FURTHER
QUESTIONS OR COMMENTS, WE WILL NOW HEAR FROM MEMBERS OF THE
PUBLIC WHO WANT TO SPEAK IN OPPOSITION OF THE APPEAL.
>> SO IF YOU ARE HERE FOR THAT, PLEASE LINE UP OVER ON YOUR
RIGHT OR LEFT. >> ALL RIGHT.
SEEING NONE. PUBLIC COMMENTS IN OPPOSITION
TO THE APPEAL IS NOW CLOSED AND THEN WE WILL GIVE THE
APPELLANT THREE MINUTES FOR A REBUTTAL ARGUMENT.
>> THANK YOU. SO WHAT I DIDN'T HEAR DURING
THE PRESENTATION FROM THE OTHER SIDE IS ANY MEANINGFUL RESPONSE
TO OUR POINT THAT THE AIR DOES NOT IDENTIFY ANY PROVIDE ANY
INFORMATION ABOUT NOISE LEVELS IN THE YEAR 2045 AND SEQUEL
MANDATES THAT IF YOU'RE GOING TO USE 2045 AS THE BASELINE
YOU'VE GOT TO PROVIDE THAT BASIC INFORMATION AS TO WHAT
THAT WHAT IS THAT NOISE GOING TO BE.
AND IF THEY PROVIDED THIS AND I DID HEAR FROM FROM THEM THAT
WELL, YOU KNOW FLIGHTS ARE AT 93% OF CAPACITY SO NOT A BIG
DEAL WHEN THEY GET TO 100% BUT THE AIR SUPPOSED TO SAY WHAT
DOES THAT MEAN? WHAT IS THE DECIBEL DIFFERENCE
GOING TO BE RESULT FROM THAT GROWTH?
AND THE AIR FUNDAMENTALLY DOES NOT INCLUDE THAT BASIC
INFORMATION AS TO AND AGAIN IT'S REQUIRED TO IF YOU'RE
GOING TO USE 2045 AS THE BASELINE, YOU'VE GOT TO SET
FORTH WHAT THOSE IMPACTS, WHAT THOSE NOISE LEVELS ARE AND IF
THEY DID HAVE THAT INFORMATION THEN THEY WOULD HAVE SOME
EVIDENCE THAT THEY COULD USE TO EXPLAIN WHY THEY CAN OR CANNOT
JUSTIFY 2045 VERSUS EXISTING CONDITIONS AS THE BASELINE.
BUT UNTIL YOU HAVE THAT BASIC INFORMATION THERE, THEY DON'T
HAVE THE SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE TO EVEN SUPPORT THE APPROACH
THAT THEY'VE TAKEN AND THEY'VE CLEARLY NOT COMPLIED WITH THE
MANDATE AND SEEK TO PRESENT THAT INFORMATION.
THE ONE OTHER POINT I HEARD WAS THAT PALO ALTO IS FILING THIS
FOR NON SECRET REASONS. I'M FLABBERGASTED BY THAT.
I THINK THAT'S THAT'S A POINT THAT SYSTEM MISFIRE ON THEIR
PART. OBVIOUSLY WE'RE CONCERNED ABOUT
INCREASED NOISE FROM INCREASE IN FUTURE FLIGHTS OVER PALO
ALTO THAT'S A QUINTESSENTIAL SEQUOIA QUESTION.
THAT'S WHY WE'RE HERE. OBVIOUSLY THERE'S SOME EXISTING
NOISE ISSUES WE WON'T SOLVED BUT THIS PLAN EXACERBATES THOSE
EXISTING NOISE ISSUES AND WE ARE LEGITIMATELY UNDER SEQUOIA
ASKING FOR THOSE TO BE ADDRESSED.
>> AND I DON'T THINK I HAVE ANYTHING ELSE TO ADD.
>> I'LL ASK I MEAN I'LL I'LL ASK SO I THINK YOU'RE SAYING
THERE'S NO NOISE IN THAT THERE'S NO ANALYSIS OF THE
NOISE IMPACTS OF FUTURE NOISE BASELINE CONDITIONS FROM FROM
AIR. >> RIGHT.
AIR TRAFFIC IT'S COMPLETELY MISSING.
>> BUT IF THERE WERE THEY WOULD BE BASED ON THIS 2045 BASELINE
WHICH AND YOU'RE ALSO CHALLENGING WHETHER THAT'S THE
RIGHT BASELINE. YES THERE'S TWO ASPECTS TO OUR
CHALLENGE. ONE IS THEY SHOULDN'T BE USED.
THERE'S NOT ENOUGH EVIDENCE TO JUSTIFY USING 2045 AS THE
BASELINE. THE CHALLENGES ARE RELATED TO
TWO AND THE SECOND CHALLENGES EVEN ASSUMING THAT THEY
PROPERLY COULD DO THAT TOO. IN ORDER TO DO THAT TYPE OF
ANALYSIS YOU'VE GOT TO PROVIDE THE INFORMATION AS TO WHAT THE
NOISE IMPACTS ARE GOING TO BE IN THE YEAR 2045 OR AT LEAST
AND AND I READ TO YOU THE SECRET GUIDELINES THAT MANDATE
YOU HAVE TO HAVE A REASONABLE PROJECTION OF WHAT THAT
BASELINE IS AND THEN THEY WOULD HAVE THAT INFORMATION AS THE
BASELINE TO PRESENT THEIR ANALYSIS.
SO THESE TWO KIND OF DOVETAIL TOGETHER BUT THERE ARE TWO
CONCEPTUALLY DISTINCT SINGLE VIOLATIONS HERE.
>> ONE IS FACTUAL. I DISAGREE.
WE DISAGREE WITH THEM AND THE OTHER IS LEGAL.
THEY NEED TO HAVE THE 2045 NOISE INFORMATION AND IT'S
COMPLETELY I MEAN THIS IS AN EMPEROR HAS NO CLOTHES TYPE
SITUATION HERE. THERE'S COMPLETELY THEY SAY
THEY'RE DOING THIS 24, FIVE, 2045 ANALYSIS AND IT'S NOT
THERE. BUT EVEN IF THE POSITION IS
THAT THERE ISN'T ANY ANY NOISE IMPACTS AT ALL, THERE COULD NOT
BE BECAUSE THIS PROJECT IS NOT ADDING TO NOISE YOU WOULD STILL
NEED TO DO THAT. >> 2045 YES TO JUSTIFY USING
THE YEAR 2045 AS THE BASELINE YOU HAVE TO PRESENT WHAT IS
THAT BASED? WHAT ARE THOSE BASELINE
CONDITIONS YOU HAVE TO DESCRIBE NOISE LEVEL.
IT'S THEIR CHOICE TO USE 2045 AS THE BASELINE.
WHAT ARE THE NOISE CONDITIONS IN THE YEAR 2045?
THERE ARE NO PROJECTIONS WHATSOEVER.
THAT'S A FUNDAMENTAL SEQUENCE VIOLATION.
THANK YOU. >> ALL RIGHT.
WELL MAYBE I MEAN I GUESS I GUESS I DO HAVE ONE MORE
QUESTION THAN THAN FOR PLANNING .
>> CAN YOU TRY TO ADDRESS THAT THAT ISSUE OF WHETHER THERE
SHOULD BE A JUSTIFICATION OF A 2045 BASE AND I'M NOT QUITE
FOLLOWING AND MAYBE I GUESS I'M ASKING YOU YOU'RE NOT THE RIGHT
PERSON TO EXPLAIN THIS BUT BUT THERE SEEMS TO BE AN ARGUMENT
THAT THERE SHOULD BE A NOISE ANALYSIS OF THE DIFFERENTIAL
BETWEEN WHAT WOULD OTHERWISE BE THE 2045 BASELINE AND THE NOISE
WE'RE GOING TO GET UNDER THIS PLAN.
AND I THINK THE CITY'S POSITION IS THERE'S NO DIFFERENCE BUT I
PRESENT MANAGEMENT CASE TO THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT STAFF.
I'LL TRY TO ANSWER YOUR QUESTION.
IT'S A LITTLE COMPLEX QUESTION BUT FROM THE DEPARTMENT'S POINT
OF VIEW THE AIR FULLY ADDRESSES FUTURE CONDITIONS FOR THE
PURPOSE OF IMPACT THROUGH IMPACT ANALYSIS.
>> SO WE DON'T AGREE WITH THE APPELLANT'S STATEMENT THAT EIA
COMPLETELY BLOCKS 2045 FUTURE BASELINES TO THE EXTENT THEY
WERE USED IN THE ANALYSIS. >> ALSO 2045 AIRCRAFT EMISSIONS
WERE CERTAINLY CONSIDERED IN THE AIR AND ALSO THE
DEPARTMENT HAD DIFFICULTY IN COMING UP WITH AN EXACT
AMOUNT OF AIRCRAFT EMISSIONS INTO 20 2520 EXCUSE ME 2045
BECAUSE IT BECOMES A LITTLE SPECULATIVE TO FIGURE OUT HOW
MANY AIRCRAFT OPERATIONS WILL OCCUR IN 2045.
>> SO THAT MAY BE THE REASON WHY APPELLANT'S POINTING OUT
THAT THE FUTURE BASELINES MISSING BUT THAT'S NOT ENTIRELY
ACCURATE STATEMENT. >> IF THAT ANSWERS YOUR
QUESTION I WOULD ADD TO LISA GIBSON AN ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW
OFFICER I WOULD ADD TO MY COLLEAGUE'S SUMMARY THERE THAT
IT'S IMPORTANT TO NOTE THAT WE DID CHARACTERIZE 2019
CONDITIONS AND THE PROJECT AS WE HAVE EXPLAINED WOULD NOT
RESULT IN ANY INCREASE IN IN AIRCRAFT FLIGHTS AND SO THE
PROJECT'S IMPACT IN THAT REGARD IS IS NO IMPACT.
SO THE INCREASE FROM EXISTING CONDITIONS IS NO IMPACT THE
INCREASE FROM 2045 CONDITIONS IS NO IMPACT.
SO THE DELTA IS VERY EVIDENT. SO THE THE APPELLANT IS
FOCUSING ON A NUANCE HERE ABOUT A BASELINE AND IT'S EVIDENT
THAT THE A READER CAN EASILY DISCERN THE IMPORTANT GOAL OF
SEQUENT ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT ANALYSIS WHICH IS TO UNDERSTAND
THE IMPACT. SO REGARDLESS OF WHICH BASELINE
YOU CHOOSE WE'VE READ WE'VE CLEARLY EXPLAINED WHAT THE THE
PROJECT'S EFFECT WOULD BE WITH REGARD TO AIRCRAFT AND AND THAT
AFFECT THE THE EMISSIONS THAT WOULD RESULT IS ZERO.
SO I THINK YOU KNOW THEY'RE KIND OF FOCUSED LIKE FOCUSING
KIND OF GRASPING AT SOMETHING HERE AND OVERCOMPLICATING
SOMETHING AND I THINK THAT'S YOU KNOW, MAKING IT AGAIN MORE
COMPLICATED THAN IS NECESSARY. >> OKAY.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MELGAR, THANK YOU SO
MUCH. PRESIDENT.
SO WHILE WE WERE LISTENING TO THE PRESENTATIONS I GOT THE
ROSTER FROM MADAM CLERK. >> WE DO HAVE A REPRESENTATIVE
SEE ON THIS SFO ROUNDTABLE COMMUNITY COMMUNITY ROUNDTABLE
AND IT IS UNFILLED SO PERHAPS GIVEN THAT WE HAVE A POLITICAL
PROBLEM WITH THE CITY OF PALO ALTO WE ONE OF US COULD DO THAT
AND YOU KNOW I SEE THE CITY OF EAST PALO ALTO AS REPRESENTED
WHICH IS OF COURSE IN SAN MATEO COUNTY.
BUT PALO ALTO IS NOT BEING IN FACT IN SANTA CLARA COUNTY.
SO WE COULD PERHAPS WORK THIS OUT THROUGH THAT THAT AVENUE.
BUT GIVEN THE PRESENTATIONS THAT HAVE BEEN MADE BY THE
PLANNING DEPARTMENT AND THE APPELLANT, I ACTUALLY DON'T SEE
A REASON TO REVERSE THE FINAL ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT
CERTIFICATE ATION. I AM NOT CONVINCED THAT THIS IS
AN ARGUMENT THAT WOULD CAUSE ME TO VOTE FOR IT SO I WOULD LIKE
TO MAKE A MOTION FOR YOU. >> DO CAN I CLOSE THE HEARING?
>> OH YEAH. SO I WOULD LIKE TO HAVE THIS
HEARING. WELL SAY THAT THIS HEARING HAS
BEEN HELD AND IS NOW FILED. OKAY.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR. OKAY.
THANK YOU. SORRY I JUMPED THE GUN THERE.
I WOULD LIKE TO MAKE A MOTION TO APPROVE ITEM 38 TO AFFIRM
THE FINAL ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT AND TO TABLE ITEMS 39
AND NUMBER 40. >> ALL RIGHT.
IS THIS SECONDED BY MAHMOOD? AND UNLESS THERE'S DISCUSSION,
MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MOTION TO
APPROVE EXCUSE ME. ITEM 38 AND TABLE ITEMS 39
AND 40. SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SARDAR SAUTER EITHER ATTORNEYS WITHOUT
OBJECTION ITEM 38 IS APPROVED ITEMS 39 AND 40 ARE TABLED.
>> ALL RIGHT THAT GETS US THROUGH OUR SECOND OF THREE.
>> MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU PLEASE CALL OUR LAST OUR FINAL
3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER ITEMS 41 THROUGH 44 TOGETHER ITEMS 41
THROUGH 44 COMPRISE A PUBLIC HEARING OF PERSONS INTERESTED
IN OR OBJECTING TO THE APPROVAL OF A CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION FOR A PROPOSED PROJECT AT 825 SANSOM STREET
ISSUED BY THE PLANNING COMMISSION DATED NOVEMBER 13TH,
2025, WHICH INVOLVES A CHANGE OF USE FROM THE EXISTING PUBLIC
PARKING GARAGE. ITEM 42 IS THE MOTION THAT
APPROVES THE COMMISSION'S DECISION TO APPROVE THE
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION ITEM 43 DISAPPROVES THE
COMMISSION'S DECISION AND ITEM 44 IS THE MOTION TO DIRECT THE
PREPARATION OF FINDINGS. I SHOULD ALSO STATE, MR.
PRESIDENT, THAT ITEM 43 REQUIRES AN EIGHT VOTE
THRESHOLD. >> ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. >> THANK YOU FOR DESCRIBING
THIS APPEAL OF THE CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION FOR THE
PROPOSED PROJECT AT 25 SANSOM. I UNDERSTAND WE RECEIVED NOTICE
FROM THE PROJECT SPONSOR THAT THEY'RE NOT GOING TO BE MOVING
FORWARD WITH THIS PROJECT. WE WILL STILL NEED TO ACT
AFFIRMATIVELY ON THE APPEAL SO I ANTICIPATE THAT WE'LL BE
CONSIDERING A MOTION TO DISAPPROVE THE CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION AFTER DISCUSSION AND PUBLIC COMMENT.
I DON'T KNOW IF SUPERVISOR SAUTER IF YOU WANT TO SAY
ANYTHING YOU DON'T DEFINITELY DON'T HAVE TO AND IF I IF THE
APPELLANT OR PROJECT SPONSOR WANT TO SAY ANYTHING.
>> GOOD EVENING OR GOOD LATE AFTERNOON EVENING.
PETER ZIBLATT ON LAND USE COUNSEL FOR THE APPELLANT I
JUST WANT TO MAKE A FEW STATEMENTS.
I KNOW YOU'VE BEEN HERE FOR QUITE SOME TIME AS YOU
INDICATED THE APPLICANT HAS ABANDONED THEIR APPEAL.
I MEAN I'M SORRY THEIR APPLICATION AND THAT ALONE
JUSTIFIES AN APPROVAL OF THE APPEAL AND A DENIAL OF THE COPY
FOR FLEET CHARGING LOCATION. BUT IRRESPECTIVE OF THAT I
THINK IT WOULD BE APPROPRIATE FOR ME TO REITERATE WHY A
CONDITIONAL USE PERMIT SHOULD HAVE NEVER BEEN GRANTED AT THIS
LOCATION BY THE PLANNING COMMISSION.
>> IT WAS NEVER WARRANTED. THIS BOARD MADE A CONSCIOUS
DECISION WHEN IT AMENDED THE PLANNING CODE AND REQUIRED THAT
FLEET CHARGING ACROSS THE CITY IN PARTICULAR BE FACE
CONDITIONAL USE APPROVAL BECAUSE OF THE EXTERNALITIES
CREATED BY FLEET CHARGING AND AUTONOMOUS VEHICLE TAXIS
IN PARTICULAR. >> AND SO BECAUSE OF THAT
CONDITIONAL USE APPROVALS REQUIRED WHICH MEANS SCRUTINY
OF THESE TYPES OF LAND USES IS REQUIRED PARTICULARLY WHEN YOU
CITE OR LOCATE THESE USES IN CERTAIN NEIGHBORHOODS.
WITH THAT BEING SAID, I JUST WANTED TO REITERATE THAT AT
THIS LOCATION RIGHT ON THE BORDER OF JACKSON SQUARE IN THE
HEART OF BARBARY COAST WHERE PACIFIC STREET RUNS ONE WAY
EAST WEST OR ACTUALLY WEST PAST KATONAH RESTAURANT AND QUINCE
AND AROUND THE CORNER FROM BIX RESTAURANT I'M OBVIOUSLY
ALLUDING TO FOOD AT 530 IN THE AFTERNOON HERE BUT THE REALITY
IS THAT WAS NEVER A GOOD LOCATION FOR FLEET CHARGING OF
AUTONOMOUS VEHICLE TAXIS. IT DID NOT MEET THE THRESHOLD
REQUIREMENTS OF SECTION 3 OR 3 OF THE PLANNING CODE.
>> I'VE BEEN IN FRONT OF THIS BOARD ON NUMEROUS OCCASIONS ON
BEHALF OF CONDITIONAL USE PERMIT APPLICANTS AS WELL AS
APPELLANTS SEEKING TO OVERTURN CONDITIONAL USE APPROVAL AND I
CAN SAY THAT I'M PRETTY WELL VERSED IN SECTION 3O3 OF THE
PLANNING CODE AND WHAT'S REQUIRED TO ESTABLISH A
CONDITIONAL USE APPROVAL AT A AT A CERTAIN LOCATION.
>> AND IN THIS CASE I MEAN YOU DON'T HAVE TO GO ANY FURTHER
THAN SECTION 3 OR 3 A WHERE WE WHERE IT SPEAKS ABOUT USES AT
ARE NECESSARY OR DESIRABLE FOR A PARTICULAR NEIGHBORHOOD OR
USES THAT ARE INCONSISTENT OR CONSISTENT WITH A NEIGHBORHOOD
. THIS LOCATION WAS A BLOCK AWAY
FROM A NOTHER AUTONOMOUS VEHICLE FLEET CHARGING LOCATION
THAT WAS GRANDFATHERED IN BECAUSE IT HAPPENED OR WAS
ESTABLISHED PRIOR TO FLEET CHARGING BECOMING CONDITIONALLY
REQUIRED A CONDITIONAL USE PERMIT REQUIREMENT PUTTING
CITYWIDE AND THAT WAS NEVER EVEN TAKEN INTO CONSIDERATION
THAT THERE WAS THIS CONSOLIDATION OR CONCENTRATION
OF FLEET CHARGING IN RIGHT ON THE BORDER OF A HISTORIC
NEIGHBORHOOD. IT'S JUST NOT THE APPROPRIATE
LOCATION. AND SO THOSE TYPES OF USES NEED
THE SCRUTINY THAT THEY'RE AFFORDED UNDER SECTION 3O3
AND THESE SHOULD NOT BE PERFUNCTORY APPROVALS AND SO
I'M HAPPY TO HEAR THAT THE APPLICANT WITHDREW OR ABANDONED
THEIR APPLICATION AT THIS LOCATION.
BUT I DID FEEL IT WAS IMPORTANT FOR ME TO GET UP HERE
AND REITERATE THAT CONDITIONAL USE APPROVALS ARE CONDITIONAL
USE APPROVALS. >> THEY HAVE A THERE'S A NEED
FOR ANALYSIS AND SCRUTINY NOT SOMETHING THAT SHOULD JUST BE
SIMPLY APPROVED BECAUSE THEY'RE CONCLUSORY.
OH IT'S THIS IS A GREAT LOCATION FOR FULLY CHARGING IT
NEEDS A LITTLE MORE ANALYSIS THAN THAT AND WITH THAT I WILL
YIELD THE REST OF MY TIME TO MARK GLEASON WHO'S ALSO HERE ON
BEHALF OF THE APPELLANT. GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS.
I'LL TRY TO BE AS DISTINCT AS POSSIBLE AS WELL RECOGNIZING
WHAT THE OUTCOME WE HAVE HERE IN FRONT OF US.
AND I WOULD SAY THAT IN IN DEVELOPMENT OF COURSE ONE OF
THE FIRST THINGS IS FOR THE PARTIES TO GET TOGETHER.
WE WOULD SUGGEST THAT THE REASON THIS DEVELOPMENT HAS
HAPPENED HERE IN THE LAST DAY OR SO IS BECAUSE WE DID HAVE
SINCERE DIALOG WITH THE APPLICANT AND THEN OTHER FORCES
TOOK PLACE ON THEIR SIDE NOT FROM US AND AND THEY MADE THEIR
DECISION. I'LL JUST SAY BECAUSE THE
MEMBERS ARE YOU AND YOU WANT TO HAVE A LITTLE VOICE HERE.
IN ANY EVENT I'LL JUST BE AGAIN AS CONCISE AS I CAN.
THE APPEAL WAS FILED IN ORDER TO ALLOW FOR THE REVIEW OF
OTHER PROPOSED AUTONOMOUS VEHICLE FLEET CHARGING A MIXED
USE COMMERCIAL RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOOD DURING THE
PREVIOUS TERM OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
IT WAS DETERMINED THAT AUTONOMOUS VEHICLE FLEET
CHARGING REQUIRES SPECIAL REVIEW SO THAT THE IMPACT OF
THESE PROPOSALS HAVE OUR COMMUNITY AND WORKERS THE THE
IMPACT ON ON OUR COMMUNITY AND WORKERS CAN BE FULLY
WEIGHED. >> THE SPECIFIC PROPOSAL
APPEALED BY THE TEAMSTERS TODAY REFLECTS ON THE PATTERN THAT WE
ARE WITNESSING OF FLEET CHARGING PROPOSALS THAT IMPACT
OUR COMMUNITIES AND AND WHICH AFFECT THE CONDITIONS OF
WORKING PEOPLE. THE TEAMSTERS INTEREST REMAINS
THE SAME AS IT HAS FOR OVER 100 YEARS IN THIS INDUSTRY WELL
BEFORE ELECTRIC VEHICLES CAME ON THE SCENE FOR FAIRNESS
AND CONTINUE CREATION OF WORKING CONDITIONS PERFORMED BY
OUR MEMBERS IN AN ENVIRONMENT COMPATIBLE WITH THE COMMUNITY
AT LARGE. WE AGAIN THANK YOU FOR YOUR
TIME TODAY AND THE REST FOR THE MOMENT.
THANK YOU ALL RIGHT. I THINK THAT IS IT FOR THE
APPELLANT DOES THE PROJECT SPONSORS REPRESENTATIVE WANT TO
SAY ANYTHING? >> HELLO MR. GENIUS THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MANDOLIN AND SUPERVISORS JUST TO CONFIRM
TESLA IS ON BEHALF OF TESLA WITHDRAWING THEIR APPLICATION
AND NOT PROCEEDING. >> THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU.
AND SO WE DO NEED TO TAKE PUBLIC COMMENT ON THIS MATTER
WITH THE UNDERSTANDING THAT IT IS UNLIKELY THE PROJECT WILL BE
MOVING FORWARD. MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE FIRST SPEAKER IF THERE ARE ANY?
ONLY ON THIS ITEM. LOOKS LIKE WE DON'T HAVE ANY
PUBLIC COMMENT PUBLIC COMMENT ON THIS ITEM IS NOW CLOSED
AND SO SEEING NO ONE ELSE WELL I'M GOING TO CLOSE THE CLOSE
THE HEARING SUPERVISOR AND THEN CALL ON YOU IF THAT'S ALL RIGHT
. >> HEARING HAS BEEN HELD AND IS
NOW FILED AND NOW I WOULD LIKE TO CALL ON SUPERVISOR
SLAUGHTER. >> THANK YOU.
PRESENT AMENDMENT I WILL TRY TO QUICKLY ADD A TOUCH MORE
CONTEXT AND SUMMARIZE AND GET US ON OUR WAY HERE.
>> THIS PROPERTY IS CURRENTLY USED AS A PRIVATE PARKING
GARAGE. IT'S EXACTLY AT THE NEXUS OF A
LOT OF DISTRICT THREE NEIGHBORHOODS LIKE JACKSON
SQUARE, TELEGRAPH HILL FINANCIAL DISTRICT AND THE
EMBARCADERO. >> THE PROPOSED PROJECT WAS FOR
30 PRIVATE EV CHARGERS TO BE USED FOR FLEET CHARGING ON THE
UPPER LEVEL 18 PUBLIC EV CHARGERS TO BE USED ON THE
GROUND LEVEL AND THEN 31 PRIVATE PARKING SPACES ON THE
BASEMENT LEVEL. THE PROPOSED PROJECT WAS
SPONSORED BY TESLA BUT THEY HAVE SINCE PULLED OUT OF THE
PROJECT AS OF LAST WEEK. >> NOW GIVEN THAT THIS
CONDITIONAL USE WAS GRANTED BASED ON THE PRIOR PROJECT
WHICH IS NOW DEFUNCT, I DON'T BELIEVE A QUEUE IS NECESSARY AT
THE MOMENT WE ARE LEFT HERE WITH NO IDENTIFIABLE ACTIVE
PROJECT PROPOSED FOR THIS SITE. SO GIVEN ALL OF THIS I WOULD
LIKE TO MOVE ITEM 43 TO GRANT THIS APPEAL AND DISAPPROVE THE
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION WITH AMENDMENTS TO THE MOTION
AS DRAFTED. WE PREPARED THESE AMENDMENTS
IN ADVANCE FOR THE BOARD TO CONSIDER BECAUSE THE PROJECT
SPONSOR HAD INDICATED THAT THEY ARE WITHDRAWING FROM THE
PROJECT AND NO LONGER CONTESTING THIS APPEAL.
THEREFORE THEREFORE I FIND THIS PROJECT TO BE INCONSISTENT WITH
SECTION 3O3 ON THE BASIS THAT IT IS NO LONGER NECESSARY OR
DESIRABLE FOR INCOMPATIBLE WITH THE NEIGHBORHOOD DUE TO THE
PROJECT NOT MOVING FORWARD. ALSO MOVED TO TABLE ITEMS 42
AND 44. >> THANK YOU.
>> OKAY. AND THAT HAS BEEN SECONDED BY
SUPERVISOR MELGAR. >> AND I DON'T SEE ANY
DISCUSSION SO MADAM CLERK CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON
ITEM 43 AS AMENDED SPECIFICALLY OR ON ITEM 43 AS AMENDED
AND TABLING 42 AND 44 ALTOGETHER?
>> OKAY. ON ITEM 43 AS AMENDED
AND TABLING ITEMS 42 AND 44. >> SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON
EYES SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MONGOLOID NOT ONE
EYES SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HIGH HANDELMAN EYES SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SAUTER I SAUTER I THERE ARE TEN
EYES ALL RIGHT WITHOUT OBJECTION ITEM 43 AS AMENDED IS
APPROVED AND ITEMS 42 AND 44 ARE TABLED.
>> AND WITH THAT MADAM CLERK LET'S GO BACK TO ITEM 22.
>> ITEM 20 TWO THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE AWARD
OF PROFESSIONAL SERVICES AGREEMENT FOR PROGRAM ADVISORY
SERVICES RELATED TO THE WATERFRONT RESILIENCE PROGRAM
BETWEEN JACOBS INTERNET ENGINEERING GROUP INC AND THE
CITY AND COUNTY IN AN AMOUNT OF 40 MILLION FOR A FIVE YEAR TERM
MARCH 2ND, 2026 THROUGH MARCH 1ST, 2023 A 2031 WITH A SINGLE
OPTION TO EXTEND FOR FIVE ADDITIONAL YEARS PLEASE CALL
THE ROLL ON ITEM 22. SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR OF MODE MARK MODE
EYES SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN MANDALAY MAN EYES SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR EYE AND SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER I
THEIR ATTORNEYS WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS
ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 23 ITEM 23 THIS IS A
RESOLUTION TO APPROVE AN EMERGENCY DECLARATION FROM THE
PORT OF SAN FRANCISCO TO PROVIDE IMMEDIATE EMERGENCY
REPAIRS TO STABILIZE DRY DOCK NUMBER TWO AT PIER 68 FOR AN
ESTIMATED COST OF 10 MILLION AND TO ADOPT ENVIRONMENTAL
FINDINGS. >> LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS
ADOPTED. MADAME CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
24. >> ITEM 24 A RESOLUTION TO
AUTHORIZE THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY
DEVELOPMENT TO EXECUTE A STANDARD AGREEMENT WITH THE CD.
THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY
DEVELOPMENT FOR A $1.5 MILLION GRANT AWARD UNDER CDW'S PIP
THEIR PRO HOUSING INCENTIVE PROGRAM TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND
ANTICIPATED REVENUE OF PIP GRANT FUNDS IN THE AMOUNT OF
1.5 MILLION. >> AGAIN SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 25 ITEM 25 THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PLANNING CODE TO PERMIT PARKING TO
PERMIT PARKING OF UP TO TWO OPERABLE VEHICLES NOT INCLUDING
BOATS, TRAILERS, RECREATIONAL VEHICLES, MOBILE HOMES OR
BUSSES IN DRIVEWAYS LOCATED IN REQUIRED FRONT SETBACKS,
SIDE YARDS OR REAR YARDS TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION
AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> SUPERVISOR WONG I'M PLEASED TO SUPPORT THIS ORDINANCE AND I
WANT TO THANK THE MAYOR AND SUPERVISORS CHAN AND MELGAR FOR
CO-SPONSORING AND BRINGING THIS FORWARD.
THIS CHANGE IS PARTICULARLY RELEVANT FOR THE WEST SIDE
NEIGHBORHOODS LIKE THE SUNSET PARK AND OTHER DISTRICT FOR
COMMUNITIES WHERE MANY HOMES HAVE FRONT SETBACK DRIVEWAYS
AND STREET PARKING CAN BE CHALLENGING ALLOWING RESIDENTS
TO PARK IN THEIR OWN DRIVEWAYS AS A PRACTICAL COMMON SENSE
APPROACH THAT REFLECTS HOW OUR NEIGHBORHOODS FUNCTION.
I ALSO WANT TO NOTE THAT THIS ORDINANCE RECEIVED UNANIMOUS
SUPPORT FROM THE PLANNING COMMISSION AND ALIGNS WITH THE
CITY'S BROADER PERMIT S.F. EFFORT TO MODERNIZE OUTDATED
RULES AND REDUCE UNNECESSARY RED TAPE.
ULTIMATELY THIS IS ABOUT CLARITY, FAIRNESS AND SENSIBLE
GOVERNANCE. IT PROVIDES CERTAINTY TO
HOMEOWNERS AND IMPROVES DAY TO DAY QUALITY OF LIFE WITHOUT
UNDERMINING OUR PLANNING GOALS .
FOR THOSE REASONS I SUPPORT THIS ORDINANCE AND URGE MY
COLLEAGUES TO VOTE YES ON FIRST READING.
>> THANK YOU. AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS
ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
26. >> ITEM 26 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE
TO AMEND THE PLANNING CODE TO MAKE VARIOUS CLARIFYING
AND TYPOGRAPHICAL CHANGES AND TO PROHIBIT MASSAGE
ESTABLISHMENTS AND MASSAGE SOLO PRACTITIONER USES AS ACCESSORY
USES TO RESIDENTIAL USES TO AFFIRM THE SPEAKER
DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS
27 AND 28 TOGETHER ITEMS 27 AND 28 ARE TWO RESOLUTIONS THAT
AUTHORIZE THE ACCEPTANCE AND RECORDING OF TO OBLIGATION
EASEMENTS. ITEM 27 IS FROM U.S. 180 EL
CAMINO OWNER LLC FOR THE DEVELOPMENT AT 180 EL CAMINO
REAL IN SOUTH SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA AT NO COST TO THE
CITY AND COUNTY. AND ITEM 28 IS FROM NAVDEEP
BERKELEY FOR THE DEVELOPMENT OF 413 A LEAD AWAY
IN UNINCORPORATED SAN MATEO COUNTY, CALIFORNIA AT NO COST
TO THE CITY AND COUNTY TO AFFIRM THE SECOND DETERMINATION
AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS FOR BOTH ITEMS.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. >> >> WHATEVER.
>> OH I HOPE IT'S NOT SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ME.
ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON. NOW I GUESS WE NEED TO DO
NOTHING. >> WE JUST NEED TO CALL THE
ROLL. MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL? WELL, WE NEED TO RESCIND THE
VOTE AND THEN REVOTE. >> ALL RIGHT.
OKAY. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MELGAR. WE CAN TAKE THAT WITHOUT
OBJECTION. WITHOUT OBJECTION.
THE THE THE MOTION IS RESCINDED OR THE ACTIONS RESCINDED
AND THEN MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE ITEMS ON
ITEMS 27 AND 28 SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG
WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
MANAGEMENT I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SADR
SADR I THEIR ATTORNEYS RIGHT WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 29 ITEM
29 RESOLUTION TO AMEND THE STREET ENCROACHMENT PERMIT
TERMS FOR MAIDEN LANE REGARDING THE DESIGNATED PERMITTED
AND PERMISSIBLE ACTIVITIES TO AMEND AND RESCIND THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS AUTHORIZATION FOR THE STREET CLOSURE OF MAIDEN
LANE BETWEEN STOCKTON AND KEARNY STREETS AND TO URGE
THE MUNICIPAL TRANSPORTATION AGENCY BOARD OF DIRECTORS TO
MODIFY THE STREET CLOSURE HOURS FOR SUCH STREETS AND TO
AUTHORIZE THE PUBLIC WORKS DIRECTOR TO FINALIZE A MODIFIED
STREET ENCROACHMENT PERMIT FOR MAIDEN LANE.
>> OKAY. AND WE DO NOW HAVE THE SAME
HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED
NOW THIS SUPERVISOR CHEN MOVE ON THE LAST ONE I BELIEVE SHE
DID. YEAH.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM
CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 30. >> ITEM 30 A RESOLUTION TO ADD
THE COMMEMORATIVE STREET NAME STEPHEN TENNIS WAY TO THE 200
BLOCK OF EDDY STREET IN RECOGNITION OF STEPHEN
TENNIS'S DECADES OF SERVICE STEWARDSHIP, LEADERSHIP
AND COMMUNITY BUILDING IN THE TENDERLOIN NEIGHBORHOOD OF SAN
FRANCISCO. >> ALL RIGHT.
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 31.
>> ITEM 31 ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE POLICE CODE TO EXPAND THE
CURRENT TENDERLOIN RETAIL HOURS RESTRICTION PILOT PROGRAM UNDER
WHICH RETAIL FOOD AND TOBACCO ESTABLISHMENTS IN THE
RESTRICTED AREA ARE PROHIBITED FROM BEING OPEN TO THE PUBLIC
FROM 12 A.M. TO 5 A.M. OR FROM 2 A.M. TO 5 A.M. IF SUBJECT TO
REGULATION BY THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF ALCOHOLIC
BEVERAGE CONTROL TO ENCOMPASS A HIGH CRIME AREA ACROSS THE
TENDERLOIN AND SOUTH OF MARKET NEIGHBORHOODS AND TO EXTEND THE
DURATION OF THE PILOT PROGRAM CURRENTLY SET TO EXPIRE IN JULY
OF 2026 TO INSTEAD EXPIRE 18 MONTHS FROM THE EFFECTIVE DATE
OF THE ORDINANCE. >> SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANKS
PRESIDENT BENJAMIN. >> COLLEAGUES, IT'S MY VIEW
THAT THIS LEGISLATION MAKES SMALL BUSINESSES THE SCAPEGOATS
FOR THE FAILURES OF S.F. PD INSTEAD OF ADDRESSING REAL
CRIME. THIS PROPOSAL PUNISHES NIGHT
WORKERS AND SMALL BUSINESSES MANY OF THEM IN IMMIGRANT OWNED
WHO ARE ALREADY DOING EVERYTHING THEY CAN JUST TO
SURVIVE. THE SMALL BUSINESS COMMISSION
VOTED AGAINST THIS FOR A REASON.
IT IS A ROUNDABOUT ATTEMPT TO CURB CRIME BY SHIFTING
RESPONSIBILITY AND FINANCIAL LOSS ONTO SMALL BUSINESSES
WHILE CONTRIBUTING TO THE DISPLACEMENT OF CRIME INTO MY
DISTRICT. THE MISSION WHICH HAS BEEN
CONSISTENT WITH D-MAX ON THE RECORD STRATEGY AND FURTHER
SUPPORTED BY THE TENTATIVE STUDY THE COMMITTEE CITED
IN APPROVING THIS ORDINANCE. >> EVEN THE MAYOR'S SORRY EVEN
THE LEGISLATION THE STUDY'S LEAD AUTHOR THAT HAS BEEN
REFERENCED IN REGARDS TO THIS LEGISLATION HAS ACKNOWLEDGED
THAT THE BAN MAY HAVE CAUSED CRIME TO BE DISPLACED.
>> ARE WE REALLY SUPPOSED TO BELIEVE THAT AS IF PD WITH A
NEW REAL TIME INVESTIGATION CENTER WITH AS OUR MAYOR HAS
SAID, ONGOING PARTNERSHIPS WITH FBI, ATF, DEA, OUR CITY
ATTORNEY AND OTHER FEDERAL AGENCIES INVOLVED IN DISRUPTING
THE DRUG TRADE WITH DRONES, SURVEILLANCE CAPABILITIES,
FLOCK CAMERAS AND MORE DOESN'T HAVE ENOUGH STAFF, TECHNOLOGY
OR INTELLIGENCE TO GO AFTER LARGE SCALE GAMBLING
OPERATIONS. ILLEGAL CASINOS AND DRUG
MARKETS WITHOUT DISPLACING THEM TO NEARBY AREAS.
THIS ISN'T A SMALL BUSINESS PROBLEM.
IT'S A LEADERSHIP AND ACCOUNTABILITY PROBLEM.
AND I WILL BE IN THE MAYOR'S OFFICE WITH MY CONSTITUENTS
WHEN CRIME TAKES UP IN THE MISSION.
>> AND I WILL KEEP REPEATING THIS POINT WHEN AS THE PD COMES
ASKING FOR MILLIONS MORE OF OVERTIME AND LATER THIS YEAR AS
COMMISSIONER WILLIAM ORTIZ CARTAGENA SAID IF YOU HAVE A
MOSQUITO ON YOUR SHOULDER YOU WOULDN'T TAKE A SLEDGEHAMMER TO
YOUR SHOULDER. >> IT WOULD KILL THE MOSQUITO
BUT WOULD ALSO LOSE YOUR ARM. >> FOR THAT REASON I WILL BE
VOTING NO SUPERVISED DORSI. >> THANK YOU PRESIDENT
MANDOLIN. COLLEAGUES, THIS LEGISLATION
BUILDS ON A PILOT PROGRAM THAT THE BOARD ADOPTED IN 2024 TO
ADDRESS PERSISTENT LATE NIGHT CONDITIONS IN THE TENDERLOIN
WHICH WAS DRIVEN BY DRUG ACTIVITY, VIOLENCE AND RELATED
STREET DISORDER. THAT PILOT WORKED IN LIMITING
LATE NIGHT RETAIL HOURS IN A TARGETED AREA BETWEEN THE HOURS
OF MIDNIGHT AND 5 A.M. HAD THE EFFECT OF REDUCING SERIOUS
CRIME, IMPROVING STREET CONDITIONS AND MAKING THE
NEIGHBORHOOD FEEL SAFER. THOSE RESULTS WERE CONFIRMED
NOT ONLY BY THE POLICE DEPARTMENT AND ITS DATA BUT
ALSO BY THE COMMUNITY'S EXPERIENCE AND AN INDEPENDENT
ACADEMIC STUDY RELEASED LAST FALL WHICH FOUND A 56%
REDUCTION IN DRUG RELATED CRIME WITH NO EVIDENCE OF
DISPLACEMENT INTO NEARBY NEIGHBORHOODS OR TO OTHER
HOURS. THIS ORDINANCE EXTENDS THAT
SAME TARGETED APPROACH TO A LARGER AREA OF THE TENDERLOIN
AND TO DEFINED PORTION OF SOUTH OF MARKET INCLUDING SIXTH
STREET WHERE STREET CONDITIONS AND OPEN AIR DRUG SCENES ARE AT
THEIR WORST AND IT RESETS THE PILOT CLOCK TO ALLOW FOR A FULL
18 MONTH EVALUATION. THERE IS BROAD COMMUNITY
SUPPORT FOR THIS EXPANSION FROM RESIDENTS, NEIGHBORHOOD GROUPS
AND STAKEHOLDERS WHO HAVE LIVED WITH THESE CONDITIONS FOR FAR
TOO LONG. AT THE SAME TIME I WANT TO BE
CLEAR THAT THE VAST MAJORITY OF BUSINESSES AFFECTED ARE LAW
ABIDING AND DOING THE RIGHT THING.
THIS IS NOT ABOUT BLAMING THEM .
IT'S A FOCUSED TIME LIMITED TOOL AIMED AT DISRUPTING LATE
NIGHT CONDITIONS DRIVEN BY A SMALL NUMBER OF BAD ACTORS.
MY OFFICE HAS BEEN WORKING CLOSELY WITH MERCHANTS
AND BUSINESS OWNERS AND WE WILL CONTINUE TO DO SO ALONGSIDE THE
OFFICE OF WORKFORCE AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT
AND OTHER PARTNERS TO EXPLORE MITIGATION STRATEGIES FOR
COMPLIANT BUSINESSES BECAUSE ACCOUNTABILITY AND SUPPORT MUST
GO TOGETHER. I DO WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR
MAHMUD FOR PARTNERING ON THIS FROM THE BEGINNING
AND SUPERVISOR WANG FOR HIS CO-SPONSORSHIP AND SUPPORT AS
WELL. I WANT TO THANK THE THE
BUSINESSES WHO THAT ARE AFFECTED MANY OF WHOM AREN'T
AREN'T THRILLED WITH THIS BUT UNDERSTAND THAT THEY'RE BEING
ASKED TO SACRIFICE FOR THE GOOD OF THE NEIGHBORHOOD TO GIVE A
LITTLE BIT OF A COOLING OFF PERIOD.
I WOULD ALSO ACKNOWLEDGE THAT THIS IS NOT THE MAGIC WAND THAT
SOLVES EVERYTHING. IT'S ONLY A PARTIAL STRATEGY.
IT'S TIME LIMITED. AS OTHER THINGS PLAY OUT.
BUT I REALLY DO WANT TO APPRECIATE THE BUSINESSES WHO
HAVE BEEN ENGAGED ON THIS. AND ONE THING THAT I HAVE SAID
TO ALL THE RESIDENTS OF THE NEIGHBORHOODS AFFECTED.
IT'S UP TO US AS CONSUMERS TO MAKE SURE THAT WE'RE DOING OUR
PART TO REWARD THE BUSINESSES THAT WERE ASKING TO CLOSE EARLY
AT MIDNIGHT. WE CAN DO THAT DURING THE HOURS
THAT THEY'RE OPEN AND I HOPE THAT THE COMMUNITY WILL SHOW UP
TO SUPPORT THEM BECAUSE THEY ARE DOING THEIR PART FOR OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD AND THAT'S SOMETHING THAT I HOPE WE CAN
ALL SUPPORT. >> SUPERVISOR MAHMUD.
THANK YOU COLLEAGUES. >> I'M A CO-SPONSOR OF THIS
LEGISLATION AS WELL WITH SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND GIVEN IT
AFFECTED MY DISTRICT ORIGINALLY AND WHERE THE POLL WAS
CONNECTED WANTED TO SHARE SOME THOUGHTS.
THIS LEGISLATION WILL EXTEND THE PILOT ALREADY IN PLACE BY
AN ADDITIONAL 18 MONTHS TO BRING THE BENEFITS THAT WE'VE
SEEN IN THE TENDERLOIN TO THE REST OF THE NEIGHBORHOOD BUT
ALSO TO SOUTH OF MARKET TO MAKE SURE THAT WE'RE TAKING A
REGIONAL APPROACH IN THESE RESPECTIVE NEIGHBORHOODS THAT
ARE SO INTERLINKED. THE DATA HAS SHOWN THAT IT IS A
PROVEN TOOL TO IMPROVE QUALITY OF LIFE IN THE NEIGHBORHOODS AT
THE HEART OF OUR CITY. >> IT'S IMPORTANT TO RECOGNIZE
THAT THIS IS NOT ABOUT TACKLING INDIVIDUAL BUSINESSES INSIDE
THEIR ESTABLISHMENTS. THE CITY ATTORNEY IS DOING
OPERATIONS SUCCESSFULLY ON THE CASINOS THE GAMBLING.
THIS IS ABOUT ADDRESSING STREET CONDITIONS OUTSIDE OF THE
RESPECTIVE ESTABLISHMENTS AND WHAT WE'VE SEEN FROM THE
PEER REVIEWED STUDIES THAT HAVE SHOWN IS THAT THE DRUG RELATED
INCIDENTS AROUND THOSE ESTABLISHMENTS DROPPED BY 56%
DURING THE PILOT PERIOD AND LOITERING AROUND LATE NIGHT
ESTABLISHMENTS AND AGAIN THIS IS MIDNIGHT TO 5 A.M. NOT
DURING THE DAYTIME ISN'T JUST AN ISSUE OF OPTICS.
IT'S PART OF A LARGE AND A VERY REAL PERSISTENT PROBLEM OF
UNSAFE DRUG MARKETS TAKING HOLD OF OUR NEIGHBORHOODS IN THE
PUBLIC SAFETY NEIGHBORHOOD SERVICES COMMITTEE.
>> WE'VE HAD A COUPLE OF HEARINGS ON THIS TOPIC LAST
YEAR. WE HEARD FROM FAMILIES, WE
HEARD FROM WOMAN, WE HEARD FROM CHILDREN, WE HEARD FROM
IMMIGRANTS WHO CAME IN, SOME OF WHOM WERE IN TEARS DUE TO THE
CONDITIONS THAT THEY HAVE TO WALK THROUGH IN THE
NEIGHBORHOOD EVERY DAY AND EVERY NIGHT JUST THIS
MORNING SOMEONE WAS TELLING ME HOW THEY FEEL THAT THEM AS
RESIDENTS ARE ALREADY UNDER A CURFEW AND HOSTAGE IN THEIR OWN
NEIGHBORHOOD WHERE THEY DON'T FEEL SAFE GOING OUTSIDE.
>> WE ARE ADMINISTERING THIS TYPE OF SOLUTION SO THAT THE
RESIDENTS OF THE TENDERLOIN THEMSELVES DON'T FEEL THEY'RE
IN A DE FACTO CURFEW TO BE ABLE TO FEEL COMFORTABLE WALKING
OUTSIDE. NO ONE IS SAYING THAT THIS IS A
PERFECT SOLUTION. IT IS A TEMPORARY MEASURE FOR
18 MONTHS AS SUPERVISOR DORSEY MENTIONED, TO ALLOW THE CITY TO
DEVELOP A MORE LONG TERM PLAN TO FIGURE OUT WHAT CHANGES DO
WE ADMINISTER TO BALANCE ALL THE NEEDS OF THE NEIGHBORHOOD
AND ENSURE THAT WE HAVE THE EFFECTIVE TOOLS IN PLACE.
BUT WE HAVE TO STEM THE BLEEDING BEFORE WE CAN FIGURE
OUT THE ACTUAL SOLUTION. I WILL ALSO CONTINUE TO WORK
WITH SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND WITH THE COMMUNITY STAKEHOLDERS TO
IDENTIFY WAYS TO UPLIFT AND SUPPORT THE SMALL
BUSINESSES IN THE YEAR AHEAD AND THAT ACKNOWLEDGE THAT THE
SMALL BUSINESSES HAVE BEEN STRONG PARTNERS TO THE CITY
THROUGHOUT THIS EFFORT AND SHARE OUR GOAL CREATING A
NEIGHBORHOOD THAT CAN BE BOTH SAFE AND VIBRANT.
AND THIS CURFEW WILL ENSURE THAT IT'S AN IMPORTANT STEP TO
TACKLING THOSE STREET CONDITIONS.
AND THANK YOU AGAIN, SAM DORSEY FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP ON TAKING
THIS FORWARD. >> SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MADAM AND I JUST WANTED TO ADD BECAUSE WHEN I
100% AGREE WE'RE SUPERVISOR FIELDER BUT ALSO LOOK AT WHEN
WE HAVE TYPICALLY IN THE PAST DONE SOMETHING THAT AFFECTED
OUR BUSINESSES. WE TRY TO BRING BUSINESSES
TOGETHER TO ADDRESS THE LOSS OF REVENUE.
>> WHEN WE BANNED E-CIGARETTES HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO WE
CREATED A MITIGATION GROUP WITH THE SMALL BUSINESS COMMUNITY TO
TRY AND ATTEMPT TO ADDRESS THE IMPACTS OF REVENUE LOSS.
>> I DIDN'T HEAR A CONVERSATION ABOUT THIS HAPPENING
AND WORKING WITH BUSINESSES TO TRY TO COME UP WITH SOMETHING
THAT WILL ASSIST THEM DURING THIS TIME PERIOD.
AND I KNOW 18 MONTHS OF REVENUE LOSS CAN MAKE OR BREAK A
BUSINESS PARTICULARLY IN THIS CLIMATE.
AND SO I AM NOT GOING TO SUPPORT THIS AT THIS TIME.
>> SIMPLE AS ONE. >> THANK YOU.
PUBLIC SAFETY IS MY NUMBER ONE PRIORITY.
I LAST TIME WHEN WE MET ABOUT THIS AT THE PUBLIC SAFETY
NEIGHBORHOOD SERVICES COMMITTEE I HEARD OVERWHELMING SUPPORT
FROM THE COMMUNITIES THAT WERE AFFECTED BY THESE RESTRICTED
ZONES AND THERE WAS OVERWHELMING SUPPORT.
I ALSO WANT TO POINT OUT THAT PUBLIC SAFETY IMPACTS AND DRUG
MARKETS IN IN NEIGHBORHOODS AND IN DISTRICTS FIVE AND SIX
ALSO AFFECT THE REST OF THE CITY BECAUSE WHEN WHEN THERE IS
AN ENVIRONMENT LIKE THAT WE LOSE BUSINESS, WE LOSE TOURISM.
PEOPLE DO NOT WANT OR FEEL SAFE COMING INTO THE CITY AND WE
NEED TO BE ABLE TO CREATE THE ENVIRONMENTS FOR FOR SUCCESS
FOR OUR COMMUNITIES AND THAT'S WHY I AM STRONGLY IN SUPPORT OF
THIS. IT'S NOT THE PERFECT SOLUTION
BUT IT'S A A WAY TO BRING IN MORE ENVIRONMENTAL FACTORS
TO HELP REDUCE DRUG MARKETS OUT IN THE OPEN.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR JAN THANK YOU.
PRESENT AMENDMENT I THINK WE HAVE DONE SOMETHING SIMILAR
HAVEN'T WE IN THE PAST IN TENDERLOIN LIKE RESTRICTING
THE HOURS. BUT AS A PILOT PROGRAM AS WELL
AND I'M JUST KIND OF CURIOUS THAT I APPRECIATE A
PRESENTATION FROM THE PUBLIC SAFETY COMMITTEE FROM AS A PD
INDICATING THE PHOTOS OF BEFORE AND AFTER COMPARING THE
PREVIOUS LIKE 2024 VERSUS 2025 TIME PERIOD.
BUT I DO ALSO SHARE THE CONCERN OF SUPERVISOR PHIL DURHAM
MENTIONING WHEN YOU WHEN YOU'RE SORT OF RESTRICTING ONE AREA
SOMETIMES YOU WHAT WE DO IS YOU END UP PUSHING THE FLOW OF THAT
POPULATION TO SOMEWHERE ELSE. I'M JUST KIND OF THROUGH THE
THROUGH THE CHAIR TWO PUBLIC SAFETY COMMITTEE MAYBE OR TWO
ANYONE CAN ANSWER THE QUESTION IS THEN HOW DO WE ADDRESS ONCE
YOU IMPLEMENT TO RESTRICT HOURS IN THIS AREA WHAT WHAT WHAT ARE
WE GOING TO DO WITH THE NEIGHBORING AREA?
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR THE QUESTION.
IF CHAIR DORSEY THE AUTHOR WOULD LIKE TO ANSWER THAT.
>> OKAY. SO THE THE THE FEEDBACK THAT WE
GOT FROM THE POLICE DEPARTMENT WAS THAT THERE WAS NOT AN
APPRECIABLE MIGRATION OF BAD BEHAVIOR TO ADJACENT
NEIGHBORHOODS INCLUDING THE NEIGHBORHOOD I REPRESENT THERE
WAS BAD BEHAVIOR THERE ALREADY. WHAT WAS INTERESTING IS, YOU
KNOW, IN THE PROCESS OF DOING OUTREACH TO THE BUSINESSES
AND TO THE NEIGHBORHOOD AND COMMUNITY YOU MAY RECALL
THE SAN FRANCISCO STANDARD ACTUALLY PUBLISHED A STUDY THAT
WAS DONE BY AN ITALIAN UNIVERSITY THAT FOUND THE SAME
THING. I THINK THAT THERE THERE WAS A
REDUCTION IN DRUG RELATED LAWLESSNESS WITHOUT A
MEASURABLE DISPLACEMENT TO ADJACENT NEIGHBORHOODS.
ULTIMATELY THIS WAS A STRATEGY I.E. ABOUT A TEMPORARY COOLING
OFF PERIOD BETWEEN THE HOURS OF MIDNIGHT AND 5 A.M. TO MAKE THE
NEIGHBORHOOD LESS INVITING TO DRUG RELATED LAWLESSNESS THAT
INCLUDES THINGS LIKE FENCING OPERATIONS AND OFTEN VIOLENCE
AND SORT OF CHAOTIC CONDITIONS THAT ARE REALLY WREAKING HAVOC
ON SOME OF THE RESIDENTIAL AREAS AROUND THERE.
SO THE I WAS CERTAINLY SATISFIED THAT THIS WAS BORNE
OUT IN A COUPLE OF DIFFERENT RESULTS.
SO IT'S 18 MONTHS WE'RE GOING TO BE WORKING WITH BUSINESS
COMMUNITIES AND I THINK THIS IS SOMETHING THAT'S WORTH VOTING
FOR. >> SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK
YOU. I JUST WANT TO FOLLOW UP ON
THAT STUDY. IT WAS THE LEAD AUTHOR WHO ALSO
ACKNOWLEDGED THAT THERE MAY BE DISPLACEMENT EFFECTS OF CRIME
TO SOMA AND THAT THIS WAS A TENTATIVE STUDY THEY NEEDED TO
DO MORE AND SO IT'S ALL ABOUT WHERE YOU'RE LOOKING AND ALSO
JUST TAKING THE AUTHOR'S WORD FOR IT THAT THERE'S MORE
RESEARCH TO BE DONE ABOUT THE ACTUAL IMPACTS OF THIS POLICY
INCLUDING DISPLACEMENT AND SO THAT IS THAT IS EXACTLY THE
STUDY I'M REFERRING TO WHEN WHEN STATING MY POSITION AROUND
THIS THIS LEGISLATION. >> ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK,
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 31 SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON NO
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NO SUPERVISOR FARMER MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI GENTLEMEN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I IN SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I THERE ARE EIGHT EYES
AND TWO NOS WITH SUPERVISORS WALTON AND FIELDER ARE VOTING
NO AND THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK
PLEASE CALL ITEM 30 TWO ITEM 32 RESOLUTION TO DETERMINE THAT
THE PERSON TO PERSON PREMISE TO PREMISE TRANSFER OF A TYPE 21
OFF SALE GENERAL BEER WINE AND DISTILLED SPIRITS LIQUOR
LICENSE TO A MALLS MARKET LOCATED AT 1416 HAIGHT STREET
WILL SERVE THE PUBLIC CONVENIENCE AND TO REQUEST THAT
THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF ALCOHOLIC BEVERAGE CONTROL
IMPOSE CONDITIONS ON THE ISSUANCE OF THE LICENSE, PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 32 SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN HI MANAGEMENT I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I AND SUPERVISOR SAUTER SADR I THERE ARE TEN EYES
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED AND LET'S
GO TO COMMITTEE REPORTS PLEASE CALL ITEMS 45 AND 46 TOGETHER
ITEMS 45 AND 46 ARE TWO ORDINANCES THAT WERE CONSIDERED
BY THE LAND USE AND TRANSPORTATION COMMITTEE AT
A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY FEBRUARY 2ND AND WERE FORWARDED
AS COMMITTEE REPORTS. ITEM 45 IS AN ORDINANCE TO
AMEND THE PLANNING CODE TO ADD A NEW APPENDIX P TO ARTICLE TEN
PRESERVATION OF HISTORICAL ARCHITECTURAL AND ESTHETIC
LANDMARKS TO CREATE THE CHULA ABBEY EARLY RESIDENTIAL
HISTORIC DISTRICT. LET'S TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME
HOUSE SAME CALL WITH A APOLOGIES MR. PRESIDENT.
THAT WAS JUST ITEM 45 OH, KEEP GOING.
I WILL FINISH WITH ITEM 46 ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PLANNING
CODE TO ADD A NEW APPENDIX Q TO ARTICLE TEN PRESERVATION OF
HISTORICAL ARCHITECTURAL AND ESTHETIC LANDMARKS TO
CREATE THE ALERT ALLEY EARLY RESIDENTIAL HISTORIC DISTRICT
AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION AND MAKE THE
APPROPRIATE FINDINGS FOR BOTH ITEMS AND LIKE LET'S TAKE THESE
ITEMS SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCES ARE PASSED ON FIRST READING AND LET'S GO TO ROLL
CALL SUPERVISOR WALTON, YOU'RE UP FIRST.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK COLLEAGUES, TODAY I AM
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION ON BEHALF OF THE YOUTH COMMISSION
TO DECLARE FEBRUARY AS TEEN DATING VIOLENCE AWARENESS
AND PREVENTION MONTH. THANK YOU TO THE YOUTH
COMMISSION FOR WORKING ON THIS IN PARTNERSHIP WITH BLACK WOMEN
REVOLT AND ASIAN WOMEN'S SHELTER ON THIS IMPORTANT
ISSUE, 1 IN 3 HIGH SCHOOLERS WILL EXPERIENCE DATING ABUSE
BEFORE HIGH SCHOOL GRADUATION. YOUNG PEOPLE ARE IMPACTED BY
ABUSIVE RELATIONSHIPS WHEN THEY ARE THREATENED WITH OR
SUBJECTED TO PHYSICAL VIOLENCE SEXUAL VIOLENCE, PSYCHOLOGICAL
AGGRESSION OR STALKING FROM A CURRENT OR FORMER INTIMATE
PARTNER DATING VIOLENCE CAN ALSO OCCUR DIGITALLY THROUGH
SOCIAL MEDIA AND OTHER ELECTRONIC COMMUNICATIONS
AND YOUNG PEOPLE EXPERIENCING VIOLENCE ARE MORE LIKELY TO BE
VULNERABLE TO LONG TERM BEHAVIORAL AND HEALTH
CONSEQUENCES INCLUDING MENTAL TRAUMA AND DRUG ABUSE WHICH
ALSO INCREASES THE RISK OF VIOLENCE IN ADULTHOOD
AND FUTURE RELATIONSHIPS. THEREFORE, IT IS CRITICAL TO
EDUCATE YOUNG PEOPLE ABOUT THE SIGNS OF DOMESTIC VIOLENCE TO
SET THEM UP FOR SUCCESS BY ALLOWING THEM TO RECOGNIZE FOR
THEMSELVES WHAT'S HEALTHY NONVIOLENT RELATIONSHIPS LOOK
LIKE. I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISORS
FIELDER CHAN MANDO MAN MAHMOOD WONG FOR YOUR EARLY CO-SPONSOR
OF THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WALTON SUPERVISOR
WANG I WAS SUBMIT OH THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN SUBMIT THANK
YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU MADAM CLERK COLLEAGUES TODAY
I'M HONORED TO INTRODUCE OUR RESOLUTION CELEBRATING 2026 AS
THE YEAR OF THE HORSE. >> THIS RESOLUTION IS VERY
MEANINGFUL TO OUR CITY AND TO MY DISTRICT.
CELEBRATION OF NOONA NEW YEAR IN SAN FRANCISCO HAS BECOME A
CULTURALLY SIGNIFICANT EVENT WHICH BEGINS WITH THE NEW MOON
ON THE FIRST DAY OF THE NEW YEAR AND ENDS ON THE FULL MOON
15 DAYS LATER TO NOON ON NEW YEAR.
IT'S SIGNIFICANT HOLIDAY FOR ASIAN FAMILIES TO GATHER
TOGETHER TO HONOR THEIR ANCESTORS, WELCOMING THE NEW
YEAR WITH HOPES, PROSPERITY AND GOOD HEALTH TO CELEBRATE
CULTURES AND TRADITIONS AS 2026 IS THE YEAR OF THE HORSE WHICH
PROMISES TO BRING ENERGY FREEDOM AND FORWARD MOMENTUM.
I WOULD LIKE TO THANK ALL MY COLLEAGUES FOR YOUR UNANIMOUS
CO-SPONSORS SHIP AND I WOULD ALSO ESPECIALLY LIKE TO THANKS
TO BOTH MYSELF CONNIE CHEN FOR SUPPORT AS MY CO SPONSOR.
THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN
SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUBMIT THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR FIELDER. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
>> COLLEAGUES TODAY I INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION TO
AFFIRM THE BOARD AND THE CITY'S COMMITMENT TO PROTECTING THE
FUTURE OF A CENTER FOR LATINO ARTS AND CULTURE AT 2868
MISSION STREET THE SITE OF THE CURRENT MISSION CULTURAL CENTER
FOR LATINO ARTS, ALSO KNOWN AS MTC L.A. FOR 49 YEARS THE
NONPROFIT ORGANIZATION KNOWN AS THE MISSION CULTURAL CENTER FOR
LATINO ARTS HAS BEEN PROVIDING NOT JUST PROGRAMING BUT
LIFELINES FOR THOUSANDS OF LATINOS FRANCISCANS WHO TAKE
PRIDE AND PURPOSE FROM VISUAL ARTS, DANCING AND PERFORMING
ARTS. CURRENTLY THAT ORGANIZATION'S
STABILITY AND FUTURE IS UNCERTAIN, CAUSING A GREAT DEAL
OF CONCERN AND UPSET IN THE MISSION COMMUNITY.
I DON'T THINK I CAN OVERSTATE THE IMPORTANCE OF THE
HISTORICAL LEGACY OF THIS BUILDING THIS BUILDING HAS BEEN
THE SITE WHERE MANY SUCCESSFUL LATINO POETS PRINTMAKERS
DANCERS, MUSICIANS, PAINTERS, AUTHORS, SCULPTORS, MURALISTS
AND MORE HAVE INCUBATED THEIR CRAFT WHERE ICONIC AND WORLD
RENOWNED ANNUAL CELEBRATIONS IN SAN FRANCISCO HAVE TAKEN
PLACE INCLUDING LATIN HERITAGE COMMUNITY CELEBRATION DIA DE
LOS MUERTOS DAY OF THE DEAD SOLO MU HEAD IS AN ANNUAL ART
EXHIBIT EXHIBITION AND OF COURSE CARNIVAL IN THE SPRING
ALONG WITH DAILY PROGRAMING AND EXPOSITIONS FEATURING LOCAL
LEGENDS AND LATINO ARTISTS FROM THE COMMUNITY.
>> IT WAS DECLARED A SAN FRANCISCO LANDMARK BUILDING
IN 2022 BY THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND PER CITY
CHARTER THE SAN FRANCISCO ARTS COMMISSION.
THE OWNER OF THE BUILDING IS MANDATED TO USE IT FOR
COMMUNITY ARTS AND CULTURE. IT IS A CENTRAL AND VERY
PROMINENT FEATURE OF THE MISSION AND 24TH STREET
CORRIDOR AND A GUIDE IN THE QUATRO CULTURAL DISTRICT OF
DISTRICT NINE. THIS RESOLUTION AFFIRMS THE
COMMITMENT BY THE CITY TO ENSURE THAT THIS BUILDING AT
2868 MISSION NOW AFTER THE PLANNED EARTHQUAKE RETROFIT
AND INTO THE FUTURE REMAINS A HUB FOR LATINO ARTS AND CULTURE
DESPITE THE UNCERTAINTIES OF THE STATUS OF ANY SINGLE
NONPROFIT PROGRAMING GRANTS CAN AND SHOULD BE AVAILABLE TO A
SUITABLE NONPROFIT THAT MEETS THE CRITERIA TO RUN SUCH A
CENTER. ADDITIONALLY, WE WANT TO ENSURE
THAT THE HISTORICAL ARCHIVES AND COMMUNITY ARTS ASSETS
IN THE BUILDING SHOULD BE PRESERVED AND PROTECTED BY
AND FOR THE COMMUNITY. >> THE ARTS IN GENERAL AND OUR
CITY ARE CURRENTLY AT RISK WITH THE COLLAPSE OF CALIFORNIA
COLLEGE OF THE ARTS, MEXICAN MUSEUM AND OTHER CENTERS FACING
THREATS TO THEIR INTEGRITY, THE REVITALIZATION OF SAN FRANCISCO
CANNOT HAPPEN WITHOUT THE IMPORTANT ROLE OF COMMUNITY
ARTS AND CULTURE AND SPECIFICALLY LATINO ARTS
AND CULTURE WHICH MUST NOT ONLY BE CULTIVATED BUT PROTECTED
AND CONSIDERED AS IMPORTANT AS ANY OTHER PLACEMAKING STRATEGY
. I WANT TO THANK MY CO SPONSORS
SUPERVISORS MELGAR CHAN AND WALTON AS WELL.
>> TODAY I'M INTRODUCING A REVENUE MEASURE TO BE PUT ON
OUR NOVEMBER BALLOT TO ESTABLISH A PUBLIC BANK FOR SAN
FRANCISCO. SAN FRANCISCO WAS ONCE A PLACE
WHERE PEOPLE WITH ALMOST NOTHING COULD COME MAKE THEIR
DREAMS REAL. NOW SAN FRANCISCO IS
INCREASINGLY BECOMING A PLACE WHERE DREAMS REQUIRE VAST
CAPITAL OR PROXIMITY TO THOSE WHO HAVE IT.
FOR THOSE WITHOUT EITHER WALL STREET BANKS OFFER CAPITAL
IN EXCHANGE FOR PROFIT MAXIMIZING INTEREST RATES IF
ANY CAPITAL AT ALL. THIS HAS CULMINATED IN A
PERNICIOUS CYCLE OF EXCLUSION IN THE ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL
FABRIC OF OUR CITY OF BLACK AND BROWN PEOPLE IMMIGRANTS,
LGBTQ PEOPLE, ARTISTS AND WORKING CLASS PEOPLE OF ALL
BACKGROUNDS WHO HAVE ALL MADE SAN FRANCISCO WHAT IT IS TODAY.
>> RENTS ARE RISING FASTER THAN ANYWHERE ELSE IN THE NATION.
OUR CITY HAS A GOAL OF BUILDING 46,000 AFFORDABLE HOMES BY 2031
WITH NO FINANCING PLANS TO GET THERE.
SMALL BUSINESSES WE KNOW AND LOVE ARE DYING ALONG WITH
THE JOBS THAT THEY BRING. THAT IS WHY TODAY I'M
INTRODUCING THIS REVENUE MEASURE TO BE PUT ON OUR
NOVEMBER BALLOT TO TAX SOME OF THE WEALTHIEST FINANCIAL
CORPORATION BONDS IN THE CITY OVER A PERIOD OF EIGHT YEARS TO
ESTABLISH A PUBLIC BANK. THIS BANK WILL PUT SUSTAINABLE
CAPITAL INTO THE HANDS OF WORKING PEOPLE AND THE SECTORS
THAT DIRECTLY SUPPORT OUR PLACE IN THIS CITY.
TRULY AFFORDABLE HOUSING, SMALL BUSINESSES AND GREEN PROJECTS.
IT WILL ACHIEVE THIS BY PARTNERING WITH LOCAL CREDIT
UNIONS AND OTHER FINANCIAL INSTITUTIONS THAT SHARE OUR
GOAL OF MAXIMIZING PUBLIC GOOD RATHER THAN MAXIMIZING PROFITS
IN THE FORM OF NO TO LOW COST LOANS.
ANY EARNINGS REALIZED FROM THE PUBLIC BANK WILL BE REINVESTED
INTO THE BANK AND THE PUBLIC GOOD.
IT PROMOTES THE SYNERGISTIC ECOSYSTEM WILL HELP PROVIDE
CONTROL OVER OUR LOCAL ECONOMY AND PROMOTE DIVERSITY IN A
LOCAL AND GLOBAL ECONOMY THAT LEAVES OUR MOST IMPORTANT
AND LEAST PRIORITIZED SECTORS BEHIND.
I LOOK FORWARD TO TALKING WITH YOU MORE ON HOW WE CAN STAND UP
THIS PUBLIC BANK FOR THE PUBLIC GOOD OF SAN FRANCISCO AND I
WANT TO THANK SCOTT REBER MATSU BARRA IN THE CITY ATTORNEY'S
OFFICE, COMPTROLLER GREG WAGNER AND AMANDA KAHN FOR YOU AND THE
TREASURER AND TAX COLLECTORS OFFICE FOR THEIR WORK ON THIS
ORDINANCE. THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUPERVISOR
MY WOULD SUBMIT THANK YOU SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN THANK YOU
MADAM CLERK I GOT A A RESOLUTION AND IN MEMORIAM
AND SOME OTHER ITEMS WILL SUBMIT.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION TO ADD
THE COMMEMORATIVE STREET NAME ED DECKER WAY TO THE SIGNAGE
FOR THE BLOCK OF VENICE AVENUE BETWEEN OAK STREET AND HICKORY
ALLEY. ED DECKER IS THE FOUNDER
AND ARTISTIC DIRECTOR OF THE NEW CONSERVATORY THEATER CENTER
AND HAS LED THE ORGANIZATION FOR 45 YEARS.
DISTINGUISHING HIM AS A TRAILBLAZER IN THE WORLD OF
LGBTQ PLUS THEATER AND PROGRESSIVE THEATER
EDUCATION DURING HIS TENURE AT BUILT THE THEATER WHICH IS
LOCATED AT THE CORNER OF VENICE AND OAK INTO ONE OF SAN
FRANCISCO'S MOST PRIZED CULTURAL INSTITUTIONS.
UNDER HIS DIRECTION, THE THEATER HAS PRODUCED MORE THAN
50 WORLD PREMIERES BY ESTABLISHED AND EMERGING
PLAYWRIGHTS EMPLOYED THOUSANDS OF BAY AREA THEATER
PROFESSIONALS AND TEACHING ARTISTS AND LAUNCHED THE
CAREERS OF NATIONALLY RECOGNIZED THEATER ARTISTS.
AS A THEATER LEADER, ACTIVIST AND ARTS EDUCATOR SINCE 1974,
ED DECKER HAS WORKED WITH A BROAD SWATH OF ARTISTS,
POLITICAL LEADERS, AUDIENCES, COMMUNITY ORGANIZERS, LOCAL
BUSINESSES AND VOLUNTEERS. IN 1986, IN RESPONSE TO THE
AIDS EPIDEMIC SWEEPING THE NATION, ED CREATED THE LANDMARK
YOUTH AWARE TOURING EDUCATIONAL THEATER PROGRAM TO EDUCATE
AND RAISE AWARENESS AMONG YOUNG AUDIENCES ABOUT THE IMPACT OF
HIV AIDS AN EFFORT THAT REACHED MORE THAN 800,000 STUDENTS
IN THE BAY AREA AND NORTHERN CALIFORNIA.
HE ALSO SET UP AN AFTER SCHOOL DRAMA PROGRAM THAT OFFERED
SCHOLARSHIPS AND LOW COST FEES ENSURING THAT ANY CHILD COULD
PARTICIPATE REGARDLESS OF ABILITY TO PAY.
>> ED'S LEADERSHIP HAS WON HIM NUMEROUS AWARDS, INCLUDING
KQED'S LOCAL HERO AWARD STOP AIDS PROJECT'S CHUCK FRITCHEY
AWARD AND ENDEAVOR FOUNDATION AWARD AND TO SAN FRANCISCO'S
CHAMBER OF COMMERCE ARTS EXCELLENCE AWARDS.
HE'S ALSO A NATIONALLY RECOGNIZED PLAYWRIGHT.
ON MAY 20TH ON MAY 19TH, 2026, THE NEW CONSERVATORY THEATER
WILL CELEBRATE ITS 45TH BIRTHDAY.
ED WILL BE STEPPING DOWN AS THE ARTISTIC DIRECTOR FOR THE
THEATER THAT MONTH ENDING A REMARKABLE TENURE DISTINGUISHED
BY EXTRAORDINARY LEADERSHIP AND DEDICATION TO HIS CRAFT.
THE SIGN IS A WAY TO HONOR ED DECKER FOR HIS INCOMPARABLE
ACHIEVEMENTS ON BEHALF OF THE ARTS AND ON HIS RETIREMENT.
AND I WANT TO THANK BARBARA HODGDON FOR THE BARBARA HAYDEN,
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE NEW CONSERVATORY THEATER CENTER FOR
CHAMPIONING THIS COMMEMORATIVE STREET RENAMING.
I ALSO WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR DORSEY FOR HIS EARLY
CO-SPONSORSHIP AND COLLABORATION ON THE
PROJECT AS WELL AS MY LEGISLATIVE AIDE GRACE HUANG
FOR HER WORK. SECONDLY, TODAY I'M ASKING THAT
WE PAUSE TO HONOR THE LIFE AND LEGACY OF MICHAEL B
FREEMAN, A COLLEAGUE WHOSE WORK HELPED SHAPE HOW SAN
FRANCISCANS SEE AND UNDERSTAND THEIR GOVERNMENT.
FOR MORE THAN 20 YEARS MICHAEL SERVED THE CITY AND COUNTY OF
SAN FRANCISCO WITH COMMITMENT AND QUIET EXCELLENCE.
HE WAS A FOUNDATIONAL FORCE IN THE CREATION AND GROWTH OF
S.F. GOV TV HELPING GUIDE THE CHANNEL FROM ITS EARLIEST
BEGINNINGS INTO ONE OF THE MOST RESPECTED LOCAL GOVERNMENT
TELEVISION OPERATIONS IN THE COUNTRY THROUGH PERIODS OF
TRANSITION AND GROWTH, MICHAEL PROVIDED STEADY LEADERSHIP
OVERSEEING MAJOR ADVANCES IN PRODUCTION FACILITIES
AND TECHNOLOGY AND HELPING MODERNIZE CITY HALL'S BROADCAST
OPERATIONS FOR A NEW DIGITAL ERA.
>> MICHAEL WAS ALSO A GIFTED CREATIVE PRODUCER VIDEOGRAPHER
,EDITOR AND MUSICIAN. THROUGH PROGRAMS LIKE DISTRICT
S.F. MEET YOUR DISTRICT SUPERVISOR LEGISLATIVE UPDATES
AND ELECTION COVERAGE HE BROUGHT CLARITY, CONTEXT
AND HUMANITY TO LOCAL GOVERNMENT MAKING CIVIC LIFE
MORE ACCESSIBLE TO RESIDENTS ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO.
JUST AS IMPORTANT AS HIS TECHNICAL AND CREATIVE
CONTRIBUTIONS WAS THE ROLE HE PLAYED AS A MENTOR AND TRUSTED
COLLEAGUE. MICHAEL WAS GENEROUS WITH HIS
KNOWLEDGE, THOUGHTFUL IN HIS APPROACH AND DEEPLY RESPECTED
BY THOSE WHO HAD THE PRIVILEGE OF WORKING ALONGSIDE HIM.
MICHAEL RETIRED IN JUNE 2015 AND SPENT THE LAST TEN YEARS
ENJOYING LIFE WITH HIS WIFE SUSAN KUCZYNSKI AS HIS SUDDEN
PASSING IS A PROFOUND LOST ALL WHO KNEW HIM AND THE
INSTITUTION HE HELPED BUILD. MICHAEL'S WORK REMINDS US THAT
PUBLIC SERVICE DOESN'T ALWAYS HAPPEN AT A PODIUM OR IN THIS
CHAMBER. IT ALSO HAPPENS BEHIND THE
SCENES THROUGH DEDICATION, CRAFTSMANSHIP AND A BELIEF
IN THE VALUE OF PUBLIC ACCESS AND TRANSPARENCY.
ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO, WE EXTEND OUR DEEPEST CONDOLENCES
TO SUSAN, TO MICHAEL'S FAMILY AND TO HIS MANY COLLEAGUES
AND FRIENDS. HIS LEGACY WILL CONTINUE TO
LIVE ON THROUGH S.F. TV AND THROUGH THE MANY PEOPLE HE
INSPIRED ALONG THE WAY AND THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU, MR.
PRESIDENT. >> AND WE WILL SEND THE
IN MEMORIAM ON BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD.
>> THAT WOULD BE GREAT. THANK YOU, MR. JACKSON.
>> LET'S DO THAT. NEXT UP, SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. I THANK YOU COLLEAGUES.
I JUST WANT TO ECHO AND SUPPORT SUPERVISOR FIELDER IN THE
SOLUTIONS SHE HAS INTRODUCED TO DECLARE THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS COMMITMENT TO PROTECTING AND PRESERVING THE
LONG TERM FUTURE OF THE CENTER FOR ARTS AND CULTURE IN THE
MISSION AT 2868 MISSION STREET. AND I WANT TO THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR FOR YOUR WORK AND YOUR LEADERSHIP AND THAT OF
YOUR STAFF. IT HAS BEEN REALLY AMAZING.
I HAVE BEEN SOUNDING THE ALARM ABOUT THE SITUATION THERE FOR
SEVERAL YEARS AND YOU HAVE TAKEN IT SERIOUSLY AS DID YOUR
PREDECESSOR SUPERVISOR RONEN. LIKE MANY OF YOU WHO SPENT TIME
IN CHINATOWN OR FILLMORE OR BAYVIEW YOU KNOW, FOR LATINOS
THE MISSION IS THE CENTER OF CULTURE AND COMMUNITY IN THIS
BUILDING IN PARTICULAR CONNECTS US TO OUR CULTURE AND COMMUNITY
. I DANCE AFRO-LATINO ARTS
AND DANCE IS A VERY IMPORTANT PART OF MY LIFE IN MY FAMILY'S
LIFE. I'VE DANCED IN CARNAVAL EVERY
YEAR SINCE I WAS 18 YEARS OLD THROUGH THREE PREGNANCIES
AND MY GIRLS DANCE NOW AND THEY DANCE WITH ME AND IT'S A REALLY
IMPORTANT PART OF HOW WE CONNECT TO OUR COMMUNITY
AND OUR CULTURE AND IT HAPPENS AT THAT BUILDING.
I JUST HAVE TO ADD THAT YOU KNOW THE STRUGGLES THAT THE
COMMUNITY HAS HAD IN THAT BUILDING AND IN WITH FUNDING
WITH THE CITY AND ITS RELATIONSHIP WITH THE CITY
WOULD NEVER HAVE HAPPENED IF THIS HAD BEEN THE BALLET OR THE
OPERA. I THINK IT IS A DIRECT RESULT
OF AN UNDERSERVED COMMUNITY THAT DOESN'T HAVE AS MANY
RESOURCES BUT DESPERATELY NEEDS THAT CONNECTION TO COMMUNITY,
TO CULTURE AND THE ARTS. AND SO WE'VE GOT TO DO BETTER
AS THE CITY TO PRESERVING THE CULTURAL COMMUNITIES OF THE
RICH DIVERSITY THAT IS THE FABRIC OF OUR PEOPLE EVERYWHERE
IN THE CITY. AND WE HAVE TO DO BETTER WITH
HOW WE HAVE THESE RELATIONSHIPS THE RESPECT IN THE DIGNITY THAT
WE OFFER TO THESE COMMUNITIES. AND SO THANK YOU COLLEAGUES FOR
TAKING IT SERIOUSLY. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FOR INTRODUCING THIS RESOLUTION AND THE REST I SUBMIT THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR MELGAR. >> SUPERVISOR SUTTER COLLEAGUES
TODAY I AM SUBMITTING A LETTER OF INQUIRY REQUESTING
INFORMATION ON THE RECRUITMENT OF BILINGUAL PUBLIC FACING CITY
EMPLOYEES RESIDENTS IN OUR DISTRICT'S DIVERSE
NEIGHBORHOODS SHOULD ENCOUNTER AS FEW OBSTACLES AS POSSIBLE
WHEN INTERACTING WITH CITY EMPLOYEES AND ACCESSING CITY
SERVICES. BUT TOO OFTEN I'VE HEARD FROM
CONSTITUENTS WHO FOUND LANGUAGE BARRIERS AT THE MOMENTS THAT
THEY NEEDED SUPPORT FROM THE CITY MOST BE IT CALLING A911
DISPATCH OPERATOR ASKING FOR DIRECTIONS FROM A TRANSIT
OPERATOR ABOARD MUNI OR ENGAGING WITH FIRE POLICE
AND EMT. AND AS FEDERAL IMMIGRATION
ENFORCEMENT ESCALATE THE NEED FOR LANGUAGE ACCESS IN CRISIS,
HIGH TENSION SITUATIONS IS GREATER THAN EVER.
IN FACT, THE OFFICE OF CIVIC ENGAGEMENT AND IMMIGRATION
AFFAIRS 2026 REPORT STATES THAT THERE HAS BEEN AN 11% YEAR OVER
YEAR INCREASE AND A 36% INCREASE OVER THE FIVE YEAR
AVERAGE FOR LIMITED ENGLISH PROFICIENCY CLIENT
INTERACTIONS. >> MOST CRITICALLY FOR THE
DISTRICT I REPRESENT CLIENT ENGAGEMENTS IN CANTONESE
SURPASS 500,000 INSTANCES IN FISCAL YEAR 2425.
THIS AMOUNTS TO A 42% INCREASE COMPARED TO THE PREVIOUS FISCAL
YEAR AND A 41% INCREASE FROM THE FIVE YEAR AVERAGE.
>> INVESTING IN BILINGUAL CITY EMPLOYEES IS THE SINGLE BEST
WAY THAT WE CAN BOLSTER OUR LANGUAGE CAPACITY AND SUPPORT.
WE MUST DO MORE TO RECRUIT, RETAIN AND SUPPORT FRONT LINE
PUBLIC FACING CITY EMPLOYEES IN KEY ROLES ACROSS DEPARTMENTS
LIKE S.F. PD FIRE, THE DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY
MANAGEMENT, DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH 311 AND S.F. MTA
. >> THE DEPARTMENT OF HUMAN
RESOURCES DATA SHOWS THAT CERTIFIED BILINGUAL EMPLOYEE
POSITIONS HAVE A 17% VACANCY RATE HIGHER THAN A CITYWIDE
AVERAGE OF 12%. >> THIS HIGHER VACANCY RATE
SUGGESTS THAT OUR CURRENT APPROACH IS NOT ADEQUATE.
>> SO MY LETTER OF INQUIRY ASKS FOR SPECIFIC STRATEGIES,
BUDGETS AND PLANS FOR KEY DEPARTMENTS IN THEIR WORK TO
RECRUIT MORE BILINGUAL EMPLOYEES.
WE SHOULD EXAMINE HOW OUR BILINGUAL PAY BONUSES COMPARE
TO OTHER CITIES AND WE SHOULD ENSURE THAT CERTIFICATION EXAMS
CONDUCTED BY DEPARTMENT OF HUMAN RESOURCES MEET THE
REALITY OF LANGUAGE USED ON THE GROUND.
OUR CITY HAS SHOWN THAT IT CAN PRODUCE RESULTS WHEN IT GETS
SERIOUS ABOUT IMPROVING RECRUITMENT EFFORTS.
LAST YEAR'S MAYORAL DIRECTIVE REBUILDING THE RANKS HAS
ALREADY IMPROVED APPLICATIONS TO THE POLICE ACADEMY BY SOME
50% AND WITH A SIMILAR LEVEL OF FOCUS AND INTENT HERE I KNOW WE
CAN DO THE SAME TO FILL CRITICAL FRONTLINE ROLES.
SO I LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING WITH DEPARTMENTS AND MY
COLLEAGUES TO ENSURE THAT WE DO JUST THAT AND THE REST OF IT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR FOR CHARTER.
MR. PRESIDENT, SEEING NO FURTHER NAMES ON THE ROSTER
THAT INCLUDES THE INTRODUCTION OF NEW BUSINESS ALL AND LET'S
GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT. >> ALL RIGHT.
AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT IF YOU LINE
UP ON YOUR RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER.
YOU MAY SPEAK TO ITEMS 49 THROUGH 54.
THOSE ARE ON ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE.
YOU MAY ALSO SPEAK TO GENERAL MATTERS NOT ON THE PUBLISHED
AGENDA BUT MUST BE WITHIN THE BOARD'S SUBJECT MATTER
JURISDICTION. ALL OTHER AGENDA CONTENT WILL
HAVE ALREADY BEEN REPORTED OUT BY A COMMITTEE WHERE PUBLIC
COMMENT HAS OCCURRED BY PRIOR ARRANGEMENT.
OUR OFFICE IS IN RECEIPT OF A REQUEST FOR LANGUAGE
ACCOMMODATION FOR ITEM 51 AND WE WILL HAVE SPANISH
INTERPRETATION PROVIDED. COMMENT DURING GENERAL PUBLIC
COMMENT. LET'S HEAR FROM OUR FIRST
SPEAKER PLEASE WELCOME. WE'RE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO
MINUTES. >> THANK YOU.
GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS LANCE TOMA.
I'M THE CEO OF SAN FRANCISCO COMMUNITY HEALTH CENTER.
WE APPLAUD THE SPONSORS OF THE RESOLUTION THAT REAFFIRMS SAN
FRANCISCO'S COMMITMENT TO GENDER AFFIRMING CARE.
>> THE SPONSORS SUPERVISORS CHAN MENDELSON FIELDER, DORSEY
CHAN WALTON MAHMOOD AND MELGAR. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
AND WE URGE PASSAGE OF THIS RESOLUTION ON SAN FRANCISCO
COUNTY HEALTH CENTER WAS TARGETED WITHIN A FEW DAYS OF
THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION TAKING OFFICE WITH OUR TRANS FOCUSED
CDC FUNDING TERMINATED OUTRIGHT BECAUSE OF THE EXECUTIVE ORDER
ON GENDER IDEOLOGY. WE HAD NO OTHER CHOICE BUT TO
FIGHT BACK AND SUED THE ADMINISTRATION ALONG WITH EIGHT
OTHER LGBTQ ORGANIZATIONS ACROSS THE COUNTRY WITH LAMBDA
LEGAL REPRESENTING US ALONGSIDE THE OUR HEALTH CENTERS LONG
STANDING GENDER AFFIRMING CARE THAT WE PROVIDE.
WE CURRENTLY OPERATE A STAND ALONE FACILITY RUN BY AND FOR
THE TRANS COMMUNITY. TRANS THRIVE IS A SAFE HAVEN, A
REFUGE AND A COMMUNITY INSPIRED SPACE FOR THE TRANS COMMUNITY
TO ACCESS RESOURCES AND SERVICES AND TO CONTINUE TO
CONTRIBUTE TO THE FABRIC OF OUR COMMUNITY.
>> WE ALSO LEAD THE HEALTH ACCESS POINT FOR THE TRANS
COMMUNITY. WE LEAD HIV CARE AND TREATMENT
SERVICES FOR THE COMMUNITY AND FOR THE PAST TWO YEARS
WE'VE BEEN OPERATING THE FIRST OF ITS KIND IN THE COUNTRY
EMERGENCY SHELTER FOR TRANS AND GENDER NONCONFORMING
INDIVIDUALS IN OUR CITY. THE TEAM AND BUTON NAVIGATION
CENTER 84 BEDS THAT ARE FILLED EVERY SINGLE NIGHT WE AT SAN
FRANCISCO COMMUNITY HEALTH CENTER ARE ENGAGED IN EFFORTS
TO ENSURE THAT THE RIGHTS AND PROTECTIONS FOR UNFETTERED
ACCESS TO COMPREHENSIVE HEALTH CARE FOR TRANS INDIVIDUALS ARE
PROTECTED AND UPHELD. >> WE LOOK FORWARD TO YOU FOR
YOUR EXPLICIT COMMITMENT TO TRANS COMMUNITIES, TO JUSTICE
AND TO AFFIRMING YOUR STANCE THAT PREMATURELY COMPLYING
AND ANTICIPATORY OBEDIENCE TO THE RULES AND LAWS THAT TO NOT
APPLY TO US IN CALIFORNIA WILL NOT BE TOLERATED HERE IN OUR
CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
BEFORE THE NEXT SPEAKER SPEAKS I APPRECIATE YOUR ENTHUSIASM
BUT THE BOARD HAS A RULE THAT THERE'S NO AUDIBLE SOUNDS OF
APPROVAL OR AGAINST SOMETHING. BUT IF YOU DO WANT TO SEND US A
SIGN JUST SIGNAL AS SUCH. THANK YOU FOR YOUR PATIENCE.
WELCOME. >> THANK YOU.
GOOD EVENING, SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS DR. TATIANA MOULTON.
SANTIAGO. I'M THE CHIEF STRATEGY
AND WORKFORCE OFFICER IN SAN FRANCISCO.
COMMUNITY HEALTH CENTER AND THE CO-CHAIR OF THE NATIONAL
TRANSGENDER HEALTH CARE ADVISORY GROUP.
OUR HEALTH CENTER SERVES 1871 TRANSGENDER CLIENTS INCLUDING
65% OF ALL TRANSGENDER WOMEN IN SAN FRANCISCO.
WHEN THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT TERMINATED OUR CDC FUNDING AS
MY COLLEAGUE SAID BECAUSE WE SERVE TRANS PEOPLE SPECIFICALLY
WE DIDN'T RETREAT. WE FOUGHT BACK AND WE SUED THE
ADMINISTRATION. WE NEVER STOPPED SERVING OUR
COMMUNITY FOR A SINGLE DAY. THAT IS THE STANDARD EVERY
PROVIDER IN THIS CITY SHOULD BE HELD TO AND THAT IS WHY THIS
RESOLUTION MATTERS. RIGHT NOW HEALTH CARE PROVIDERS
IN SAN FRANCISCO ARE PREEMPTIVELY STOPPING GENDER
AFFIRMING CARE FOR YOUTH BEFORE ANY FINAL FEDERAL RULE EXISTS.
WHILE CALIFORNIA LAW STEALS MANDATES ACCESS AND WHILE OUR
ATTORNEY GENERAL STANDS READY TO BLOCK THESE PROPOSED RULES
IN COURT, THAT IS NOT LEGAL CAUTION THAT IS ABANDONMENT
AND OUR YOUNG PEOPLE ARE PAYING FOR IT WITH THEIR LIVES.
THE DATA IS UNAMBIGUOUS. YOUTH RECEIVING GENDER
AFFIRMING CARE HAVE 73% LOWER ODDS OF SUICIDAL THOUGHTS.
THE SUICIDALITY IN STATES THAT HAVE ENACTED BANS SUICIDE
ATTEMPTS AMONG TRANS YOUTH INCREASED 72% IN THE FIRST YEAR
ALONE. EVERY MAJOR MEDICAL ASSOCIATION
IN THIS COUNTRY SUPPORTS THIS QUOTE THIS CARE AS MEDICALLY
NECESSARY AND LIFESAVING. THAT IS NOT A DEBATE.
THAT IS NOT A DEBATE THAT IS A SETTLED SCIENCE.
SAN FRANCISCO HAS ALWAYS LIVED FROM THE AIDS CRISIS TO
MARRIAGE EQUALITY TO SANCTUARY PROTECTIONS.
THIS CITY HAS NEVER WAITED FOR PERMISSION TO DO WHAT IS RIGHT.
25 STATES HAVE BANNED THIS CARE.
40% OF TRANS YOUTH IN AMERICA LIVE UNDER THESE RESTRICTIONS.
THEY ARE LOOKING TO CITIES LIKE OURS AND ASKING DOES ANYONE
STILL BELIEVE WE DESERVE TO LIVE?
THIS RESOLUTION ANSWERS YES ON AN UNEQUIVOCALLY YES.
I URGE YOU TO PASS IT UNANIMOUSLY.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS CAITLIN FOWLER. I SERVE AS THE COMMUNITY
RELATIONS MANAGER AT SAN FRANCISCO COMMUNITY HEALTH
CENTER. I URGE YOU TO CONSIDER THIS
CRUCIAL IMPORTANCE OF MAINTAINING AND ENHANCING
GENDER AFFIRMING CARE AND RESOURCES WITH OUR
COMMUNITY AT SAN FRANCISCO COMMUNITY HEALTH CENTER.
WE HAVE CONSISTENTLY CONSISTENTLY ANSWERED CALLS
DURING EVERY HEALTH CRISIS WHETHER IT COMES FROM THE
DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH OR WHETHER IT COMES FROM A DIVERSE
COMMUNITY THAT WE SERVE. SAN FRANCISCO HAS SET A
COMMENDABLE STANDARD AND AFFIRMING IDENTITIES OF
WOMEN OF TRANS EXPERIENCE BOTH YOUNG AND OLD.
OUR WORK AT SAN FRANCISCO COMMUNITY HEALTH CENTER GOES
BEYOND JUST FULFILLING THE NEED WE PROVIDE SPACE TO RESTORE
DIGNITY, HOPE, CONFIDENCE IN INDIVIDUALS WHO FACE
SYSTEMATIC BARRIERS. WE ALSO IN WE OFTEN CONSIDER
GENDER AFFIRMING CARE A SAFE HAVEN FOR MANY OF OUR YOUTH.
GENDER AFFIRMING SERVICES SERVE AS MERELY AS NOT JUST A MEDICAL
NECESSITY BUT A WAY OF LIFE. >> AS WE MOVE FORWARD IT IS
IMPERATIVE THAT WE CONTINUE TO INVEST AND PROTECT THESE
ESSENTIAL STRUCTURE. THE IMPORTANCE OF GENDER
AFFIRMING CARE IS PROFOUND AND SHAPE THE FUTURE OF OUR
COMMUNITY. >> LET US PRIORITIZE.
LET'S PRIORITIZE AND CONTINUE TO ADVOCATE FOR THE RESOURCE
THIS THAT SUPPORT OUR TRANS AND NON-BINARY INDIVIDUALS
ENSURING THEM TO ACCESS CARE THEY DESERVE.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR ATTENTION TO THIS.
THANK YOU FOR THIS YOUR ATTENTION TO THIS MATTER
AND LET'S CONTINUE TO MAKE A BETTER AND HEALTHIER SAN
FRANCISCO. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME NICK.
SPEAKER GOOD AFTERNOON BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
SUPER BOWL WEEK. >> I LOVE FOOTBALL AS MUCH AS
THE NEXT GUY BUT I GOT TO SAY, YOU KNOW TIRED OF ALL THE
GAMES. ONCE AGAIN IN TYPICAL SAN
FRANCISCO FASHION FOR A MAJOR EVENT WE HAVE SHEPHERDED HORDES
OF FIN ALL ADDICTS AND HOMELESSNESS INTO THE
SURROUNDING NEIGHBORHOODS. DOWNTOWN IS SPARKLING CLEAN
ONCE AGAIN BUT SIMILAR TO THAT OF WHEN PRESIDENT XI VISITED A
FEW YEARS AGO DURING THE ASIA PACIFIC ECONOMIC COOPERATION
CONFERENCE. IT'S NICE.
SOME OF THE SUPERVISORS HERE TODAY HAVE INTENTIONS OF
CRACKING DOWN ON THE CRIME AND THE DRUG TRADE AND ALL THAT
JAZZ. UNFORTUNATELY THE HONDURAS
VIGNALE DEALERS WHO ARE OPERATING IN OUR COMMUNITY WHO
HAVE TAKEN ADVANTAGE AND EXPLOITED OUR SANCTUARY
CITY. I LOVE IMMIGRANTS AS MUCH AS
ANYBODY ELSE. I BELIEVE THERE'S SOME OF THE
BEST PEOPLE IN THE WORLD. BUT IF YOU'RE HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO TO SELL FENTANYL YOU SHOULD BE DEPORTED.
>> AND THESE DRUG DEALERS ARE OPERATING ON ELECTRIC SCOOTERS.
THEY'RE CIRCLING AROUND. SO THIS WHOLE HIDE AND GO SEEK
WHACK A MOLE GAME YOU GUYS GOT GOING ON IT'S IT'S NOT
SUSTAINABLE SAD WE HAVE TO CLOSE DOWN OUR BUSINESSES
EARLIER THAN THEY SHOULD BE OPEN ALL NIGHT IF ANYTHING
RIGHT. >> YOU KNOW FOR NOT SHOWING UP
ON PLAYGROUNDS IN SCHOOLS 5000 PEOPLE HAVE DIED FROM FENNEL
IN SAN FRANCISCO BETWEEN THE YEARS 2019 AND 2026.
THIS IS A FEDERAL GENOCIDE, A HUMANITARIAN CRISIS.
PHENOL COMES FROM CHINA ACROSS SOUTHERN BORDER THROUGH THE
PORT OF OAKLAND AND YOU KNOW I JUST A SOUND LIKE A BROKEN
RECORD AND I THINK YOU KNOW, I'VE HEARD YOU GUYS PROMISE
YEAR AFTER YEAR YOU'RE GOING TO CRACK DOWN OR DO SOMETHING
ABOUT IT. SEEMS LIKE THE ONLY TIME OUR
CITY GETS CLEANED UP IS WHEN THERE'S A MAJOR EVENTS.
IT'S REALLY SAD BECAUSE RESIDENTS WE'VE BEEN BEGGING
DAYS UPON MONTHS UPON YEARS ON END TO PLEASE DO SOMETHING
ABOUT THE HUMANITARIAN CRISIS IN OUR COMMUNITY.
IT'S REALLY INTERESTING TO SEE YOU GUYS WHAT YOU WILL DO, WHAT
YOU WILL ACCOMPLISH WHEN YOU WANT TO.
>> BUT IF IT'S THE SUPER BOWL, IT'S REGULAR SCHEDULE.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME.
OUR NEXT SPEAKER OH GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS SIMEON QUASI. I'M A REGISTERED NURSE WORKING
IN PSYCHIATRIC AND MENTAL HEALTH CARE HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> I'D LIKE TO SPEAK BRIEFLY
ABOUT WHAT HAPPENS DOWNSTREAM WHEN TRANSGENDER YOUTH LOSE
ACCESS TO APPROPRIATE HEALTH CARE AND MENTAL HEALTH SETTINGS
SUCH AS MINE. WE DON'T SEE ABSTRACT DEBATES.
WE SEE THE OUTCOMES HIGHER RATES OF DEPRESSION, ANXIETY,
SELF-HARM AND CRISIS LEVEL PRESENTATIONS WHEN CARE IS
DELAYED OR DENIED FROM A HEALTH CARE SYSTEMS PERSPECTIVE THIS
IS NOT COST SAVING. IT'S COST SHIFTING WHEN
PREVENTATIVE OUTPATIENT CARE IS BLOCKED THOSE NEEDS DON'T
DISAPPEAR. THEY REEMERGE LATER AS
EMERGENCY VISITS, INPATIENT ADMISSIONS AND LONG TERM
PSYCHIATRIC CARE WHICH ARE FAR MORE EXPENSIVE FOR THE CITY,
THE STATE AND OUR COUNTRY AS A WHOLE.
AS A NURSE I SUPPORT POLICIES TO KEEP CARE EVIDENCE BASED,
ACCESSIBLE AND PREVENTATIVE ESPECIALLY FOR YOUNG PEOPLE
BECAUSE THAT'S HOW WE PROTECT BOTH PATIENT OUTCOMES
AND PUBLIC RESOURCES OVER TIME. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
. YES, HI.
HELLO THERE WE GO TO MY GOT IT .
>> AM I HERE? I'M THERE.
OKAY. MY NAME IS JOSHUA MALESKY.
I'M A DISPLACED TENANT FROM 50 GOLDEN GATE APARTMENTS.
I WAS DISPLACED DUE TO FIRE. I'M ASKING TO PLEASE APPROVE
ITEM 51 SUPPORTING FIRE DISPLACED RESIDENTS WITH
EXTENDED AID CASE MANAGEMENT AND STRONGER LANGUAGE ACCESS
WHAT I FOUND OUT FROM BECOMING DISPLACED DUE TO FIRE IS THAT
WHEN YOU GO LOOKING FOR ANOTHER PLACE TO RENT LANDLORDS DON'T
CARE TOO MUCH ABOUT YOUR ASSETS.
>> THEY LOOK AT YOUR INCOME AND I'M RETIRED AND I LIVE IN A
FIXED INCOME BUT THE INCOME ISN'T ENOUGH TO SECURE HOUSING
IN THIS MARKET WHICH IS VERY CONSTRAINED ALTHOUGH I HAVE
LIKE LIQUIDITY ASSETS IN A4A1K THAT CAN COVER RENT IN THIS
MARKET LANDLORDS ARE RELUCTANT TO RENT TO ME BECAUSE OF MY
INCOME AND THEN WHAT I FOUND IS WHEN I APPLIED FOR TEMPORARY
ASSISTANCE FOR DISPLACED PERSONS THROUGH SAN FRANCISCO'S
HUMAN SERVICES AGENCY MY LIQUIDITY ASSETS BECAME A
LIABILITY FOR QUALIFYING FOR TEMPORARY HOUSING.
I'M ONE OF THOSE PEOPLE IN THE MISSING MIDDLE EXCLUDED FROM
RENTAL ASSISTANCE DUE TO ASSET THRESHOLDS THAT DO NOT REFLECT
THE ACTUAL NEEDED LIQUIDITY RESOURCES AS REQUIRED TO LIVE
IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> THIS RESOLUTION SUPPORTING
FIRE DISPLACED RESIDENTS WITH EXTENDED AID CASE MANAGEMENT
AND STRONGER LANGUAGE ACCESS ADDRESSES THESE ISSUES AND I
URGE THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO APPROVE APPROVED THE
RESOLUTION AND PLEASE HOLD MASA ACCOUNTABLE FOR ITS ACTIONS
CONCERNING TENANT REFUNDS OF THEIR DECEMBER RENT.
>> AND THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD EVENING. HI MY NAME IS MELBA VILLA
AND I'M ALSO ONE OF THE DISPLACED TENANT AT 50 GOLDEN
GATE. LIKE MANY RESIDENTS OF THE
BUILDING, MY FAMILY MY FAMILY LOST A SENSE OF SAFETY
OVERNIGHT. WE WERE FORCED OUT OF OUR HOME
WITH LITTLE WARNING LIMITED ACCESS TO OUR BELONGINGS AND NO
CLEAR TIMELINE FOR WHEN OR IF WE COULD RETURN.
>> SPACE IS DISPLACEMENT IS NOT JUST ABOUT LOSING A PHYSICAL
SPACE. >> IT'S ABOUT LOSING STABILITY,
ROUTINE AND PEACE OF MIND. WE WERE TOLD TO SEEK ASSISTANCE
THROUGH THE HUMAN SERVICE AGENCY WHICH IS MEANT TO BE A
LIFELINE FOR PEOPLE IN CRISIS. WE WOULD AID IN ALL CAUSE OF A
NEW TEMPORARY APARTMENT. HOWEVER, WE WERE INFORMED THAT
WE DO NOT QUALIFY FOR HELP BECAUSE OUR ASSETS ARE ABOVE
THE CURRENT LIMIT. I WANT TO BE VERY CLEAR ABOUT
WHAT THAT MEANS IN MY LIFE. MY HUSBAND HAS SURVIVED TWO
BRAIN TUMORS BECAUSE OF THAT REALITY.
>> WE HAVE BEEN FINANCIALLY CAUTIOUS OUT OF NECESSITY NOT
PRIVILEGE. THE ASSETS WE HAVE ARE NOT
ACCESS OR DISPOSABLE. THEY ARE A SAFEGUARD AGAINST
CATALYSTS OFFING MEDICAL COSTS, GAPS IN INSURANCE COVERAGE
AND FUTURE EMERGENCIES. THEY REPRESENT SURVIVAL
PLANNING, NOT FINANCIAL COMFORT.
YET UNDER CURRENT SYSTEM HAVING PREPARED RESPONSIBILITY
DISQUALIFY US FROM RECEIVING EMERGENCY ASSISTANCE DURING THE
ONE OF THE MOST STABLE HOUSING EVENTS A FAMILY CAN EXPERIENCE.
>> THIS IS WHERE THE SYSTEM FAILS THE VERY PEOPLE IT SHOULD
BE PROTECTING. MIDDLE CLASS FAMILIES OFTEN
FALL INTO A PAINFUL GAP. >> WE EARN TOO MUCH TO QUALIFY
FOR HELP BUT NOT ENOUGH TO OBSERVE SUDDEN LIFE ALTERING
LOSSES. A FIRE DOES NOT DISCRIMINATE
BASED ON INCOME AND NEITHER SHOULD ACCESS EMERGENCY SUPPORT
. >> DISPLACEMENT AFFECTS MENTAL
HEALTH, PHYSICAL HEALTH, EMPLOYMENT STABILITY AND LONG
TERM FINANCIAL SECURITY. REGARDLESS OF WIDESPREAD AID,
WHAT A SPREADSHEET SAYS ABOUT THE ASSETS.
WE'RE NOT ASKING FOR SPECIAL TREATMENT.
WE'RE ASKING FOR A SYSTEM THAT REFLECTS FAIRNESS, COMPASSION
AND A TRUE COST OF LIVING IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> SO PLEASE SUPPORT NUMBER 51 AND PLEASE HOLD MOSER
ACCOUNTABLE. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HELLO. MY NAME IS ARIEL PARK AND I'M
ALSO A DISPLACED RESIDENT AT 50 GOLDEN GATE.
AND I WAS SOMEONE THAT FORTUNATELY DID QUALIFY FOR FHA
FUNDING AND I'M CURRENTLY RESIDING AND CURRENTLY RESIDING
IN T&E PROPERTY. SO I MEAN I'M AN AM AN EXAMPLE
OF WHEN THE CITY GETS IT RIGHT AND I'D LIKE TO SEE THE CITY
GET IT RIGHT MUCH MORE OFTEN BECAUSE SOME OF SOME OF MY
NEIGHBORS ARE YOU KNOW YOU KNOW THEY THEY HAVE LOW INCOME BUT
THEIR ASSETS ARE TOO HIGH OR THERE'S SOMETHING PREVENTING
THEM FROM QUALIFYING FOR EMERGENCY ASSISTANCE AND AND
THE $30,000 THRESHOLD WOULD EVAPORATE VERY QUICKLY HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO AND EVEN IN LOWER COST OF LIVING AREAS.
>> SO I'M HERE IN SUPPORT OF 50 51 AND ALSO TO HOLD MASSER
ACCOUNTABLE. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
HI. MY NAME IS PAMELA SMITH.
I'M ALSO DISPLACED FROM 50 GOLDEN GATE, MY HOME FOR 19
YEARS AND I JUST WANT TO SAY IT WAS VERY TRAUMATIC NOT
QUALIFYING FOR HSA ALTHOUGH MY INCOME IS VERY IT'S NOT VERY
MUCH AND I JUST REALLY URGE YOU TO SUPPORT RESOLUTION 50 ONE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD EVENING.
MY NAME IS ANNE MARIE VAN BUREN AND I AM A RESIDENT OF 50
GOLDEN GATE THAT IS UNTIL DECEMBER 12TH WHEN AT 3:15 A.M.
THERE WAS A THREE ALARM FIRE THAT DISPLACED 66 UNITS IN OUR
BUILDING AND I AM HERE TO THANK OUR SUPERVISOR IN DISTRICT FIVE
BELAL MAHMOOD FOR PUTTING FORTH THIS RESOLUTION TO INCREASE
FUNDING TO THE HUMAN SERVICES AGENCY AND THE TEMPORARY
ASSISTANCE FOR DISPLACED PERSONS BECAUSE BEING ON THE
SIDEWALK AT 315 IN THE MORNING WHILE YOUR BUILDING IS BURNING
IS NOT AN EXPERIENCE THAT ANYONE SHOULD HAVE TO GO
THROUGH AND I HOPE YOU NEVER HAVE TO GO THROUGH IT.
THE RESOLUTION WOULD INCREASE THE ASSET CAP FROM $30,000 TO
MEDICAL LIMITS WHICH ARE $130,000 FOR AN INDIVIDUAL.
AND WHAT HAS HAPPENED IS A LOT OF PEOPLE HAVE AS IT IS NOW
YOU'RE ALLOWED 100% OF AREA MEDIAN INCOME AND $30,000 ASSET
CAT TO CAP TO QUALIFY FOR THE PROGRAM WHICH HELPS TO PAY FOR
THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN YOUR RENT CONTROLLED HOUSING
AND YOUR MARKET RATE HOUSING WHICH IS TEMPORARY UNTIL YOUR
PLACE IS RECONDITIONED. AND SO THE SITUATION EVEN WITH
RAISING THE ASSET CAP WOULD HELP SO MANY PEOPLE THAT ARE
LOW INCOME PERHAPS 50% OF AM I BUT HAVE JUST ENOUGH OVER THAT
30,000 THAT THEY'RE NOT QUALIFYING AND WHAT'S HAPPENING
IS THEY'RE FALLING THROUGH THE GAP AND ARE UNABLE TO QUALIFY
FOR HOUSING BECAUSE THEY DON'T MAKE ENOUGH TO MAKE THE RENT.
>> SO I'M HOPING YOU WILL SUPPORT THIS AND THAT WE CAN
HOLD MANSOUR ACCOUNTABLE FOR KEEPING A TIGHT TIMELINE ON
REHABILITATING OUR BUILDINGS SO IT'S INHABITABLE AGAIN.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENT.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER .
HI, MY NAME IS GREGORY JOHNSON. I'VE BEEN A RESIDENT OF 50
GOLDEN GATE SINCE 1994 AND ON DECEMBER 12TH I FOUND MYSELF
INSTANTLY HOMELESS. A FEW YEARS AGO I GOT A JOB
WHERE I WAS ABLE TO FINALLY SAVE SOME MONEY FOR MY FUTURE.
BECAUSE OF THAT I DON'T QUALIFY FOR ASSISTANCE.
I DON'T THINK IT SHOULD MATTER HOW MUCH MONEY SOMEONE HAS
SAVED WHEN A PERSON IS FACED WITH A DISASTER OR DISPLACEMENT
NOT IF THEY'RE DOING ASSISTANCE SHOULD BE AVAILABLE.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR CONSIDERATION.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
ALLOW IN A SERVICE I MEAN I'M READY FOR LETHAL SO SERVICE
IN THE WINDOW
. >> THE FOLLOWING IS A SUMMARY.
HELLO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS ALICIA LITTLE.
I'M ALSO A RESIDENT FROM 50 GOLDEN GATE.
I'M GOING TO READ YOU AN EMAIL THAT I SENT TO THE LANDLORD
REGARDING THE SITUATION THAT I FIND MYSELF IN THE LET ME TELL
YOU DO YOU ALREADY KNOW THAT YOUR SECURITY WORKERS, YOUR
WORKERS AND THE SECURITY STAFF BROKE INTO MY APARTMENT
AND STOLE ALL MY CASH. THEY SEARCHED MY BED AND IN MY
DRAWERS AND TOOK AWAY MY DESIGNER HANDBAGS AND GOLD
BRACELETS. I BOUGHT FIVE YEARS AGO FOR MY
SON'S GRADUATION NEXT YEAR AT THE NOW CLOSED MALL THEY TOOK
MY PASSPORT AND MY HEADPHONES LOOK MERRY.
I CAN REPLACE ALL MATERIAL THINGS BY WORKING BUT
I HAD BEEN SAVING CASH FOR MY SON'S COLLEGE TUITION IN MEXICO
FOR EIGHT MONTHS FOR OVER $8,000 IN CASH.
>> I EMAILED YOU EARLIER TO LET YOU IN TO GET BACK MY MONEY.
I WARNED YOU THAT YOU DIDN'T WANT ANY SURPRISE THIS THAT I
DIDN'T WANT ANY SURPRISES BUT WHEN I WALKED INTO MY APARTMENT
IT WAS A COMPLETE MESS. YOU'RE NOT HELPING ME GET A NEW
APARTMENT. YOU HAVEN'T EVEN PAID BACK THE
RENT. I PAID FOR DECEMBER.
AND YOU THINK THE SITUATION IS GOING TO STAY THAT WAY?
>> I REQUEST TO BE TEMPORARILY RELOCATED TO ANOTHER LARGER
UNIT WHILE 50 GOLDEN GATE IS RESTORED DURING ANY TEMPORARY
RELOCATION MY CURRENT LEASE MUST REMAIN IN FULL EFFECT
AND MY CURRENT RENTAL AT MY CURRENT RENTAL RATE AT THIS
TEMPORARY RELOCATION AND THIS TEMPORARY RELOCATION WILL NOT
BE CONSIDERED A VOLUNTARY VACANCY OR A TERMINATION OF MY
LEASE OR A WAIVER OF ANY RIGHT. I RELINQUISH MY RIGHTS FOR AN
APARTMENT AT 50 GOLDEN GATE. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
SUPERVISORS THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR LISTENING TO OUR STATEMENTS
. BENEATH EVERY SINGLE PERSON'S
EMOTION, EXPERIENCE AND STATEMENT THAT YOU'VE HEARD
YOU'RE GOING TO FIND THAT ULTIMATELY RESOLUTION 51 THAT'S
BEING PUT FORTH BY SUPERVISOR BILAL MAHMUD HERE IS
EFFECTIVELY A HOMELESS PREVENTION MEASURE.
IT'S ALSO A TEST OF WHETHER OUR CITY RESPONDS TO DISASTER WITH
EQUITY, TRANSPARENCY AND COMPASSION AND WHETHER WE
BUILD A SYSTEM THAT WORKS THE NEXT TIME THAT THIS HAPPENS.
AS HAS BEEN THE CASE THIS TIME SOME OF THESE TENANTS ARE NOW
HOMELESS. SOME OF THEM ARE LIVING
IN THEIR CARS. THERE WAS A WOMAN LESS THAN TWO
WEEKS AGO WHO GAVE BIRTH TO HER CHILD AT A HOSPITAL IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND WENT HOME TO HER CAR BECAUSE OF THIS FIRE.
NOW IN ADDITION TO UPPING THE ASSET ASSET THRESHOLD, IT WOULD
DIRECT HSA HUMAN SERVICE AGENCIES AND PARTNER
DEPARTMENTS TO IMPLEMENT A UNIFIED DISPLACEMENT RESPONSE
PROTOCOL WITH STAFF CASE MANAGEMENT AND SUSTAINED
LANGUAGE ACCESS FOR NON-NATIVE SPEAKERS.
DISTRICT FIRES REVIEW DOCUMENTED SERIOUS GAPS THAT
LEFT RESIDENTS WITHOUT TIMELY EMERGENCY HOUSING WITHOUT
FINANCIAL RELIEF, FOOD ASSISTANCE, TRANSPORTATION OR
CLEAR REHOUSING PATHWAYS. EFFECTIVELY IT WAS A TEMPORARY
HELP THAT EXPIRED IN A WAY THAT DIDN'T HELP RECOVERY.
IT JUST DELAYED IT. THIS RESOLUTION IS DESIGNED TO
FIX THOSE SPECIFIC FAILURE POINTS.
EVERYONE HERE IS BEGGING YOU PLEASE VOTE YES ON RESOLUTION
51 AND FUNDING IT SO THESE CHANGES ACTUALLY GET
IMPLEMENTED. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HELLO. MY NAME IS GARDENIA.
I'M A FORMER RESIDENT OF 50 GOLDEN GATE AVENUE, A MOTHER
AND AN ADVOCATE FOR MY FELLOW NEIGHBORS.
>> I NO LONGER LIVE IN SAN FRANCISCO NOT BY CHOICE, BY MY
CIRCUMSTANCES. YET I HAVE BEEN COMMUTING FROM
THE EAST BAY TO SHOW UP FOR MY NEIGHBORS BECAUSE OUR MAYOR HAS
NOT. >> PLEASE APPROVE ITEM 51.
>> THIS BUILDING IS LITERALLY THREE BLOCKS AWAY FROM CITY
HALL AND YET FAMILIES ARE SLEEPING IN CARS, SHELTERS, BUS
STOPS WITH CHILDREN. >> THIS PAST WEEKEND I RECEIVED
A CALL FROM A MOTHER WHO HAD JUST GIVING BIRTH.
THEY SHOULD HAVE BEEN RECOVERING BONDING WITH THEIR
NEWBORN INSTEAD. SHE HAS BEEN PREPARING TO
RETURN TO HER VEHICLE BECAUSE SHE WAS NOT APPROVED BY HSA.
THIS IS NOT AN INSULATOR FAILURE.
THIS IS A SYSTEMATIC BREAKING PEOPLE FAMILIES ARE STUCK INTO
A LIMBO BECAUSE THE INCOME THRESHOLDS THAT PLANNERS
RESPONSIBILITY THRESHOLDS THAT ACCOUNT SAVINGS MEAN FOR
SURGERIES, MEDICAL CARE OR RETIREMENT AS IF THEY ARE
IN WEALTH THAT IS NOT WEALTH. THIS IS PLANNING FOR SURVIVAL.
HSA IS ALSO SEVERELY UNDERSTAFFED.
TWO STAFF MEMBERS RESPONDING TO A HOUSING DISASTER.
ONE OF THEM WAS ACTUALLY ON VACATION.
THIS WAS ONE BUILDING. IMAGINE IF IT WAS AN ENTIRE
BLOCK. >> THIS IS HOW HOMELESSNESS
STARTS. NOT BECAUSE PEOPLE ARE
IRRESPONSIBLE BUT BECAUSE WORKING PEOPLE WHO PAY RENT
AND TAXES ARE ABANDONED WHEN A CRISIS HITS.
I HAVE PERSONALLY BEEN PAYING FOR FOOD, DIAPERS AND BASIC
NECESSITIES OUT OF MY OWN POCKET TO HELP SOME OF THESE
FAMILIES. >> WE WERE TOLD MANY PARCELS
WILL BE ISSUED. THEY WEREN'T.
FAMILIES CANNOT ACCESS FOOD STAMPS BECAUSE THEY DO NOT HAVE
THE ACCESS TO PROVIDE AN ADDRESS.
SO I PARTNER WITH A COUPLE OF SMALL ORGANIZATIONS INVITE THE
SUPPORT. BUT WHERE IS OUR MAYOR?
>> WE ASKED FOR ITEM 51 TO BE APPROVED BUT ALSO TO HOLD MAZUR
ACCOUNTABLE. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. LET'S WELCOME OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> HELLO.
MY NAME IS HAILEY MEYERHOFF. I AM AN ORGANIZER AT THE
HOUSING RIGHTS COMMITTEE OF SAN FRANCISCO AND I'VE BEEN
SUPPORTING THE TENANTS OF 50 GOLDEN GATE.
>> I JUST WANT TO SAY THAT THIS ISN'T THE ONLY BUILDING THAT
DESPERATELY NEEDS YOU TO PASS RESOLUTION 51.
>> AS AN ORGANIZER I'M CURRENTLY WORKING WITH TWO
OTHER MASTER OR FORMERLY MASTER BUILDINGS WHO EXPERIENCED FIRES
AND IN THEIR TIME OF CRISIS THEY ONLY GOT EMPTY PROMISES
FROM MASTER OVERALL OUR ORGANIZATION HAS SEEN NO LESS
THAN HUNDREDS, MAYBE THOUSANDS OF TENANTS OVER THE YEARS WHO
HAVE BEEN DISPLACED BY FIRES. MANY OF THEM HAVE NOT BEEN
ELIGIBLE FOR CITY SERVICES OR THEY HAVEN'T BEEN ABLE TO
ACCESS THEM BECAUSE OF LANGUAGE BARRIERS.
IT IS ABSOLUTELY CRITICAL THAT THE CITY INCREASE THE HSA
THRESHOLD AND PROVIDE MORE SUPPORT TO THIS SERVICE.
>> IT'S THE CITY'S RESPONSIBILITY TO TAKE CARE OF
ITS PEOPLE AND TO PROTECT THEM FROM LANDLORDS THAT AIM TO MAKE
MONEY OFF OF BAD CONDITIONS, NEGLECT AND DISPLACEMENT.
ADOPTING RESOLUTION 51 WOULD BE A FIRST STEP THAT EACH OF YOU
COULD TAKE TODAY TO PROVE TO THESE RESIDENTS AND TO ALL
TENANTS IN SAN FRANCISCO THAT THE CITY HAS THEIR BACKS.
I URGE YOU TO IMMEDIATELY ADOPT THIS RESOLUTION AND PROVE SAN
FRANCISCO CITY GOVERNMENT TO BE ONE THAT STANDS WITH TENANTS
IN THE FACE OF LANDLORDS WHO NEGLECT AND DISRESPECT THEIR
RESIDENTS. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
MAY I ASK THE GENTLEMAN IN THE BACK WITH THE LIGHT ON THE
CAMERA TO. >> YOU'RE WELCOME TO FILM SIR.
JUST DON'T USE YOUR LIGHT. >> CATCH UP.
WELCOME. >> HELLO.
I'M HERE TO SUPPORT A RESOLUTION OF 49 FOR A GENDER
AFFIRMING CARE FOR TRANS KIDS. I ALSO SUPPORTS RESOLUTION 51
AND AND AM IN SOLIDARITY WITH EVERYONE THOSE DISPLACED BY THE
FIRE IN THE TENDERLOIN. >> I THANK THE RAINBOW FAMILIES
ACTION AND THE TRANS CAUCUS FROM THE HARVEY MILK CLUB.
GENUINELY THANK THEM FOR WORKING ON THIS RESOLUTION.
MY COMMENT IS JUST REPRESENTING MYSELF SO WHY WHY DID THIS TAKE
SO LONG TO EVEN SAY THAT YOU WOULD SUPPORT TRANS KIDS
AND THAT THEY SHOULD HAVE GENDER AFFIRMING CARE?
ESPECIALLY IT'S BEEN A YEAR AND SOME OF YOU STOOD ON A
STAGE IN FRONT OF A CAMERA SAYING YOU WOULD PROTECT TRANS
KIDS FROM LIKE THIS. A YEAR LATER IS WHEN YOU COME
OUT AND WITH THE RESOLUTION LIKE I'M OFFENDED.
I'M NOT GRATEFUL FOR YOUR SEVERE TARDINESS.
I'M NOT GRATEFUL THAT YOU WERE SILENCE FOR THIS PAST YEAR
WHILE KIDS WERE HAVING THEIR HEALTH CARE TAKEN AWAY FROM
THEM TEMPORARILY IN SAN FRANCISCO.
THAT WAS UNDER THREAT A FEW TIMES.
YOU THE BOARD HERE PREVIOUS BOARD ALSO UNANIMOUSLY VOTED TO
PASS MY RESOLUTION TO PROTECT TRANS KIDS AND ADULTS.
>> SO I AM INTIMATELY FAMILIAR WITH YOUR PERFORMATIVE NATURE
AS A BOARD. >> IF YOU WANT TO PROVE THAT
THIS IS NOT PERFORMATIVE. BACK THIS UP WITH SOME REAL
ACTION. OKAY.
HOW ABOUT STOPPING THE OFFICE OF TRANSGENDER INITIATIVES FROM
BEING DISMANTLED OLD, DEFUNDED AND DISEMPOWERED?
YOU CAN START THERE. YOU CAN MAKE THE TRANS
SANCTUARY CITY RESOLUTION AN ORDINANCE LIKE THE IMMIGRANT
SANCTUARY CITY ORDINANCE IS SO THAT SOMETHING IS ENFORCEABLE
IS NOT JUST WORDS, WORDS, WORDS.
>> YOU CAN RETURN THE CULTURAL COMPETENCY TRAINING TO S.F.
GOVERNMENT EMPLOYEES. THAT WAS TAKEN AWAY.
YOU COULD ADVOCATE FOR US TO NOT HAVE OUR FUNDING TAKEN AWAY
BY THE MAYOR. >> THE MAYOR IS JUST LIKE
CUTTING EVERYONE OFF AT THE KNEES IN THIS CITY LIKE REALLY
ADVOCATE FOR US LIKE I DON'T KNOW DO YOUR OWN PROTEST OR
SOMETHING. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
,GENERAL COMEY. THIS WEEK IN SAN FRANCISCO WE
ARE HOSTING THE SUPER BOWL ACTIVITIES.
BUT JUST LAST FRIDAY A CHILD WAS SHOT AND KILLED AT A PUBLIC
PARK AND TWO OTHER CHILDREN. WENDY SIT WITH ASKED WHY THE
CITY PREPARES FOR CELEBRATION, FAMILIES ARE PLANNING FUNERALS.
WE ARE TOLD TO CHEER TO SPEND MONEY TO LOOK AWAY WHILE OUR
CHILDREN ARE DYING. THIS IS NOT JUST RANDOM
VIOLENCE. THIS IS SYSTEMATIC FAILURE.
WE NEED TO TALK ABOUT PREVENTION.
ARE YOU ANY PLACES TO GO? REAL FUNDED NEIGHBORHOOD BASED
HUBS WHERE THERE ARE SAFE MEANS ALREADY AND SUPPORTED HAS SEEN
PARKS AND PLAYGROUNDS SHOULD NOT BE DANGEROUS ZONES THEY
SHOULD BE PROTECTED SPACES. WE ALSO HAVE TO BE HONEST ABOUT
DISPLACEMENT. BLACK FAMILIES HAVE BEEN
SYSTEMATICALLY PUSHED OUT OF THE VERY NEIGHBORHOODS WE HAVE
BUILT AROUND THE WORLD OFTEN IN THE NAME OF REDEVELOPMENT
WHEN FAMILIES ARE REMOVED, COMMUNITIES TIES ARE BROKEN,
YOUTH ARE DESTABILIZED AND SAFETY DECLINES.
YOU CANNOT DISPLACE PEOPLE, REMOVE RESOURCES AND THEN ACT
SURPRISED WHEN VIOLENCE INCREASES.
THESE OUTCOMES ARE CONNECTED. THEY ARE THE RESULT OF POLICY
DECISIONS. THE CITY CONTINUES TO SPEND
MILLIONS ON MAJOR EVENTS AND INSTITUTIONS ARE FAILING TO
INVEST AT THE SAME LEVEL IN BLACK CHILDREN AND FAMILIES
THE ONES THAT'S LEFT MEANWHILE BLACK YOUTH ARE BEING LOST TO
VIOLENCE, DISPLACEMENT AND NEGLECT.
>> WE ARE DESPAIRING FROM SAN FRANCISCO BUT NOT BY ACCIDENT
BUT BY POLICY. >> YOU CANNOT CONTINUE TO FIND
SPECTACLE WHILE NEGLECTING SURVIVAL.
THAT IS A CHOICE AND CHOICES HAVE CONSEQUENCES.
I'M ASKING THE BOARD TO PRIORITIZE FUNDING FOR
NEIGHBORHOOD BASED YOUTH HUBS AND VIOLENCE PREVENTION BEFORE
THE NEXT TRAGEDY HAPPENS NOT AFTER.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> JUST A REMINDER SHOW YOUR
SUPPORT AS SUCH NO AUDIBLE SOUNDS PLEASE BOARD ROOM.
THANK YOU. WELCOME.
>> GOOD EVENING, SUPERVISORS. REVEREND DR. MEGAN ROYER PROUD
TRANSGENDER RESIDENT OF BERNAL HEIGHTS.
>> I KNOW THAT THIS IS THE PLACE WHERE WE WILL BE
REAFFIRMING TRANS HEALTH CARE BECAUSE THIS IS THE PLACE WHERE
TRANSGENDER HEALTH CARE WAS BORN.
I WAS HERE IN THE ROOM THE DAY THAT SUPERVISOR BEVAN DUFTY
MADE IT A LAW THAT EMPLOYEES OF SAN FRANCISCO COULD GET TRANS
SERVICES COVERED IN THEIR INSURANCE WHICH PROVED TO
ADDITIONAL INSURANCE COMPANIES THAT IT WAS AFFORDABLE.
IT WASN'T GOING TO SINK THE BILL THAT TRANS PEOPLE AREN'T
THE CRAZY THINGS IMAGINED BY ANGRY LOUD PEOPLE ON TV
AND THAT COMPASSION CAN LEAD THE WAY.
Y'ALL DID IT IN THIS ROOM. >> AND I ALSO KNOW THAT EACH
DAY YOU SHOW UP TO DO IT AGAIN. REMEMBER WHEN VICKI LEE WAS
HERE SO MANY HOURS AGO YOU GUYS A YOUNG VICKY LEE FILLED OUT
THE PAPERWORK TO ALLOW THE VERY FIRST TRANSGENDER ORGANIZER
IN THE UNITED STATES TO BE FOUNDED AT GLIDE CHURCH.
>> IT WAS STILL ILLEGAL TO BE TRANS THEN WE FIXED THAT LATER
. >> THAT GROUP WAS FOUNDED TO
CREATE PEER BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CARE SUPPORT BECAUSE NO
THERAPISTS WOULD DO IT. DOWN THE STREET ON HYDE STREET,
TRANS MAN LOU SULLIVAN, WHOSE JOURNALS ARE STORED AT THE SAN
FRANCISCO PUBLIC LIBRARY CREATED A NEWSLETTER THAT FOR A
DECADE TAUGHT TRANS PEOPLE HOW TO ADVOCATE FOR THEMSELVES AT
THE DOCTOR'S OFFICE. BECAUSE BACK THEN TO DOCTORS
REFUSE TO LEARN HOW TO CARE FOR US USING MISOGYNY MOTION MOSTLY
HARRY BENJAMIN HAD THE VERY FIRST HEALTH CLINIC THAT WAS
ACTIVELY CARING FOR TRANS PEOPLE.
IT WAS AT UNIONS SQUARE. AND AS WE HAVE HEARD BEFORE, WE
GET MOST OF OUR INFORMATION ABOUT WHERE TO GET OUR HEALTH
CARE NOW FROM THE COMMUNICATIONS OFFICE AT THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE OF TRANSGENDER INITIATIVES A POSITION
CURRENTLY NOT FILLED BECAUSE OF A HIRING FREEZE.
WE WANT BOTH YOUR SUPPORT IN THIS DOCUMENT AND IN THE
BUDGET IN THE MONTHS TO COME. THE CULTURE DISTRICT HOSTS A
LOT OF OUR TRANS AWARENESS ORGANIZATIONS BECAUSE THE
DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE FEDERALLY DECLARED A BOUNTY FOR PEOPLE
WHO DECLARE TRANS HEALTH CARE. >> WE NEED OUR THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HI. MY NAME IS RICHARD JOHNSON
AND I'M DOING EXCUSE ME A FOLLOW UP TO WHAT I DISCUSSED
AT LAST WEEK'S BOARD OF SUPERVISORS MEETING.
IT'S ABOUT THE HISTORY CLOSURE AND IT'S ABOUT THE UNDUE
INFLUENCE THAT'S HAPPENING WITHIN THIS QUARTER.
WE HAVE A SUPERVISOR THAT IS UNDULY INFLUENCING THE S.F.
MTA. WE ARE FINDING THIS OUT THROUGH
DISCLOSURE REQUESTS. >> WE'RE AT THE WHIM OF THE
BOARD HERE BECAUSE THE WAY THAT THE APPEAL PROJECT PROCESS
GOES. IT COMES TO YOU AS A
SUPERVISORS TO APPEAL ON AN APPEAL FROM THE MTA.
WE HAVE OVER 60 WEEKS OF VIOLATIONS THAT HAVE BEEN
DOCUMENTED. AND THIS IS ACTUALLY LED TO ONE
OF OUR MEMBERS TO HAVE LEGAL ACTION THREATENED AGAINST THEM
FOR A STAY AWAY ORDER. AND THE OTHER ISSUE IS WITH
WE'VE BEEN THROUGH THIS ROAD BEFORE ABOUT S.F. MTA APPEALS.
AND IT'S INTERESTING IT COMES DOWN TO WHAT THE SUPERVISOR
WANTS. WE HEAR FROM EVERY OTHER
SUPERVISOR. AND I THINK THAT NEEDS TO BE
CALLED TO ATTENTION OF BOTH WHAT'S HAPPENING WITH THE S.F.
MTA AND THE CULTURE OF KIND OF BACKING WHAT WHAT A FELLOW
SUPERVISOR DOES AT THE EXPENSE OF A MINORITY GROUP THAT IS
VERY VOCAL, VERY LOUD. WE HAVE WELL WELL DOCUMENTED
THINGS AND IT'S INTERESTING HOW WE'RE DISCUSSING ABOUT THIS ALL
THESE ISSUES OF DIVERSITY AND EQUITY AND THIS TO ME
EMBODIES ALL OF THIS AND IT COMES BACK TO YOU AS A GROUP
THAT THIS IS AN IN-HOUSE THING THAT NEEDS TO BE LOOKED AT AT
THE UNDUE INFLUENCE OF THE BOARD OF ON THE S.F. MTA
AND THE PARK AND THE APPEAL PROCESS.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR YOUR TIME AND LOOK FORWARD TO
SPEAKING WITH YOU AGAIN. >> I THANK YOU FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
SESSION. ALL RIGHT.
>> BEFORE I START I WANTED TO SAY THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR
CHAN FOR SUPPORTING TRANS PEOPLE'S RIGHT TO HEALTH CARE.
>> HELLO EVERYONE. >> MY NAME IS CADEN OR CAGE
GIACOMO. MY PRONOUNS ARE HIM AND THEY
THEM AND I AM A TRANS MAN. I CAME OUT AS GENDERQUEER
AND NEARING THE END OF THE PANDEMIC AND STARTED
IDENTIFYING AS A TRANS MALE THREE YEARS AGO.
>> CURRENTLY I AM HOPING TO MEDICALLY TRANSITION.
>> IN FACT ABOUT A YEAR AGO NOW I THOUGHT I'D BE PREPARING FOR
TOP SURGERY. HOWEVER, DUE TO INTENSE
PRESSURE FROM THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT, MY HEALTH CARE
PROVIDER PUT A BAN ON GENDER AFFIRMING SURGERIES TO PEOPLE
UNDER 19. STOPPING THE PROCESS FOR ME AS
AN 18 YEAR OLD. AS YOU MAY HAVE HEARD BEFORE
TRANSFERRING CARE IS LIFE SAVING AND I'M NOT GOING TO GO
MORE SORRY. GENDER AFFIRMING CARE ISN'T
JUST TOP SURGERY AND BOTTOM REASSIGNMENT SURGERY.
GENDER AFFIRMING CARE IS GENDER THERAPY COUNSELING, HORMONE
REPLACEMENT AND BLOCKERS. FOR MANY PEOPLE UNDER 18,
SURGERIES ARE RARE BECAUSE OF THE LONG EVALUATION PROCESS.
I KNOW SOMEONE WHO'S BEEN ON THE LIST FOR FIVE YEARS.
>> I'M SORRY. FOR MANY REASON.
>> FOR MANY PEOPLE BY CUTTING ACCESS TO HEALTH CARE FOR TRANS
PEOPLE NOT JUST FOR MINORS. WE ARE INCREASING THE RATES OF
SUICIDE IN TRANS INDIVIDUALS AND PUTTING THEIR SAFETY AT
RISK. AT THIS MOMENT OUR CURRENT
ADMINISTRATION HAS LABELED PEOPLE LIKE ME TERRORISTS.
>> WE HAVE SEEN A SPIKE IN HATE CRIMES AGAINST TRANS PEOPLE
THROUGHOUT THE U.S.. SUICIDE RATES IN LGBTQ
COMMUNITIES HAVE INCREASED SIGNIFICANTLY.
DISCRIMINATION IS RAMPANT AND OUR RIGHTS ARE BEING
STRIPPED FROM US. SAN FRANCISCO WOULD NOT BE SAN
FRANCISCO WITHOUT TRANS PEOPLE .
>> BUT I FEEL THAT I KNOW I FEEL THE NEED TO REMIND YOU
THAT WE ARE HOME TO THE WORLD'S FIRST TRANSGENDER DISTRICT
FOUNDED IN 2017. WHILE WE'VE HAD OUR PROBLEMS
SAN FRANCISCO HAS HISTORICALLY BEEN A SAFE SPOT FOR LGBTQ
PEOPLE ESPECIALLY THE TRANS COMMUNITY.
TO NOT SUPPORT YOUR TRANS NEIGHBORS AND CITIZENS IS AN
INSULT TO OUR HISTORY. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> MY NAME IS ELLA. I'M A HIGH SCHOOLER AND I USE
THEY THEM PRONOUNS. I FIRST CAME OUT IN JULY OF
2022. I WOULDN'T HAVE BEEN BRAVE
ENOUGH TO FIND AND STAND UP FOR MYSELF WITHOUT OTHER STRONG
TRANS YOUTH TELLING ME THAT THERE WAS SOMETHING WORTH
FINDING AND SOMETHING WORTH FIGHTING FOR.
WE NEED TO BE ALIVE TO SUPPORT EACH OTHER.
GENDER AFFIRMING CARE SIMPLY DOES THAT.
I WANT TO GO TO SCHOOL WITH OTHER TRANS KIDS.
>> I WANT TO LEARN FROM TRANS TEACHERS AND I WANT TRANS
PEOPLE TO MY FRIENDS AND BOSSES AND COWORKERS BECAUSE THEY MAKE
ME FEEL SAFE AND THEY MAKE ME FEEL LIKE I CAN LIVE IN THIS
WORLD. COMMUNITY IS EVERYTHING FOR ME.
I'VE BEEN LUCKY ENOUGH TO FIND SOME OF THESE PEOPLE IN MY LIFE
AND IT HAS BEEN LIFE AFFIRMING. >> BUT DUE TO RESTRICTIONS ON
GENDER AFFIRMING CARE FOR TRANS YOUTH, SELF-HARM AND SUICIDE
CONTINUE TO THREATEN MY COMMUNITY.
SELF-HARM AND SUICIDE SHOULD NOT BE SOMETHING MY FRIENDS
AND I TALK ABOUT. IF WE ARE NOT ALIVE IT IS HARD
TO HAVE A COMMUNITY. I URGE SAN FRANCISCO TO PASS
ITEM 49 SO TRANS YOUTH AND ADULTS CAN HAVE A COMMUNITY
TO FIND WHEN THEY COME OUT. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD EVENING BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS ATTICUS. I GO BY THIS YEAR AND I WANTED
TO SPEAK ON THE FACT THAT THIS RESOLUTION HAS THE CHANCE TO BE
A DRIVING FORCE OF HOPE FOR TRANS PEOPLE IN THIS COUNTRY.
NOW AS WE ALL KNOW THAT THERE HAVE BEEN MANY ANTI-TRANS BILLS
BEING PASSED OR INTENDED TO BE PASSED IN OTHER STATES
AND CITIES THAT CAN ONLY BE DESCRIBED AS BLEAK BLOCKING
ACCESS TO LIFESAVING GENDER AFFIRMING HEALTH CARE FOR
YOUNGER PEOPLE AND NOT ALLOWING TRANS PEOPLE TO TRAVEL
AND VALIDATE THEIR DRIVER'S LICENSE AND PASSPORTS.
BUT WITH SO MANY OF THESE HARMFUL AND OPPRESSIVE BILLS,
WE HAVE THE CHANCE TO BE DIFFERENT AND TO GIVE TRANS
PEOPLE THE HOPE THEY DESPERATELY NEED.
DRIVING PEOPLE TO STAY IN THE CITY AND FEEL SAFE.
THIS RESOLUTION WILL NOT ONLY CHANGE LIVES BUT IT'LL SAVE
LIVES. AND FOR THE SAKE OF THIS CITY'S
COMMUNITY. PASS THE RESOLUTION.
THANK YOU. THAT'S ALL THE TIME I NEED.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME.
>> HELLO. I'M ARNIE WITH RAINBOW FAMILIES
ACTION. IT'S COMMON PRACTICE IN OUR
GROUP TO SPEAK FOR ROUGHLY THE MAJORITY OF OUR PARENTS FOR
WHOM SPEAKING OUT LOUD WOULD ACTUALLY ENDANGER THEIR
CHILDREN. I JUST WANT THAT TO SINK IN FOR
A SECOND. FOR PARENTS TO SPEAK UP FOR
THEIR CHILDREN WILL ENDANGER THEIR CHILDREN.
>> AND I'M GOING TO READ ONE OF THOSE.
NOW I HAVE BEEN FORTUNATE ENOUGH TO COUNT AGAINST MANY
TRANS NONBINARY AND GENDER NONCONFORMING YOUNG PEOPLE ON
MY MIND STUDENTS, FRIENDS AND EXTENDED FAMILY ACROSS
MULTIPLE STATES AND COUNTRIES. SOME OF THESE FOLKS HAVE BEEN
ABLE TO ACCESS GENDER AFFIRMING CARE AND SOME HAVE NOT.
AND I HAVE SEEN FIRSTHAND WHAT A DIFFERENCE THAT ACCESS CAN
MAKE. THIS CARE IS NOT ONLY GENDER
AFFIRMING, IT IS LIFE AFFIRMING AND I AM GRATEFUL TO THE BOARD
OF SUPERVISORS FOR RECOGNIZING THAT TODAY IN AN IDEAL WORLD
WHERE EVEN A DECENT AND REASONABLE ONE.
THIS RESOLUTION WOULD NOT NEED TO EXIST AS A REALIZATION
ITSELF POINTS OUT SAN FRANCISCO IS ALREADY A SANCTUARY CITY
AND SAFE HAVEN FOR THOSE WHO NEED AND THOSE WHO PROVIDE THIS
CARE. AND OUR STATE AND LOCAL LAWS
ALREADY PROTECT GENDER AFFIRMING CARE AS MEDICALLY
NECESSARY. BUT IN THIS WORLD WHEN THE CEOS
AND ADMINISTRATORS OF THE HEALTH CARE PROVIDERS OUR
COMMUNITY MEMBERS DEPEND ON FOR CARE HAVE REPEATEDLY SHOWN THAT
THEY ARE WILLING TO THROW VULNERABLE CHILDREN UNDER THE
BUS OUR CHILDREN WHEN THEY ARE CHOOSING TO PRE COMPLY WITH
FEDERAL RULE CHANGES BASED ON IGNORANCE AND BIGOTRY NOT
MEDICAL UNDERSTANDING IT BECOMES NECESSARY.
I AM GRATEFUL TO THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR RECOGNIZING
THAT NECESSITY. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN
AND ALL THOSE WHO CO-SPONSORED AND WORK TO PASS THIS
RESOLUTION. FOR REMINDING HEALTH CARE
PROVIDERS OF THEIR ONGOING AND UNCHANGED OBLIGATION TO
THEIR PATIENTS. THANK YOU FOR STANDING UP TO
FEDERAL OVERREACH AND INSISTING THAT HEALTH CARE PROVIDERS PUT
PATIENTS BEFORE POLITICS. THANK YOU FOR SEEING
AND VALUING AND PROTECTING TRANS KIDS.
>> AND THAT'S FROM THE VOICE FROM A MOTHER WHO IS NOT ABLE
TO BE HERE TODAY BECAUSE SHOWING THEIR FACE WOULD
ENDANGER THEIR CHILD. AND I WANT YOU ALL TO REMEMBER
THAT AS ALLIES WE NEED YOU TO STAND UP BECAUSE MANY FAMILIES,
MANY KIDS CANNOT STAND UP FOR THEMSELVES BECAUSE IT WOULD
MAKE THEIR LIVES MISERABLE. SO PLEASE STAND UP AS YOU HAVE
TODAY. >> WE APPRECIATE IT, SUPERVISOR
CHAN AND EVERYONE ELSE. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME.
NEXT SPEAKER. >> HELLO THERE.
MY NAME IS JIM JAFFE. I USE THE IN THEM PRONOUNS
AND THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF LION MARTIN COMMUNITY HEALTH
SERVICES AND THE MISSION WHERE A FEDERALLY QUALIFIED HEALTH
CENTER AND I AM THE ONLY TRANSGENDER EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR
OF A FEDERALLY QUALIFIED HEALTH CENTER IN THE COUNTRY.
AND I COMMEND SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR INTRODUCING THIS
RESOLUTION. TRANS PEOPLE HAVE BEEN DYING
ALL AROUND US SO IT FEELS REALLY HOPEFUL TO FINALLY SEE
ACKNOWLEDGED MANY OF THE VULNERABILITIES OF OUR
COMMUNITIES. GENOCIDE EXPERTS HAVE SAID THAT
A GENOCIDE IS ALREADY IN PROGRESS AGAINST TRANSGENDER
PEOPLE IN THIS COUNTRY. WE'RE IN FACT QUITE FAR ALONG
THAT PATH ALREADY AND THE LACK OF RESPONSE FROM THE CITY LAST
YEAR LED US TO ACTUALLY EXPAND AND OPEN OUR DOORS TO MINORS
FOR GENDER AFFIRMING CARE AT LION MARTIN.
WE DECIDED THAT WE WOULD BE THE SAFETY NET TO THE SAFETY NET
BECAUSE THE CITY DID NOT HAVE A RESPONSE.
AS CLINICS AND HOSPITALS ACROSS THE COUNTRY SUDDENLY SHUTTERED
THEIR DOORS TO THESE KIDS, WE OPENED DOORS AND SO AGAIN, I
JUST WANT TO COMMEND SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR THIS RESOLUTION.
AND YET I REALLY WANT TO HIGHLIGHT THAT CITY THE
DEPARTMENTS ARE CUTTING $400,000 PER YEAR IN OUR BUDGET
THIS YEAR STARTING AND STARTING IN JULY.
AND THIS IS DESPITE PROMISES AND DECLARATIONS EVEN IN MARY
LORI'S INAUGURAL SPEECH HE MENTIONED THAT THERE WOULD BE
NO CUTS TO LAMERTON. DO NOT LET THIS RESOLUTION BE
PERFORMATIVE. WE HAVE WORK TO DO THAT WE CAN
ONLY DO WITH YOUR SUPPORT AND WE ARE HERE AND READY TO DO
IT. ONLY ONE OF YOU HAS RESPONDED
TO MY REQUEST TO MEET AND TO DISCUSS THE GENOCIDE AT HAND
AND THAT IS SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN.
I WELCOME ALL OF YOU TO COME TO LIMA AND TO SEE WHAT WE'RE
ABOUT TO SEE WHAT WE'RE DOING AND SEE WHAT WE'RE BUILDING SO
YOU CAN JOIN US. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
. >> GOOD EVENING.
I AM A CITY EMPLOYEE. A MEMBER OF I HAVE TPL 21 AND A
PART OF RAINBOW FAMILY ACTION. >> I'M HERE TO SPEAK ON BEHALF
OF MYSELF AND ALL OF OUR FAMILIES SUPPORTING SUPERVISORS
CHAN'S RESOLUTION. AS A PERSON WITH A DISABILITY I
KNOW THE DIRECT ACTIONS OF THE POWERFUL CAN DETERMINE WHOSE
LIVES ARE DEEMED WORTHY AND ABLE TO ACCESS LIFE OR
DEATH HEALTH CARE. GENDER DIVERSE KIDS ARE WORTHY
. I WISH SHE COULD HAVE BEEN
IN ALL OF HER NURSERY ROOMS. WHEN OUR CHILD DECLARED WHO
THEY ARE FIRST TO THE DOG OR TO OR THREW PARTY TRAINING BOOKS
BEFORE THEY KNEW THE RIGHT TERMS FOR ANATOMY IF ONLY YOU
WERE THERE AT PRESCHOOL WHEN THEY WERE THAT PRINCESS DRESS
OR JUMPED UNDER THE PARACHUTE WITH THE BOYS YOU MISSED THE
FAMILY DINNER WHEN OUR NON-BINARY PRE-TEEN RETOLD
COURAGEOUSLY USING THEY THEM PRONOUNS AT SCHOOL FOR THE
FIRST TIME. >> YOU WEREN'T IN GRANDMA'S CAR
WHEN OUR TEENS SPOKE THEIR TRUTH ON LIVING STEALTH BECAUSE
ULTIMATELY IT WAS UNDER THEIR CLOTHES IS NO ONE ELSE'S
BUSINESS. >> BUT MOST OF ALL I WISH YOU
WERE IN THE EXAM ROOM WITNESSING THE ELATED RELIEF ON
THEIR FACE THEIR FIRST HORMONE TREATMENT.
NO ONE ELSE UNDERSTANDS MORE THAN THE MEDICAL CARE TEAM THAT
HAVE KNOWN THEM FOR YEARS AND ARE SERVING OUR YOUTH
DAILY. GENDER DIVERSE KIDS ARE STRONG.
>> WHEN OTHERS DON'T UNDERSTAND OR AGREE WITH WHO THEY ARE
STAYING TRUE TO THEMSELVES WHEN THEY LOSE FRIENDSHIPS FAITH,
COMMUNITY OR FAMILY RELATIONSHIPS AFTER COMING OUT
WE NEED THE POWERFUL IN THIS CITY TO BE AS COURAGEOUS AS OUR
YOUTH AND STAND UP FOR ACCESS TO TRANSGENDER HEALTH CARE FOR
DOCTORS, TRANS BIPOC CHILDREN OF SAN FRANCISCO AND FAMILIES
FROM OTHER STATES WHO HAVE SUFFERED BY LOSING LOCAL ACCESS
OR ACCESS TO CARE IS AT RISK AND WE NEED YOUR POWERFUL
SUPPORT BEHIND US TO SHOW THAT THAT WOULD MIGHT SHATTER THE
LARGER HOSPITAL CLINICS WHEN THEY CLOSE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. HELLO.
>> THANK YOU ALL. I'LL BE READING SOMETHING I PUT
TOGETHER AND I JUST WANT TO BE CLEAR THAT I'M HERE ON MY OWN
TIME IN PERSONAL CAPACITY. SO THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN
FOR THIS RESOLUTION. I RISE IN SUPPORT OF ITEM FOUR
A 49 AFFIRMING SAN FRANCISCO COMMITMENT TO TRANS FOLKS
AND ACCESS TO HEALTH CARE. >> MY NAME IS SHANE ZALDIVAR.
I WORK FOR THE OFFICE OF TRANSGENDER INITIATIVES.
I'M A TRANS WOMAN AND COMMUNITY ADVOCATE AND ARTIST THAT HAS
SERVED THE CITY FOR FIVE YEARS AND HAS BEEN DOING ART WITH THE
CITY FOR OVER TEN YEARS AS THE POP UP DRAG QUEEN AT THE FERRY
BUILDING AS WELL AS BEING WITH THE COMPTON'S CAFETERIA RIOT
PLAY PUT ON BY THE TENDERLOIN MUSEUM HONORING TRANS WOMEN OF
COLOR WHO MADE TRANS MOVEMENT POSSIBLE HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO
. SO SAN FRANCISCO IS HOME TO THE
ONLY TRANS GENDER GOVERNMENT OFFICE IN THE WORLD AND THE
OFFICE OF TRANSGENDER INITIATIVES IS GOING THROUGH A
MOMENT OF DIMINISHMENT AND CHANGE THAT I WANT TO MAKE
SURE IS PERTINENT TO YOUR ROLES AS SUPERVISORS AND LEADERSHIP.
WHILE THE CITY REAFFIRMS ITS VALUES THROUGH RESOLUTIONS LIKE
THIS ONE, BUDGET DECISIONS ARE DIMINISHING.
OTIS LEE AND CUTTING FUNDING TO COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS THAT
PROVIDE DIRECT LIFESAVING SERVICES.
THESE ARE NOT ABSTRACT DECISIONS.
THEY ARE DIRECT. THEY ARE DIRECTLY IMPACTING
CARE SAFETY AND SURVIVAL AND THEY ARE INDEED DECISIONS.
>> SAN FRANCISCO'S HISTORY DEMANDS FOR TRANS WOMEN
PARTICULARLY TRANS WOMEN OF COLOR BUILT THE FOUNDATION THAT
ALLOWS ME TO STAND HERE TODAY. THEIR LEADERSHIP HAS LAID THE
GROUNDWORK FOR PROTECTIONS ACROSS THE ENTIRE LGBTQ PLUS
COMMUNITY. AND SO WHILE THIS RESOLUTION IS
EXTREMELY IMPORTANT AND WE WANT SAN FRANCISCO LEADERSHIP TO
STAND AND SAY WHAT IT'S SAYING FOR COMMUNITY, WE NEED THAT THE
DECISIONS MADE BY PUBLIC ELECTED OFFICIALS TO REFLECT
THEIR SUPPORT AND RELATIONSHIP. >> WE FEEL THESE.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER READING SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS WREN SCHAEFER. THEY THEN AND I AM A MEMBER OF
INDIVISIBLE WHO MOVED TO THE RICHMOND NEIGHBORHOOD OF SAN
FRANCISCO FROM THE UNITED STATES SOUTH JUST AT THE
BEGINNING OF COVID. AS A TRANS PERSON WHO FOUND
REFUGE HERE IT'S HEARTENING TO SEE A SUPERVISOR I VOTED FOR
SPONSOR ITEM 49 MAKING AN ATTEMPT TO COUNTER THE INSANE
CIRCUMSTANCE OF HOSPITALS DENYING CARE SUPPORTED BY
DOCTORS AND SCIENCE MAKING THEIR DECISIONS INSTEAD BASED
ON FASCISTIC MORAL PANICS AND SCAPEGOATING.
AS SOMEONE WHO EXPERIENCED SUICIDE IDEATION IN MY TEENS
FROM FAILURE TO FIND CARE THAT I DIDN'T KNOW EXISTED, I'D LIKE
TO HOPE THAT SAN FRANCISCO CAN TAP INTO THE HISTORY THAT MADE
THIS CITY A BEACON OF EQUALITY AND PROGRESS AND GUIDE THE REST
OF THE COUNTRY IN PASSING SIMILAR INITIATIVES OF CARING
SO THAT SUCH STANDARDS CAN ALSO BE EXTENDED TO MY SIBLINGS
IN THE SOUTH. I'D LIKE TO ADD MY SUPPORT FOR
ITEM 51 AND FOR PREVIOUS STATEMENTS SUPPORTING TRANS
SANCTUARY ORDINANCES AND FORCING AN END TO
MAYOR LURIE'S ASSOCIATED HIRING FREEZES TO MAKE THESE ACTIONS
MORE SUBSTANTIAL. THANK YOU FOR YOUR
CONSIDERATION. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
SUPERVISORS. >> MY NAME IS BEVERLY
LITTLETON. I'M A SUMMER RESIDENT ORGANIZER
WITH INDIVISIBLE SAN FRANCISCO AND A TRANSGENDER WOMAN.
WE SUPPORT SUPERVISORS CHEN'S RESOLUTION AS A WONDERFUL FIRST
STEP. I NEED PROGESTERONE OR I GET
DEPRESSION. I NEED ESTROGEN OR MY BONES
START TO CRUMBLE. I NEED A GENDER AFFIRMING
SURGERY TO LIVE A SAFE LIFE WITHOUT GENDER DYSPHORIA.
AND I GOT IT IN THE BAY AREA. ADULTS AND CHILDREN LIKE ME
NEED CLINICS TO STAY OPEN. SAN FRANCISCO IS SUPPOSED TO BE
THE SHINING CITY ON A HILL WHERE RAINBOW REFUGEES FLEE THE
WHOLE WORLD WATCHES US AND FOLLOWS OUR EXAMPLE.
>> IN THIS TIME OUR REPUTATION AND THE LIVES OF OUR TRANS
POPULATION ARE AT STAKE. THE CITY CAN CHOOSE TO USE ITS
POWER TO HELP THE TRANS COMMUNITY.
I HAVE SOME SUGGESTIONS. UPGRADE THE TRANS SANCTUARY
RESOLUTION TO A STRONGER TRANS SANCTUARY ORDINANCE.
>> ENFORCE OUR LAWS FOR SAN FRANCISCO HEALTH PROVIDERS WHO
OBEY AND ADVANCE. LET US ENFORCE THE LAWS WITH A
PRIVATE RIGHT TO ACTION FOR THAT NOT DENIAL OF GENDER
AFFIRMING CARE. MAKE IT POSSIBLE FOR US TO FILE
CIVIL SUIT FOR IMMINENT AND ACTUAL INJURY DUE TO THE
DENIAL OF GENDER AFFIRMING CARE.
SAY BY AN HMO COVER GENDER AFFIRMING CARE UNDER THE SAN
FRANCISCO HEALTH PLAN REGARDLESS OF FEDERAL ATTACKS.
BUDGET ADEQUATE FUNDS TO TRANS CARE.
>> HORMONE THERAPY AS YOU HEARD EARLIER.
SAVES MONEY WITH BETTER MENTAL HEALTH.
BETTER ECONOMIC PRODUCTIVITY AND FOR CHILDREN.
PREVENTS THE NECESSITY OF GENDER AFFIRMING SURGERIES.
FINALLY SUPPORT OUR PROVIDERS TO GIVE CARE TO OTHER STATES BY
TELEMEDICINE AND MAIL. >> I AM GLAD THAT ONE YEAR INTO
THIS DARK TIME THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS HAS TURNED ITS
ATTENTION TO HELPING THE TRANS COMMUNITY.
PLEASE WORK WITH OUR COMMUNITY LEADERS TO FOLLOW UP THIS
RESOLUTION WITH SUBSTANTIVE LEGISLATION.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. HI, I'M RACHEL SCARBOROUGH.
SHE HER PRONOUNS AND I'M GRATEFUL TO SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR
PUTTING THIS RESOLUTION FORWARD AND I HOPE TO SEE IT APPROVED
UNANIMOUSLY. >> I CAN SAY THAT TRANSITIONING
AND THE GENDER AFFIRMING CARE THAT I HAVE RECEIVED IN SAN
FRANCISCO HAS BEEN TRANSFORMATIVE TO ME.
I LIVE A HAPPIER LIFE, A FULLER LIFE AND I'M A BETTER PERSON
FOR IT. BUT IT WAS A LONG ROAD FOR ME
TO GET HERE. >> I GREW UP IN A DEEP
CONSERVATIVE AND RURAL AREA IN CALIFORNIA IN THE 80S.
AND AT THAT TIME IN PLACE THERE WAS NO SPACE FOR ME TO REALLY
UNDERSTAND MYSELF EVEN THOUGH DEEPLY INTERNALLY I KNEW WHAT I
WAS. >> AND WE SEE WHAT'S HAPPENING
NOW THAT WE HAVE AN ADMINISTRATION AT THE FEDERAL
LEVEL WHO WANTS WHO WANTS TO TAKE THE WORLD BACK TO THE
WORLD THAT I GREW UP IN. I HOPE THAT NO CHILD WOULD EVER
HAVE TO ENDURE WHAT I ENDURED TO GET WHERE I AM NOW.
I GOT LUCKY. I SURVIVED.
I MADE IT THROUGH. BUT THAT IS NOT THE OUTCOME FOR
MANY, MANY OTHERS. SO AGAIN I'M VERY HAPPY TO SEE
THIS RESOLUTION BEING PUT FORTH.
I HOPE TO SEE IT FOLLOWED UP WITH WITH ACTION AND FUNDS.
AND THAT'S ALL I'VE GOT TO SAY. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. >> WELCOME.
>> GOOD EVENING, EVERYBODY. I'M HERE TO COMMENT ON THE
GENDER AFFIRMING CARE FOR TRANS YOUTH.
MY NAME IS JOHN ALLMAN AND I'VE LIVED IN THE MISSION DISTRICT
FOR THE PAST 16 YEARS. I AM AGAINST THIS BILL WHICH OF
COURSE MEANS THAT I WAS BORN MALE AND HAVE ALWAYS IDENTIFIED
AS MALE. >> I AM ALSO A COMMITTED ALLY
TO THE TRANS WOMEN AND A BIG SUPPORTER OF PRO TRANS
LEGISLATION AND I AM A MEMBER OF THE NEW CIVIL SRF AND I'M A
VERY ACTIVE IN OUR LGBTQ WORKGROUP.
THE WORKGROUP ISN'T NECESSARILY FOCUSED THESE DAYS APPROACHING
ISSUES BECAUSE OUR FEDERAL GOVERNMENT IS WORKING SO HARD
TO RESTRICT OUR PERSONAL FREEDOMS ESPECIALLY THOSE OF
THE TRANS COMMUNITY. INDIVISIBLE ITSELF HAS A LARGE
MEMBERSHIP THAT WE CAN QUICKLY ORGANIZE TO PROVIDE SUPPORT FOR
ANY PRO TRANS THIS NATION. >> NOW ON A PERSONAL NOTE,
SEVERAL YEARS AGO I NEEDED TO GET TESTOSTERONE INJECTIONS
TWICE A WEEK BECAUSE I GUESS MY DOCTOR THOUGHT I WAS GETTING
FATIGUE EARLY. >> BUT SERIOUSLY AS A HORMONE
INJECTIONS ARE CONSIDERED TO BE GENDER AFFIRMING CARE, MY
INJECTIONS COULD BE DETERMINED TO BE ILLEGAL.
THIS ESPECIALLY APPLIES TO TRANS YOUTH WHO MAY BE IN THE
MIDDLE OF RECEIVING HORMONE THERAPY.
WHEN THE LAW IS PASSED POTENTIALLY CAUSING SEVERE
MEDICAL AND PSYCHOLOGICAL ISSUES WE MUST REMAIN VIGILANT.
MAKE NO MISTAKE THE CURRENT LAW MAY ONLY APPLY TO TEENAGERS
RIGHT NOW BUT IT'S PRETTY MUCH GUARANTEED THAT CONSERVATIVES
IN OUR GOVERNMENT WON'T STOP THERE BUT WILL EVENTUALLY TEND
TO EXPAND THE LAW TO REFUSE GENDER FROM CARE TO ANYONE
REGARDLESS OF AGE. THEY'RE VERY PROUD TO LIVE
IN SAN FRANCISCO AND APPRECIATE THAT WE HAVE PEOPLE LIKE
SUPERVISOR SHARED IN THEIR COMMITMENT TO PRIORITIZING
THESE ISSUES. >> THANK YOU FOR ALLOWING ME TO
SPEAK. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
WELCOME. I.
>> MY NAME IS VICTORIA LIANG. I AM A NURSE HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. I WORK AT KAISER AND A SUTTER B
AND C AND I'M HERE IN SUPPORT OF SUPERVISOR CHEN'S RESOLUTION
TO REAFFIRM SAN FRANCISCO'S COMMITMENT TO GENDER AFFIRMING
CARE FOR TRANSGENDER GENDER EXPENSIVE AND LGBTQ A PLUS
RATES. I'M SORT OF FRUSTRATED WITH HOW
BAD THE WORLD IS TODAY THAT HEALTH CARE THE HEALTH CARE OF
VULNERABLE COMMUNITIES ARE CONSTANTLY BEING UNDER ATTACK.
TRANS RIGHTS AFFECT EVERYONE AND I BELIEVE THAT HEALTH CARE
IS A HUMAN RIGHT, NOT A PRIVILEGE.
GENDER AFFIRMING CARE IS LIFE AFFIRMING LIFE SAVING CARE.
AND IT'S NOT JUST TRANSITION RELATED CARE AS PEOPLE HAVE
MENTIONED. GENDER AFFIRMING CARE AFFIRMS
THE EXPERIENCE OF ALL HEALTH CARE ENCOUNTERS.
TRANSGENDER FOLKS ARE ALREADY AT INCREASED RISK OF HAVING
JUST A HORRIBLE TIME AT THE DOCTOR'S OFFICE OR ANYWHERE
IN HEALTH CARE. SO WHY EXACERBATE WHY
EXACERBATE THESE ALREADY STRAINED RELATIONSHIPS BETWEEN
TRANS FOLKS AND THE HEALTH CARE SYSTEM?
WHY MAKE IT HARD FOR NURSES TO CARE FOR OUR PATIENTS?
WHAT WE NEED RIGHT NOW IS MORE CARE AND WE NEED MORE COURAGE
FROM THOSE OF US LIVING IN ANY FORM OF A PRIVILEGED BODY.
IF YOU'RE NOT STANDING UP FOR COMMUNITIES MORE MARGINALIZED
THAN YOU THEN WE THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO WE JUST WANT YOU
TO STEP ASIDE. SPEAKING UP IS THE LEAST I CAN
DO AND PASSING THIS RESOLUTION IS HONESTLY THE BARE MINIMUM
THAT YOU GUYS CAN DO. WE NEED MORE LEADERS TO GUIDE
US OUT OF THIS WRECKAGE OF AN ADMINISTRATION NOT MORE
SOLDIERS TO FALL IN LINE. AND I WAS BORN HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO AT THE SAME KAISER THAT I WORK IN RIGHT NOW AND I
WAS RAISED IN A SAN FRANCISCO THAT HAD THE SPIRIT OF EQUALITY
AND EXPANDED THE CIRCLE OF INCLUSION.
AND I LOVE THE CITY BECAUSE I FELT FREE TO GROW UP HERE AND I
WANT THAT FOR OUR FUTURE KIDS. AND WHAT DON'T YOU WANT TO BE
CARED FOR BY A NURSE WHO ACCEPTS YOU FOR WHO YOU ARE
TAKING AWAY HEALTH CARE FROM CHILDREN IS JUST UNNECESSARY
AND SHORTSIGHTED AND NOTHING REALLY SHOULD BE TAKEN AWAY.
WE SHOULD BE EXPANDING HEALTH CARE FOR EVERYONE AND SAN
FRANCISCO HAS THE OPPORTUNITY TO REMAIN A LEADER IN THE LGBTQ
PLUS RIGHTS AND WE SET THE STANDARD SO THANK YOU FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. THANK YOU.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD EVENING.
I'M TAB BUCKNER AND SAN FRANCISCO HAS TAKEN PRIDE
IN BEING A SANCTUARY CITY FOR OUR IMMIGRANT RESIDENTS.
BUT WE ALSO NEED TO MAKE SURE THAT THE SAME APPLIES TO OUR
TRANS SIBLINGS. MANY OF WHOM MOVED HERE TO
ESCAPE HOSTILE SURROUNDINGS. THE NATION'S TOXIC POLITICAL
CLIMATE HAS ALLOWED HUNDREDS OF ANTI-TRANS LEGISLATION TO BE
PASSED AROUND THE COUNTRY. THIS ONSLAUGHT HAS
UNFORTUNATELY CONTRIBUTED TO ELECTED OFFICIALS INCLUDING OUR
OWN GOVERNOR BACKED OFF ON TRANS RIGHTS AND EMBOLDENED THE
PRIVATE SECTOR TO RESTRICT OR COMPLETELY BAN SERVICES FOR THE
TRANS COMMUNITY. THIS CRISIS HAS SEVERELY
AFFECTED THE SECURITY MENTAL HEALTH AND QUALITY OF LIFE FOR
TRANS PEOPLE OF ALL AGES PARTICULARLY OUR YOUTH.
AS EXECUTIVES AND UPPER MANAGEMENT IN THE FOR PROFIT
HEALTH CARE INDUSTRY MAKE OBSCENE AMOUNTS OF MONEY, TRANS
PEOPLE EARN SIGNIFICANTLY LESS THAN THE AVERAGE AMERICAN
WORKER AND A DISPROPORTIONATE AMOUNT OF UNHOUSED YOUTH HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO ARE TRANS. >> IT IS IMPERATIVE THAT ALL
SUPPORT SERVICES INCLUDING HEALTH CARE ARE ACCESSIBLE TO
ALL OF TRANS RESIDENTS THAT WE HAVE HERE INCLUDING CRITICAL
GENDER AFFIRMING CARE THAT HAS BECOME INCREASINGLY DIFFICULT
TO OBTAIN EVEN HERE IN THE BAY AREA.
THE TRANS COMMUNITY HAS HISTORICALLY MADE AND CONTINUES
TO MAKE ENORMOUS CONTRIBUTIONS TO SAN FRANCISCO'S CULTURAL
FABRIC AND LIVELIHOOD. PLEASE IMPLEMENT SUPERVISOR'S
TRANS RESOLUTION TO PUT OUR CITY ON RECORD WITH A FIRM
COMMITMENT TO ENSURE THE SAFETY, FREEDOM, HEALTH
AND WELL-BEING OF OUR TRANS COMMUNITY.
AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR YOUR AUTHOR AUTHORING.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WE WILL COME OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> MEMBERS OF WHAT WERE
SUPERVISORS AND MAYOR OFFICES OF SAN FRANCISCO TWO WEEKS AGO
I SAW A MOVIE ELEMENTARY ON ROSEMEAD.
THE LEADING ACTRESS LUCY LIU I SAW HER THE POSTER AT LAST TWO
FULL HOURS TO WATCH HER. SHE IS NOT ONLY AN IDEAL
ACTRESS BUT SHE'S MY HERO. >> I'M HERE TO REPORT THE
FINDING OF WHAT THE MOVIE WAS ABOUT.
IT WAS ABOUT A MOM, IRENE AND HER SON JOE.
WHEN JOE WAS A FRESHMAN, HIS DAD DIED OF CANCER AND AS HE
APPROACHES 18 IT'S VERY APPARENT THAT HE HAS
SCHIZOPHRENIA. >> AND SO UPON APPROVAL FROM
HIS HIGH SCHOOL THEY HAVE A HEART STICKER, A DRILL TO TO
AFFIRM THAT HE IS NOT MENTALLY STABLE AND THEY OFFER HELP TO
SUPPORT HIS SON. BUT IRENE BECAUSE THERE'S SUCH
A STIGMA ATTACHED TO MENTAL HEALTH ESPECIALLY TO ASIAN
COMMUNITY SHE DECIDED IT MATTERS TO HER OWN HAND.
ON HIS 18TH BIRTHDAY. HE DECIDED TO END HIS LIFE JUST
BEFORE HE SHOOT HIM TWICE IN A CHEST CALL HIS BEST FRIEND IS
THAT CAN YOU PLEASE OPEN ORDER PHOTOS BECAUSE I WISH TO BE
FORGOTTEN. WELL, TOWARD THE END SHE DID
NOT END HER LIFE BECAUSE SHE WENT TO PUNISH HERSELF.
BUT BECAUSE OF LUCY LIU'S GREAT ACTRESS HER STORIES LIVE ON.
I MYSELF AM VERY GRATEFUL TO HAVE A CHANCE TO LEND MY VOICE
TO THE PUBLIC. JUST YESTERDAY IN OUR MASS I
ACQUIRE SPACE X AS WELL AS I. I AM HUGE AFFIRMED I AM A CHIEF
SOFTWARE ARCHITECT OF A.I. AND I JUST SPOKE TO TONY
ROBBINS. AND WHAT TONY ROBBINS SAID AS A
GIFT COULD NOT BE COULD ONLY BE CREATED.
I'M HERE TO CONTINUE MY VOICE ESPECIALLY IN ASIAN COMMUNITY
AND BEYOND. >> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HELLO SUPERVISORS. THANK YOU FOR HEARING US.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD FOR
INITIATIVE 51. >> I WAS WITH YOU AT THE
FILLMORE NEIGHBORHOOD CLEANUP THIS SATURDAY.
>> MY NAME IS JULIE CHUNG OR JULIE TRAN.
I USE XI THAT XI THEY PRONOUNS. >> I'M AN ALLY TO OUR TRANS
FRIENDS. I SEE YOU AND YOU MATTER TO ME
. >> AND I WAS ALSO DISPLACED
FROM 50 GOLDEN GATE AVENUE AND I AM HERE IN SUPPORT OF
ITEM 51. I WAS NOT PLANNING TO SPEAK
TODAY BECAUSE I AM ONE OF THE LUCKY FEW.
>> I AM ONE OF THE LUCKY FEW WHO HAVE BEEN APPROVED FOR A
TEMPORARY HOUSING FOR A TEMPORARY HOUSING SUBSIDY.
>> I AM STILL UNHOUSED THOUGH I HAVE BEEN HOTEL HOPPING
AND COUCH SURFING FOR OVER A MONTH NOW.
I CAME TODAY IN SOLIDARITY AND IN COMMUNITY WITH MY
NEIGHBORS WHO WERE DENIED HOUSING ASSISTANCE.
>> I LIVED AT 50 GOLDEN GATE AVENUE FOR NEARLY TWO DECADES
AND I'VE GOTTEN TO KNOW MY DEAR NEIGHBORS DURING THESE YEARS.
>> WITHOUT NAMING NAMES, I WOULD LIKE TO SHARE SOME OF
THEIR OCCUPATION AND CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO. MY NEIGHBORS ARE OR WERE A
GARDENER IN GOLDEN GATE PARK, A SERVER IN THE CASTRO A CASHIER
IN SOMA WORKERS IN THE DESIGN DISTRICT IN MISSION BAY AS A
TRAVEL AGENT. >> SECURITY GUARDS
AND STAGEHANDS IN THE THEATER DISTRICT.
>> I STAND HERE NOT SO MUCH FOR MYSELF BUT FOR THEM.
>> I STAND HERE TO ASK YOU THIS IS SAN FRANCISCO A SANCTUARY
CITY ONLY FOR TECH COMPANIES WITH TAX BREAKS FOR PEOPLE
LIVING, DEALING, USING ON THE STREETS AND THE SIDEWALKS AND
EXCUSE MY LANGUAGE. >> OR IS SAN FRANCISCO A
SANCTUARY CITY FOR THE WORKING MIDDLE CLASS TO.
>> IF SANCTUARY IF SAN FRANCISCO IS TRULY A SANCTUARY
CITY FOR ALL THEN I URGE YOU TO SAY TO ITEM 51 THANK YOU FOR
YOUR TIME THIS EVENING. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
>> HI SUPES. MY NAME IS SYDNEY SIMPSON WITH
THE CALIFORNIA NURSES ASSOCIATION EXECUTIVE BOARD OF
THE SAN FRANCISCO LABOR COUNCIL AND CO-FOUNDER OF THE HARVEY
MILK CLUB TRANS CAUCUS. BIG THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR
CHAN FOR SPONSORING THIS RESOLUTION FOR US.
AND I'M GOING TO TAKE UP A LITTLE MORE OF YOUR TIME TO ASK
YOU WHAT WE CAN DO NEXT. UM, I WANT TO MAKE MYSELF
AVAILABLE TO YOU AS WELL AS ALL OF OUR PARTNERS IN LABOR
COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS, DEMOCRATIC CLUBS AND THE 300
FAMILIES OF RAINBOW FAMILIES. UM, WE'RE AVAILABLE TO YOU FOR
CONVERSATION ON HOW WE CAN TANGIBLY SUPPORT THIS COMMUNITY
WITH LEGISLATION. I THINK WE CAN START WITH
RESPONDING AND SCHEDULING A CONVERSATION WITH JIM FROM LA
AND MARTIN THAT SEEMS LIKE A REASONABLE PLACE TO START
AND WE LOOK FORWARD TO HEARING HOW THAT CONVERSATION GOES.
KAISER LITERALLY PAYS ME TO FIGURE OUT HOW TO IMPROVE THE
QUALITY OF CARE FOR OUR TRANS PATIENTS.
>> SO AS THEY ACTIVELY STRIP SERVICES AWAY FROM THEM I WOULD
LOVE TO USE THAT TIME TO FIGURE OUT HOW TO GET THIS LIFESAVING
CARE TO THESE PATIENTS BY ANY CREATIVE MEANS NECESSARY.
AND I THINK YOU ALL COULD PROBABLY HELP ME WITH THAT.
WE'RE VERY INTERESTED IN WAYS WE CAN BACKFILL OUR FUNDING FOR
OUR PROGRAMS, SUPPORT OUR TRANS RESIDENTS IN TANGIBLE WAYS SO
WE AREN'T GOING ANYWHERE. WE AREN'T GOING AWAY.
AND I LOOK FORWARD TO HEARING MORE FROM YOU.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
ALL RIGHT. ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF
THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING
GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT? >> PLEASE STEP UP.
ALL RIGHT. MR. PRESIDENT, PUBLIC COMMENT
IS NOW CLOSED. >> MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR
FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA ITEMS 49
THROUGH 54 ITEMS 49 THROUGH 54 WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION
BUT WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE.
A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED FOR FOR ADOPTION OF A
RESOLUTION ON FIRST APPEARANCE TODAY.
ALTERNATIVELY A MEMBER MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST
APPEARANCE TO GO TO COMMITTEE. >> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD I DO
REQUEST SEVERING I AM 51 AND 52 PLEASE.
>> SUPERVISOR WALTON PLEASE SEVER ITEM 53.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR I'D LIKE TO BE ADDED AS A CO-SPONSOR TO
49 AND 51 PLACE NOTED SUPERVISOR CHIN SEVER 49.
OKAY. >> ALL RIGHT.
SO MADAM CLERK ON ITEMS 5054 AND 54 CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE
ROLL ON ITEMS 50 AND 54? >> SUPERVISOR WALTON I WALTON I
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISE HER CHIN I CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I SUPERVISOR DORSI DORSI I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN I MANDEL MAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
I AND SUPERVISOR SAUDER SAUTER EITHER ARE TONIGHT WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 49 ITEM 49 RESOLUTION TO
REAFFIRM SAN FRANCISCO'S COMMITMENT TO THE RIGHTS OF ITS
TRANSGENDER GENDER NONCONFORMING INTERSEX PERSON
TO SPIRIT RESIDENTS AND EMPLOYEES TO OBTAIN GENDER
AFFIRMING CARE WITHOUT DISCRIMINATION AND STRONGLY
URGE HEALTH CARE PROVIDERS AND INSURANCE CARRIERS
OPERATING WITHIN THE CITY TO ADHERE TO STATE AND LOCAL LAWS
MANDATING ACCESS TO MEDICALLY NECESSARY HEALTH CARE INCLUDING
GENDER AFFIRMING CARE. >> SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MENDOZA AND I DO WANT TO FIRST THANK RAINBOW FAMILIES
AND THE AND AS WELL AS HARVEY MILK DEMOCRATIC CLUB
SPECIFICALLY TRANS CAUCUS FOR THEIR REALLY GUIDANCE
AND SUPPORT ON THIS RESOLUTION AND I COLLEAGUES I ALSO WANT TO
THANK YOU BECAUSE OF YOU AND BECAUSE OF SAN FRANCISCO
THAT I HAVE NO DOUBT TO BE ABLE TO INTRODUCE THIS RESOLUTION
AND TO TRUST THAT IT IS NOT CONTROVERSIAL THAT WE CAN PUT
THIS ON ADOPTION WITHOUT REFERENCE TO COMMITTEE AND THAT
IT WILL BE UNANIMOUSLY APPROVED .
BUT I DO WANT TO ARTICULATE THAT THIS IS A MOMENT WHERE AS
I WANT TO BE BEFORE YOU ABOUT THIS CLAUSE AS SPECIFICALLY
AMENDMENT THAT IS PUT BEFORE YOU TODAY ON PAGE FIVE
AND HIGHLIGHTING A MOMENT WHY IS SO DEAR FRIEND AND WHY WE
HAVE TO DO THIS RESOLUTION AND AT THIS MOMENT AND THAT IS
ON PAGE FIVE TO ADD THIS CLAUSE FURTHER RESOLVE THAT THE BOARD
OF SUPERVISORS HEREBY DIRECTS THE CLERK OF THE BOARD TO SEND
A COPY OF THIS RESOLUTION TO LEADERSHIP OF SUTTER HEALTH
KAISER PERMANENTE UNIVERSITY OF SAN FRANCISCO HEALTH
AND STANFORD MEDICINE. THAT BEING THE REASON BEING IS
IS THAT THESE HEALTH CARE SERVICE PROVIDER ARE HALTING
VERY CRITICAL GENDER AFFIRMING CARE FOR OUR YOUTH AS THEIR
THEIR RESPONSE TO THE THREATS FROM THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION
WHICH IS NOT NECESSARY BECAUSE BOTH THE STATE AND LOCAL LAW
PROTECT THEM TO PROVIDE THIS CARE AND YET HERE WE ARE WE
HAVE LEARNED FROM THE RING BOTH FAMILIES AND MANY HAVE ACTUALLY
PUSHED BACK ON SUTTER HEALTH AND SUCCESSFULLY BE ABLE TO
PUSH BACK ON SUTTER HAVE TO CONTINUE TO PROVIDE THAT CARE
BUT WE KNOW THAT THE FIGHT IS NOT OVER IS THE REASON WHY DOES
SAN FRANCISCO SUPERVISOR HAVE TO INTRODUCE IN PASS THIS
RESOLUTION TO SHOW THAT IN SOLIDARITY WE DO WANT OUR
HEALTH CARE SERVICE PROVIDER TO PROVIDE US CARE AND TO ALSO
REMIND THEM THEY ARE OPERATING AND DOING BUSINESS IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND THAT WE WILL THEY WILL FACE PUSHBACK SHOULD THEY
NOT PROVIDE THIS CARE. I THINK THAT IS A STRONG
STANCE. HOWEVER, AS YOUR BUDGET
COMMITTEE CHAIR I ALSO WANTED TO RECOMMIT OURSELVES AND IN
THIS UPCOMING BUDGET AND I DO WANT TO FLAG FOR YOU THAT TWO
YEARS AGO, TWO FISCAL YEARS AGO WE HAVE A BLEAK BALANCE
AND BALANCE AND BALANCE AND YOU KNOW, HEARING WHICH MEANS THAT
THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH IS GOING TO CUT ROUGHLY ABOUT
$17 MILLION AND THAT TIME WHILE WE APPROVE THAT REDUCTION IT
WASN'T CLEAR TO US EXACTLY WHAT WILL BE CUT AS WE'RE LEARNING.
I THINK THAT AS WE'RE LEARNING MORE AND FROM DIRECTOR DAN SIPE
ABOUT WHAT IS BEING CUT, I CERTAINLY HOPE THAT THROUGH
THOSE CONVERSATION THAT BOTH THE MAYOR AND HIS DEPARTMENT OF
PUBLIC HEALTH WILL RECONSIDER SOME OF THESE CUTS THAT
IMPACTING OUR TRANSGENDER COMMUNITY IN OUR LGBT COMMUNITY
THROUGH THROUGH THE BUDGET PROCESS.
>> SO WITH THAT SAID, COLLEAGUES, I HOPE TO AMEND
THIS RESOLUTION AND AS I READ OUT LOUD WITH THIS ADDITIONAL
CLAUSE AND I HOPE TO HAVE YOUR SUPPORT SUPERVISOR JANICE MADE
A MOTION AND SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR DORSEY AND I THINK
WE CAN TAKE THAT MOTION WITHOUT OBJECTION.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION. THE MOTION PASSES.
>> AND THEN ON THE AMENDED RESOLUTION I THINK WE CAN TAKE
THAT SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE AMENDED
RESOLUTION PASSES AS AMENDED. ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, PLEASE
CALL ITEM 51. >> ITEM 51 THIS IS A RESOLUTION
TO URGE THE CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO TO STRENGTHEN FIRE
DISPLACED DISPLACEMENT RESPONSE SYSTEMS AND PREVENT NEWLY
DISPLACED RESIDENTS FROM BECOMING HOMELESS.
>> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD COLLEAGUES I WANT TO START BY
SINCERELY THANKING THE TENANTS OF 50 GOLDEN GATE AND COMMUNITY
ADVOCATES WHO CAME OUT TODAY AND OVER THE PAST WEEKS FOR
CONTINUING TO SHARE THEIR EXPERIENCES.
THIS RESOLUTION WAS CALLED FOR IN LIGHT OF THE DISPLACED
RESIDENTS AFTER A THREE ALARM FIRE AT 50 GOLDEN GATE
IN DECEMBER. SINCE THEN, AS WE'VE HEARD
DURING TESTIMONY TODAY, WE'VE HEARD FROM PARENTS WHO ARE
CARING FOR NEWBORNS WITHOUT STABLE SHELTER FROM FAMILIES
WHO HAVE BEEN FORCED TO SLEEP IN CARS, SHELTERS OR ROTATE
BETWEEN COUCHES JUST BLOCKS FROM THIS BUILDING THAT WE'RE
IN RIGHT NOW. WE'VE HEARD FROM RESIDENTS WHO
DID EVERYTHING RIGHT, PAID THEIR RENT, WORKED, SAID
RESPONSIBLY AND STILL FOUND THEMSELVES FALLING THROUGH THE
CRACKS AFTER A FIRE. >> SEVERAL SPEAKERS TODAY
HIGHLIGHTED HOW CURRENT INCOME AND ASSET THRESHOLDS EXCLUDE
WORKING FAMILIES WHO ARE NOT WEALTHY BUT ARE PENALIZED FOR
HAVING MODEST SAVINGS SET ASIDE FOR MEDICAL CARE, EMERGENCIES
OR RETIREMENT. OTHERS SPOKE ABOUT LANGUAGE
BARRIERS, UNDERSTAFFING AND THE EMOTIONAL TOLL OF NAVIGATING A
COMPLEX SYSTEM WHILE TRAUMATIZED AND DISPLACED.
WE ALSO HEARD HOW RESIDENTS WERE LEFT TO ORGANIZE FOOD,
DIAPERS, TRANSPORTATION AND HOUSING SEARCHES ON THEIR
OWN, RELYING ON MUTUAL AID AND COMMUNITY GROUPS RATHER
THAN A COORDINATED CITY RESPONSE.
THAT SHOULD CONCERN ALL OF US. I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE WORK
THAT FRONTLINE STAFF AND COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS
HAVE DONE UNDER VERY DIFFICULT CIRCUMSTANCES.
AT THE SAME TIME, THE TESTIMONY TODAY MAKES CLEAR THAT OUR
CURRENT SYSTEMS ARE NOT BUILT TO MEET THE SCALE OR DURATION
OF DISPLACEMENT THAT FIRES ARE CAUSING IN SAN FRANCISCO TODAY
. THIS RESOLUTION EXISTS BECAUSE
OF THE PEOPLE WHO SPOKE TODAY REFLECTS WHAT THEY TOLD US WE
NEED MORE STAFFING, CLEARER SUPPORT, FAIRER ELIGIBILITY
RULES AND LANGUAGE ACCESS THAT ACTUALLY WORKS IN PRACTICE.
>> NO FAMILY DISPLACED BY FIRE SHOULD BE PUSHED CLOSER TO
HOMELESSNESS SIMPLY BECAUSE OUR SYSTEMS ARE TOO RIGID OR TOO
UNDER-RESOURCED. >> THE STORIES WE HEARD TODAY
ARE EXACTLY WHY THIS BODY NEEDS TO ACT.
I'M GRATEFUL TO EVERY TENANT AND ADVOCATE WHO CAME AND TOOK
THE TIME TO SHOW UP TO RELIVE PAINFUL EXPERIENCES AND TO
DEMAND BETTER FROM THEIR CITY. YOUR VOICES ARE SHAPING THIS
POLICY AND THEY DESERVE TO BE MET WITH ACTION.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISORS CHEN CHAN, DORSEY AND MELGAR FOR
YOUR CO-SPONSORSHIP. COLLEAGUES I HOPE TO HAVE YOUR
SUPPORT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS
ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
52. >> ITEM 52 IS A RESOLUTION TO
SUPPORT CALIFORNIA STATE ASSEMBLY BILL NUMBER 1633 WHICH
SEEKS TO ESTABLISH THE PRIVATE DETENTION FACILITY TAX LAW TO
IMPOSE AN ANNUAL TAX ON PRIVATE DETENTION FACILITY OPERATORS
AND DIRECT REVENUES TO THE DUE PROCESS FOR ALL FUND TO SUPPORT
IMMIGRATION RELATED SERVICES AND TO REAFFIRM SAN FRANCISCO'S
COMMITMENT TO IMMIGRANT RIGHTS. DUE PROCESS AND COMMUNITY
WELL-BEING. >> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD.
>> THANK YOU PRESIDENT. TODAY WE'RE VOTING ON A
RESOLUTION TO SUPPORT ASSEMBLYMEMBER MATT HANEY'S HB
1633 LEGISLATION THAT ADDRESSES THE GROWING ROLE OF PRIVATE
CORPORATIONS PROFITING FROM IMMIGRANT DETENTION WHILE
FAMILIES ARE SEPARATED AND COMMUNITIES DESTABILIZE
PRIVATE DETENTION OPERATORS CONTINUE TO GENERATE REVENUE
FROM ICE FUNDED FACILITIES. HB 1633 WOULD IMPOSE A 50%
GROSS RECEIPTS TAX ON PRIVATE DETENTION FACILITIES AND DIRECT
THE FUNDS TO THE DUE PROCESS FOR ALL FUND SUPPORTING LEGAL
SERVICES AND OTHER CRITICAL RESOURCES FOR IMMIGRANTS
AND THEIR FAMILIES. >> IT'S A STRAIGHTFORWARD IDEA.
IF COMPANIES PROFIT FROM DETENTION THEY SHOULD HELP PAY
FOR THE LEGAL AND COMMUNITY SUPPORT SYSTEMS THEIR PRACTICES
MAKE NECESSARY. SAN FRANCISCO'S LONG STOOD FOR
DUE PROCESS DIGNITY AND PROTECTING IMMIGRANT
COMMUNITIES. >> SUPPORTING THIS BILL IS
CONSISTENT WITH OUR VALUES AND OUR COMMITMENT TO JUSTICE.
I RESPECTFULLY ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT ON THIS RESOLUTION AS
WELL. >> AND WITH THAT LET'S TAKE
THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 53.
ITEM 53 RESOLUTION TO RECOGNIZE AND CELEBRATE BLACK HISTORY
MONTH DURING THE MONTH OF FEBRUARY 2026 IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO. >> SUPERVISOR WALTON.
>> THANK YOU PRESIDENT MENEM AND COLLEAGUES.
EVERY FEBRUARY WE TAKE THIS TIME TO REFLECT ON THE
ACHIEVEMENTS CONTRIBUTIONS AND RICH CULTURAL HERITAGE OF
BLACK AMERICANS BOTH IN OUR CITY AND ACROSS THE NATION.
I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE FORMER SUPERVISOR SOPHIE MAXWELL
AND DR. REVEREND AMOS BROWN FOR INITIATING THIS RESOLUTION AT
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. MANY YEARS AGO.
THANK YOU TO ALL THE MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR
SIGNING ON. FOR MANY OF US WE CELEBRATE
BLACK HISTORY EVERY DAY OF THE YEAR.
>> AS YOU KNOW, WE ARE NOW WITNESSING WIDESPREAD ATTACKS
ON DIVERSITY, EQUITY AND INCLUSION ACROSS THE
COUNTRY AS WELL AS EFFORTS ATTACKING COMMUNITIES OF COLOR.
THESE ARE NOT ATTACKS ON BLACK COMMUNITIES ONLY BUT ALSO OUR
IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES OUR AND TRANS GENDER COMMUNITIES,
PEOPLE WITH DISABILITIES, WOMEN AND MORE.
IT IS ABSOLUTELY IMPERATIVE THAT WE REMAIN CRITICAL
AND CONTINUE TO FIGHT FOR THE RIGHTS THAT THOSE WHO HAVE COME
BEFORE US HAVE FOUGHT SO HARD FOR.
THESE ROLLBACKS IN ERASURES OF HISTORY THREATEN HARD GAME
RIGHTS AND REINFORCES SYSTEMIC INEQUITIES THAT OUR ANCESTORS
AND CIVIL RIGHTS LEADERS FOUGHT TIRELESSLY TO DISMANTLE.
>> WE CANNOT SIMPLY CELEBRATE BLACK HISTORY.
WE MUST ACTIVELY DEFEND AND ADVANCE IT.
THAT MEANS CONTINUING TO FIGHT FOR JUSTICE, PUSHING BACK
AGAINST POLICIES THAT STRIP AWAY OUR RIGHTS AND DEMANDING
ACTION THAT UPLIFTS BLACK COMMUNITIES.
>> IN SAN FRANCISCO THAT MEANS INVESTING IN OUR BLACK
COMMUNITIES. IMPLEMENTING RECOMMENDATIONS
FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO REPARATIONS PLAN.
EXPANDING ACCESS TO QUALITY EDUCATION.
CREATING PATHWAYS FOR WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT.
AND SUPPORTING BLACK HOME OWNERSHIP.
AND ECONOMIC EMPOWERMENT. AS WE CELEBRATE BLACK HISTORY
MONTH. LET'S HONOR THE PAST BY SHAPING
A MORE JUST AND EQUITABLE FUTURE ONE WHERE PROGRESS IS
NOT ONLY RECOGNIZED BUT PROTECTED AND EXPANDED
ESPECIALLY IN OUR CURRENT TIMES .
WITH THAT SAID, I DO WANT TO HIGHLIGHT SOME BLACK HISTORY
MONTH CELEBRATIONS THAT WILL BE HOSTED AS AN OFFICE NEXT
WEDNESDAY FEBRUARY 11TH FROM 4 TO 6 P.M..
WE WILL BE HOSTING OUR ANNUAL BLACK HISTORY MONTH ART GALLERY
IN OUR OFFICE AND ROOM 279 FEATURING ART BY LOCAL BAYVIEW
ARTISTS MOLEX NF RUE WHO IS AN ARTIST WHO WAS BORN AND RAISED
IN DISTRICT TEN. >> THE REST OF US.
THANK YOU. ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR WALTON. WE CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> AND MADAM CLERK, DO WE HAVE
ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS? >> THERE ARE NONE TO REPORT.
MR. PRESIDENT, COULD YOU PLEASE READ THE IN MEMORIAM?
>> TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE
FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUAL. AT THE REQUEST OF BOARD
PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN TO BE ON BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS FOR S.F. GOV. TV'S FORMER BUT LONG TIME
PRODUCTION AND OPERATIONS SUPERVISOR OUR COLLEAGUE
MICHAEL B FREEMAN AND I BELIEVE THAT BRINGS US TO THE END OF
OUR AGENDA. MADAM CLERK, DO WE HAVE ANY
FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY?
>> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR TODAY.
>> THEN WE ARE ADJOURNED.